<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BATTANER_MORO_Elena_CLARIAH_ES__A_Distributed_Research_Infra">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>CLARIAH-ES: A Distributed Research Infrastructure for the Digital Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Battaner Moro</surname>
                        <forename>Elena</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, Spain (URJC)</affiliation>
                    <email>elena.battaner@urjc.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Estarrona Ibarloza</surname>
                        <forename>Ainara</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea (UPV/EHU)</affiliation>
                    <email>ainara.estarrona@ehu.eus</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Farwell</surname>
                        <forename>Aritz</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea (UPV/EHU)</affiliation>
                    <email>aritz.farwell@ehu.eus</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-15T15:56:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Digital Humanities</term>
                    <term>Research Infrastructures</term>
                    <term>Language Resources</term>
                    <term>Cultural Studies</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>digital libraries creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>natural language processing</term>
                    <term>Computer science</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <ref target="http://www.clariah.es">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-ES</hi>
                </ref> is a Spanish national research infrastructure that strengthens research and facilitates innovative approaches within the digital humanities. It is aligned with CLARIN and DARIAH, the two main European Research Infrastructure Consortia (ERIC) dedicated to the advancement of the social sciences and humanities. By integrating language technologies, text analysis, cultural heritage, and multilingual resources, CLARIAH-ES offers a unique ecosystem for scholars interested in exploring the Spanish, Catalan, Galician, and Basque languages and cultures. 
            </p>
            <p>CLARIAH-ES provides a range of DH resources for researchers by offering tools and data essential for conducting in-depth linguistic, cultural, and social studies and analyses. Designed to support a wide range of social sciences and humanities disciplines, CLARIAH-ES is tailored to meet the specific needs of scholars who rely on digital tools to examine cultural heritage and explore the rich linguistic landscape of Spain. Its distributed infrastructure delivers open-access and user-friendly resources that allow researchers to apply computational methods to SSH research in novel ways.</p>
            <p>DH tools and services provided through CLARIAH-ES are accessible through its multiple nodes, each contributing specialized resources for specific aspects of linguistic and cultural research. These nodes include:</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">1) Main libraries and repositories for Spanish and Ibero-American written, graphic, and audiovisual cultures:</hi>
                <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ref target="http://www.bne.es">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Biblioteca</hi>
                </ref>
                <ref target="http://www.bne.es">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Nacional de España</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (BNE)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">: The central depository for the Spanish bibliographic and documentary heritage that is produced within Spain and about Spain abroad in any type of support or medium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-UA</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: Home to the </hi>
                <ref target="https://www.cervantesvirtual.com/">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">Miguel de Cervantes Virtual Library</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">, a digital humanities center at the University of Alicante. The center is dedicated to the digital publication and dissemination of major classical Hispanic cultural heritage works. Its collections are organized into thematic and institutional portals and into libraries and author pages that provide the users with structured access to content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ref target="https://dialnet.unirioja.es/">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Dialnet</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">: A collaborative scientific repository that provides relevant and fundamental scientific information to researchers, universities, and the general public.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2) Digital Humanities and Language Technology research centers and groups:</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">2.1. Basque language and culture</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-EUS</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">: A distributed research infrastructure, made up of seventeen research groups and centers, that is designed to sustain investigation related to Basque or Basque culture by providing scholars with digital resources, including corpora, tools for language analysis, and Latxa, the largest LLM for Basque. The node is led by HiTZ, the Basque Center for Language Technology, which also houses CLARIAH-ES’s administrative office and a CLARIN B-Centre repository.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">2.2. Catalan language and culture</hi>
                <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-CAT</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: Led by the Language Technologies Unit at the </hi>
                <ref target="https://www.bsc.es/es">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">Barcelona Supercomputing Center</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (BSC), this node has developed a number of relevant open source resources, including LLMs and multilingual translation models, covering all languages of Spain, speech tools for Catalan, and an array of datasets for training and evaluating a variety of tasks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">2.3. Galician and Portuguese languages and cultures</hi>
                <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-GA</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">L: The Galician node is steered by the Instituto da Lingua Galega (</hi>
                <ref target="https://ilg.usc.gal/">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">ILG</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">) and the Centro Singular de Investigación en Tecnologías Inteligentes</hi>
                <ref target="https://citius.gal/gl/">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">(CiTIUS</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">), both located at the University of Santiago de Compostela. ILG develops corpora, databases, and digital lexicographic resources, as well as applications and tools for linguistic analysis for Galician and Portuguese.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">2.4. Spanish language and culture</hi>
                <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-AND</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: Led by the </hi>
                <ref target="https://sinai.ujaen.es/es/">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">SINAI</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> research group at the University of Jaén, CLARIAH-AND offers lexicons and data corpora oriented to diverse tasks, such as opinion analysis, emotion detection, classification of offensive texts, counter-narrative generation, and a corpus of social network conversations on mental disorders and addictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ref target="https://www.ucm.es/clariah-cm/">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-CM</hi>
                </ref>: A digital research infrastructure comprising the Community of Madrid’s six public universities. It counts with the universities’ bibliographic and research resources, as well as training and research programs. 
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-ES CSIC</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">: Located at the Center for Human and Social Sciences (CCHS) in Madrid, this node is composed of six research institutes and various technical-scientific infrastructures, including the Digital Humanities Laboratory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">CLARIAH-UNED</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: Working out of the Universidad Nacional de Educación a Distancia (UNED), it is composed of 1) the Laboratorio de Innovación en Humanidades Digitales (LINHD), an international research center for digital humanities that focuses on innovation, research, dissemination, consulting, and training for researchers, and 2) </hi>
                <ref target="https://www.uned.es/universidad/inicio/unidad/lenar.html">
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">LENAR</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">, a research center dedicated to natural language processing and information retrieval.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ref target="https://iatext.ulpgc.es/es">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">IATEXT</hi>
                </ref>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">: Located at the Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria), IATEXT offers numerous free resources for Spanish and classical languages (Latin and Greek), text analysis, search engines with linguistic intelligence, diachronic lexicon, performing arts, and Canary Island cultural heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These and other DH research resources will be presented in the poster session.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="color(212121)" style="font-size:9pt" xml:space="preserve">Carreras-Riudavets, F. J. / Estarrona, Ainara / Farwell, Aritz / Iruskieta, Mikel / Marco, Manuel / Melero, Maite / Montejo-Ráez, Arturo / Riaño, Daniel / Rigau, German / Romero, Dolores / Ros, Salvador / Sánchez, Elena / Sousa, Xulio. (2024). </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:9pt">“</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(212121)" style="font-size:9pt">CLARIAH-ES: Strategic Network for the Integration in the European Research Infrastructures in Social Sciences and Humanities</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">”</hi>
                        <hi rend="color(212121)" style="font-size:9pt">, in: Proceedings of the Seminar of the Spanish Society for Natural Language Processing: Projects and System Demonstrations (SEPLN-CEDI-PD 2024) co-located with the 7th Spanish Conference on Informatics (CEDI 2024), pages30-35.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
