<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FERREIRA_Beatriz_Barrocas_Investiga__o_aberta_e_Humanidades_">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Investigação aberta e Humanidades Digitais: tendências e evidência preliminares</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                        <forename>Beatriz Barrocas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidade de Coimbra, CEIS20</affiliation>
                    <email>b.ferreira@student.fl.uc.pt</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Borges</surname>
                        <forename>Maria Manuel</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidade de Coimbra, CEIS20</affiliation>
                    <email>mmb@fl.uc.pt</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-05-04T10:04:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Investigação aberta</term>
                    <term>humanidades digitais</term>
                    <term>práticas de investigação</term>
                    <term>scoping review</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>open access methods</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Introdução: </hi>No domínio da comunicação e da investigação académica, o discurso em torno da Investigação Aberta (OS) tem ganho crescente relevância, com a sua implementação ao nível de políticas de investigação. A OS está relacionada com o movimento de 
                <hi rend="italic">Open Science</hi>, que defende a transparência, acessibilidade e colaboração nos processos de investigação, com o intuito de democratizar o acesso ao conhecimento, tirando partido das potencialidades da tecnologia digital. Num esforço para promover a OS, têm sido desenvolvidas políticas de investigação que a determinam. No entanto, nem todas as culturas epistémicas adotam plenamente as práticas promovidas pela OS, como é o caso das Humanidades, uma vez que estas dependem das características epistemológicas e metodológicas de cada disciplina 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"mJ6GHWvO","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Arthur & Hearn, 2021, 2024; Kn\\uc0\\u246{}chelmann, 2019)","plainCitation":"(Arthur & Hearn, 2021, 2024; Knöchelmann, 2019)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":832,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/W3AVYB6S"],"itemData":{"id":832,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Open research represents a new set of principles and methodologies for greater cooperation, transparent sharing of findings, and access to and re-use of research data, materials or outputs, making knowledge more freely available to wider audiences for societal benefit. Yet, the future success of the international move toward open research will be dependent on key stakeholders addressing current barriers to increase uptake, effectiveness, and sustainability. This article builds on “An Agenda for Open Science in Communication,” raising dialog around the need for a broader view of open research as opposed to open science through a deeper understanding of specific challenges faced by the humanities. It reviews how the multifaceted nature of humanities research outputs make open communication formats more complex and costly. While new avenues are emerging to advance open research, there is a need for more collaborative, coordinated efforts to better connect humanities scholars with the communities they serve.","container-title":"Journal of Communication","DOI":"10.1093/joc/jqab028","ISSN":"0021-9916","issue":"5","journalAbbreviation":"Journal of Communication","page":"827-853","source":"Silverchair","title":"Toward Open Research: A Narrative Review of the Challenges and Opportunities for Open Humanities","title-short":"Toward Open Research","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1093/joc/jqab028","volume":"71","author":[{"family":"Arthur","given":"Paul Longley"},{"family":"Hearn","given":"Lydia"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2022",3,21]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2021",10,1]]}}},{"id":959,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/CAEF5YVK"],"itemData":{"id":959,"type":"book","abstract":"Offering new insights into promising ways to facilitate the uptake of open scholarship in the humanities, this open access book gives further shape to the digital humanities and the prospects of their future as part of a far more open and public world of scholarship.\n The book begins with the history of digital developments and their influence on the founding of international policies toward open scholarship. The concept of making research more freely available to the broader community, in practice, will require changes across every part of the system: government agencies, funders, university administrators, publishers, libraries, researchers and IT developers. To this end, the book sheds light on the urgent need for partnership and collaboration between diverse stakeholders to address multi-level barriers to both the policy and practical implementation of open scholarship. It also highlights the specific challenges confronted by the humanities which often makes their presentation in accessible open formats more costly and complex. Finally, the authors illustrate some promising international examples and ways forward for their implementation. The book ends by asking the reader to view their role as a researcher, university administrator, or member of government or philanthropic funding body, through new lenses. It highlights how, in our digital era, the frontiers through which knowledge is being advanced and shared can reshape the landscape for academic research to have the greatest impact for society.\n The eBook editions of this book are available open access under a CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 licence on bloomsburycollections.com. Open access was funded by Edith Cowan University.","edition":"1","ISBN":"978-1-350-23230-3","note":"DOI: 10.5040/9781350232303","publisher":"Bloomsbury Publishing Plc","source":"DOI.org (Crossref)","title":"Open scholarship in the humanities","URL":"https://doi.org/10.5040/9781350232303","author":[{"family":"Arthur","given":"Paul Longley"},{"family":"Hearn","given":"Lydia"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",2,1]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2024"]]}}},{"id":198,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5653137/items/BLQULXY8"],"itemData":{"id":198,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Open science refers to both the practices and norms of more open and transparent communication and research in scientific disciplines and the discourse on these practices and norms. There is no such discourse dedicated to the humanities. Though the humanities appear to be less coherent as a cluster of scholarship than the sciences are, they do share unique characteristics which lead to distinct scholarly communication and research practices. A discourse on making these practices more open and transparent needs to take account of these characteristics. The prevalent scientific perspective in the discourse on more open practices does not do so, which confirms that the discourse’s name, open science, indeed excludes the humanities so that talking about open science in the humanities is incoherent. In this paper, I argue that there needs to be a dedicated discourse for more open research and communication practices in the humanities, one that integrates several elements currently fragmented into smaller, unconnected discourses (such as on open access, preprints, or peer review). I discuss three essential elements of open science—preprints, open peer review practices, and liberal open licences—in the realm of the humanities to demonstrate why a dedicated open humanities discourse is required.","container-title":"Publications","DOI":"10.3390/publications7040065","ISSN":"2304-6775","issue":"4","journalAbbreviation":"Publications","language":"en","page":"65","source":"DOI.org (Crossref)","title":"Open Science in the Humanities, or: Open Humanities?","title-short":"Open Science in the Humanities, or","URL":"https://www.mdpi.com/2304-6775/7/4/65","volume":"7","author":[{"family":"Knöchelmann","given":"Marcel"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2022",1,9]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019",11,19]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Arthur &amp; Hearn, 2021, 2024; Knöchelmann, 2019). As Humanidades Digitais (HD) emergem como um campo interdisciplinar, funcionando como um 
                <hi rend="italic">cluster</hi> inclusivo, promovendo a colaboração e socialização entre disciplinas, e ampliando a análise de fenómenos culturais e sociais 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"gE4SdBlg","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Edmond & Lehmann, 2021; Fitzpatrick, 2012; Nyhan & Flinn, 2016)","plainCitation":"(Edmond & Lehmann, 2021; Fitzpatrick, 2012; Nyhan & Flinn, 2016)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":829,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/4BLFKQ67"],"itemData":{"id":829,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This article introduces a frame of reference for understanding the fundamental challenges that inform digital humanities as an interdisciplinary research area between arts, humanities, information, and computer science. Its conclusions are based upon the evidence base developed within an EU-funded collaboration known as Knowledge Complexity, or KPLEX for short (www.kplex-project.eu), in particular via the project's thirty-eight linked interviews about big data research. When viewed from the perspective of the digital humanities, five distinct points of `aporia' with a significant impact on digital humanities (DH) appear in this corpus, places where the interviewees explicitly or tacitly expose gulfs between the epistemic cultures that contribute to DH and that create tensions between these disciplines, even as they seek to collaborate. This article will explore these areas of apparent irreconcilability, and conclude with a series of reflections on howdigital humanities researchers might build upon their unique competency profile to negotiate within these critical conversations, in particular in the framework of the emerging subfield of critical digital humanities.","container-title":"Digital Scholarship in the Humanities","DOI":"10.1093/llc/fqab031","ISSN":"2055-7671","journalAbbreviation":"Digit. Scholarsh. Humanit.","language":"English","note":"publisher-place: Oxford\npublisher: Oxford Univ Press\nWOS:000756289000010","page":"95-108","source":"Web of Science Nextgen","title":"Digital humanities, knowledge complexity, and the five 'aporias' of digital research","URL":"https://gateway.webofknowledge.com/gateway/Gateway.cgi?GWVersion=2&SrcAuth=DynamicDOIArticle&SrcApp=WOS&KeyAID=10.1093%2Fllc%2Ffqab031&DestApp=DOI&SrcAppSID=F1q2rSgpzWEpNJYjMzz&SrcJTitle=DIGITAL+SCHOLARSHIP+IN+THE+HUMANITIES&DestDOIRegistrantName=Oxford+University+Press","volume":"36","author":[{"family":"Edmond","given":"Jennifer"},{"family":"Lehmann","given":"Joerg"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2022",3,21]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2021",10]]}}},{"id":969,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/T63FR5VZ"],"itemData":{"id":969,"type":"chapter","abstract":"A few months back, I gave a lunchtime talk called “Digital Humanities: Singular or Plural?” My title was in part a weak joke driven primarily by brain exhaustion. As I sat at the computer putting together my remarks, which were intended to introduce the field, I’d initially decided to title them “What Is Digital Humanities?” But then I thought “What Is the Digital Humanities?” sounded better, and I stared at the screen for a minute trying to decide if it should be “What Are the Digital Humanities?” In my precoffee, underslept haze, I honestly couldn’t tell which one was correct.","container-title":"Debates in the Digital Humanities","ISBN":"978-0-8166-7794-8","page":"12-15","publisher":"University of Minnesota Press","source":"JSTOR","title":"The humanities, done digitally","URL":"https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctttv8hq.5","author":[{"family":"Fitzpatrick","given":"Kathleen"}],"editor":[{"family":"Gold","given":"Matthew K."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2023",4,29]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2012"]]}}},{"id":987,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/LFEED7BR"],"itemData":{"id":987,"type":"book","collection-title":"Springer Series on Cultural Computing","event-place":"Cham","ISBN":"978-3-319-20169-6","note":"DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2","publisher":"Springer International Publishing","publisher-place":"Cham","source":"DOI.org (Crossref)","title":"Computation and the Humanities","URL":"http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2","author":[{"family":"Nyhan","given":"Julianne"},{"family":"Flinn","given":"Andrew"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2022",2,16]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Edmond &amp; Lehmann, 2021; Fitzpatrick, 2012; Nyhan &amp; Flinn, 2016). Neste estudo, consideramos as HD um espaço integrador para as diversas culturas epistémicas das humanidades, onde as práticas de investigação podem ser orientadas a contribuir para a consolidação da abertura e da interdisciplinaridade. Este estudo tem como objetivo apresentar os resultados preliminares de uma 
                <hi rend="italic">scoping review</hi>, cuja realização se justifica pela necessidade de identificar as características fundamentais das HD no contexto da OS. Esta abordagem revela-se particularmente apropriada para examinar a natureza, a extensão e o alcance da evidência disponível na literatura, permitindo não só mapear práticas existentes, como também identificar lacunas no conhecimento 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"lSZtn9DJ","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Arksey & O\\uc0\\u8217{}Malley, 2005; Colquhoun et al., 2014; Miake-Lye et al., 2016)","plainCitation":"(Arksey & O’Malley, 2005; Colquhoun et al., 2014; Miake-Lye et al., 2016)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1456,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/7BHR8GMJ"],"itemData":{"id":1456,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This paper focuses on scoping studies, an approach to reviewing the literature which to date has received little attention in the research methods literature. We distinguish between different types of scoping studies and indicate where these stand in relation to full systematic reviews. We outline a framework for conducting a scoping study based on our recent experiences of reviewing the literature on services for carers for people with mental health problems. Where appropriate, our approach to scoping the field is contrasted with the procedures followed in systematic reviews. We emphasize how including a consultation exercise in this sort of study may enhance the results, making them more useful to policy makers, practitioners and service users. Finally, we consider the advantages and limitations of the approach and suggest that a wider debate is called for about the role of the scoping study in relation to other types of literature reviews.","container-title":"International Journal of Social Research Methodology","DOI":"10.1080/1364557032000119616","ISSN":"1364-5579","issue":"1","note":"publisher: Routledge\n_eprint: https://doi.org/10.1080/1364557032000119616","page":"19-32","source":"Taylor and Francis+NEJM","title":"Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework","title-short":"Scoping studies","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1080/1364557032000119616","volume":"8","author":[{"family":"Arksey","given":"Hilary"},{"family":"O'Malley","given":"Lisa"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,30]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2005",2,1]]}}},{"id":3189,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/KV6C89DM"],"itemData":{"id":3189,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Objectives\nThe scoping review has become increasingly popular as a form of knowledge synthesis. However, a lack of consensus on scoping review terminology, definition, methodology, and reporting limits the potential of this form of synthesis. In this article, we propose recommendations to further advance the field of scoping review methodology.\nStudy Design and Setting\nWe summarize current understanding of scoping review publication rates, terms, definitions, and methods. We propose three recommendations for clarity in term, definition and methodology.\nResults\nWe recommend adopting the terms “scoping review” or “scoping study” and the use of a proposed definition. Until such time as further guidance is developed, we recommend the use of the methodological steps outlined in the Arksey and O'Malley framework and further enhanced by Levac et al. The development of reporting guidance for the conduct and reporting of scoping reviews is underway.\nConclusion\nConsistency in the proposed domains and methodologies of scoping reviews, along with the development of reporting guidance, will facilitate methodological advancement, reduce confusion, facilitate collaboration and improve knowledge translation of scoping review findings.","container-title":"Journal of Clinical Epidemiology","DOI":"10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.03.013","ISSN":"0895-4356","issue":"12","journalAbbreviation":"Journal of Clinical Epidemiology","page":"1291-1294","source":"ScienceDirect","title":"Scoping reviews: time for clarity in definition, methods, and reporting","title-short":"Scoping reviews","URL":"https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895435614002108","volume":"67","author":[{"family":"Colquhoun","given":"Heather L."},{"family":"Levac","given":"Danielle"},{"family":"O'Brien","given":"Kelly K."},{"family":"Straus","given":"Sharon"},{"family":"Tricco","given":"Andrea C."},{"family":"Perrier","given":"Laure"},{"family":"Kastner","given":"Monika"},{"family":"Moher","given":"David"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",2,4]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2014",12,1]]}}},{"id":3187,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/2375028/items/FDBDHNVL"],"itemData":{"id":3187,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"The need for systematic methods for reviewing evidence is continuously increasing. Evidence mapping is one emerging method. There are no authoritative recommendations for what constitutes an evidence map or what methods should be used, and anecdotal evidence suggests heterogeneity in both. Our objectives are to identify published evidence maps and to compare and contrast the presented definitions of evidence mapping, the domains used to classify data in evidence maps, and the form the evidence map takes.","container-title":"Systematic Reviews","DOI":"10.1186/s13643-016-0204-x","ISSN":"2046-4053","issue":"1","journalAbbreviation":"Systematic Reviews","page":"28","source":"BioMed Central","title":"What is an evidence map? A systematic review of published evidence maps and their definitions, methods, and products","title-short":"What is an evidence map?","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1186/s13643-016-0204-x","volume":"5","author":[{"family":"Miake-Lye","given":"Isomi M."},{"family":"Hempel","given":"Susanne"},{"family":"Shanman","given":"Roberta"},{"family":"Shekelle","given":"Paul G."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",2,4]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016",2,10]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Arksey &amp; O’Malley, 2005; Colquhoun et al., 2014; Miake-Lye et al., 2016) e orientar futuras abordagens para uma consolidação do discurso da OS a todas as culturas epistémicas. Seguimos duas questões de investigação: Q1) Qual a evidência da adoção de práticas de investigação aberta nas publicações em HD e de que forma se alinham com as definições normativas de OS? Q2) Quais os desafios da aplicação de práticas de OS na investigação em HD? 
                <hi rend="bold">Objetivo</hi>: O objetivo do estudo é duplo. Em primeiro lugar, pretende-se mapear a evidência do estado atual da adoção e implementação das práticas de investigação aberta nas publicações em Humanidades Digitais (HD). Para tal, será analisado um 
                <hi rend="italic">corpus</hi> representativo da produção em HD, com o intuito de identificar as práticas de investigação aberta mais frequentemente adotadas. Em segundo lugar, a revisão visa discutir os principais desafios enfrentados na adoção dessas práticas no campo das HD. Esta análise incluirá um contraste entre as práticas identificadas e as definições de ciência aberta comumente referenciadas na literatura, com o objetivo de avaliar o grau de convergência entre essas práticas e os princípios normativos da ciência aberta. 
                <hi rend="bold">Métodos</hi>: Seguindo a extensão PRISMA-ScR (
                <hi rend="italic">Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews</hi>), a estratégia de pesquisa combina os conceitos de "Humanidades Digitais" e "investigação aberta", considerando termos relevantes e relacionados. As fontes selecionadas incluem 
                <hi rend="italic">Web of Science, Scopus, OpenAlex, Library and Information Science Source e Humanities International Complete</hi>, assegurando a inclusão de bases de dados multidisciplinares e específicas da área, de forma a compilar um 
                <hi rend="italic">corpus</hi> representativo e relevante de publicações. A equação de pesquisa será ajustada e aplicada em cada uma das fontes selecionadas. Relativamente aos critérios de elegibilidade, serão incluídos apenas artigos originais ou de revisão, sujeitos a revisão por pares, redigidos em inglês, português ou castelhano, publicados até 2024, e com texto integral disponível. Quanto ao âmbito dos estudos, estes deverão enquadrar-se no domínio das HD. Publicações que não façam referência explícita, apliquem ou adotem práticas de OS serão excluídas. Numa fase inicial, será feita uma seleção dos títulos e resumos, seguida da análise integral dos textos, para identificar os estudos relevantes de acordo com os critérios de inclusão. Para a gestão e análise dos dados, será utilizado o 
                <hi rend="italic">software</hi> CADIMA. 
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Resultados: </hi>Embora o estudo ainda se encontre numa fase preliminar e não permita a formulação de conclusões definitivas, resultados parecem demonstrar que as práticas mais adotadas pelas HD são: a publicação em acesso aberto; ciência cidadã; e recursos educacionais abertos. A menção a 
                <hi rend="italic">linked open data</hi> e 
                <hi rend="italic">open source</hi> é frequente nas publicações, sendo estas as referências mais recorrentes; no entanto, nem sempre tais práticas são efetivamente implementadas no contexto da OS. 
                <hi rend="bold">Conclusão</hi>: Embora haja uma valorização crescente de OS, verifica-se uma lacuna entre o discurso normalizado da OS e a efetiva implementação dessas práticas nas HD. Prova-se necessária a reflexão sobre como adaptar e expandir os princípios da OS de forma sensível às especificidades das HD, promovendo uma cultura de abertura mais inclusiva, sustentável e alinhada com os desafios contemporâneos da investigação 
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Arksey, Hilary / O’Malley, Lisa</hi> (2005). Scoping studies: Towards a methodological framework, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Social Research Methodology 8</hi>, 1: 19–32. DOI: 10.1080/1364557032000119616
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Arthur, Paul L. / Hearn, Lydia</hi> (2021). Toward Open Research: A Narrative Review of the Challenges and Opportunities for Open Humanities in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Communication 71</hi>, 5: 827–853. DOI: 10.1093/joc/jqab028
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Arthur, Paul L., / Hearn, Lydia</hi> (2024). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Open scholarship in the humanities</hi>. London: Bloomsbury Publishing Plc. DOI: 10.5040/9781350232303
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Colquhoun, Heather L. / Levac, Danielle / O’Brien, Kelly K. / Straus, Sharon / Tricco, Andrea C. / Perrier, Laure / Kastner, Monika / Moher, David</hi> (2014). Scoping reviews: Time for clarity in definition, methods, and reporting in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 67</hi>, 12: 1291–1294. DOI: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.03.013
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Edmond, Jennifer / Lehmann, Jörg</hi> (2021). Digital humanities, knowledge complexity, and the five ‘aporias’ of digital research in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities 36</hi>: 95–108. DOI: 10.1093/llc/fqab031
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Fitzpatrick, Kathleen</hi> (2012). “The humanities, done digitally”, in: M. K. Gold (Ed.), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</hi>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press 12-15
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Knöchelmann, Marcel</hi> (2019). Open Science in the Humanities, or: Open Humanities?, In: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Publications 7</hi>, 4: 65. DOI: 10.3390/publications7040065
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Miake-Lye, Isomi M. / Hempel, Susanne / Shanman, Roberta / Shekelle, Paul G.</hi> (2016). What is an evidence map? A systematic review of published evidence maps and their definitions, methods, and products, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Systematic Reviews 5</hi>, 1: 28. DOI: 10.1186/s13643-016-0204-x
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nyhan, Julianne / Flinn, Andrew</hi> (2016). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Computation and the Humanities</hi>. Springer International Publishing. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-20170-2
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
