<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KOPER_Beata_How_to_curate_access_to_the_literary_internet__G">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>How to curate access to the literary internet? Guiding through the Polish online culture with the iPBL project</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Koper</surname>
                        <forename>Beata</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Opole, Poland</affiliation>
                    <email>beata.koper@uni.opole.pl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Czwordon-Lis</surname>
                        <forename>Paulina</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>The Institute of Literary Research of the Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland</affiliation>
                    <email>paulina.czwordon-lis@ibl.waw.pl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Rosiński</surname>
                        <forename>Cezary</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>The Institute of Literary Research of the Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland</affiliation>
                    <email>cezary.rosinski@ibl.waw.pl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-28T18:29:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Polish digital culture</term>
                    <term>bibliographic database</term>
                    <term>online resources</term>
                    <term>internet archiving</term>
                    <term>public humanities</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>data publishing projects</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>database creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>digital archiving</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">This poster addresses the challenges of curating, preserving, and ensuring 
                <hi rend="bold">accessibility to internet content</hi>, with a focus on the dynamic domain of Polish digital culture. Using the example of the iPBL project<ref n="1" target="ftn1"/>, the research explores the complexities of selecting, archiving, and sharing ephemeral online resources while highlighting their richness and variability. These issues are examined through methodological innovations that aim to document and analyze Polish internet culture.
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">Polish Literary Bibliography (PBL) has been an indispensable resource for the public for decades, realizing the mission of public humanities. PBL is a complete bibliography of Polish literature, theater, and feature film and is a widely available, free service used by researchers, students, journalists, cultural animators, or librarians. The 
                <hi rend="bold">iPBL project seeks to establish a comprehensive database documenting Polish digital culture</hi>. 
                <hi rend="bold">It aspires to support users in their scholarly pursuits by providing a resource that facilitates critical exploration and engaging content discovery</hi>. This initiative addresses the needs of diverse user groups by offering curated guidance to navigate Poland's vast and varied online cultural landscape (Cf. Griffiths et al. 2008). Such guidance is increasingly critical given the staggering amount of content generated over the past three decades, much of which risks being lost due to the transient nature of online resources, their varied formats, and their uneven cultural and technical value (Miller 2020).
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">A crucial aspect of the project involves the methodology of information gathering and monitoring the development of Internet forms. The project outputs need to incorporate the latest resources—a necessity given the rapid emergence of new websites (the index will be regularly updated), monitor innovations in internet content types (Nęcka-Czapska 2022) (e.g., the rise of podcasts or transitions of bloggers to social media platforms, observed in recent years (Więckiewicz-Archacka 2024)) and account for experimental literary-digital formats unsuitable for traditional processing due to technical constraints.</p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">To ensure the effective selection of diverse and dynamic sources, we combine the results of expert literary inquiries with the PBL bibliographic methodology. The PBL integrates decades of experience in literary documentation with the challenges of digitalization, serving as a robust foundation for our project. To create a communicative and practical collection, we aim for an expert-level domain-specific bibliography, striving for representativeness and balancing between significance (importance) and inclusivity of many types of internet sources (journals, services, portals, blogs, literary creations) (Nęcka 2018) and content quality (assessing linguistic standards, eliminating informational "noise" and technically complicated sources). This approach captures the heterogeneity of the online space, where high-credibility resources coexist with amateur, anarchic, pirated, and volunteer-produced content. To ensure barrier-free access, the project provides curated collections enriched with metadata, enabling easy browsing, discovery, filtering, and searching for content (literary or otherwise), regardless of users' digital competencies. The project results in a carefully curated database of online content, including 4,000 digital sources that serve as a guide to dynamically evolving Polish cultural resources, offering broader perspectives by providing pointers in more peripheral fields (e.g., literary science organization, literary didactics), 200 of which will be supplemented of detailed bibliographic records guiding users to individual texts or their collections. These records will be accessible via pbl.ibl.waw.pl (national scope) and literarybibliography.eu (international scope), and metadata will be downloadable in multiple formats (RIS, BibTeX and MARC21).</p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">All methods, tools, and data collected within the project are designed to create reusable instruments for future bibliographic work, such as machine learning algorithms for thematic and genre classification of document content, streamlining bibliography compilation for print and digital sources, and algorithms for semi-automatic data extraction from internet sources, enabling preliminary collection of bibliographic metadata (author, title, source, access address) applicable in other digital culture archiving projects. A bibliographic data ecosystem is aligned with European standards, facilitating cross-referencing diverse sources in line with FAIR data principles. Our tools are open-access and published on GitHub.</p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">During the project, steps were taken to ensure that curated resources are available through the Wayback Machine. This ensures that even if a website is no longer available online, its content is still accessible for research and reference. </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">By balancing tools for a broad national audience with specialized resources for professional users, the iPBL project creates a bibliographic ecosystem for multiple purposes. Students, teachers, journalists, and literary enthusiasts gain access to user-friendly collections, while scholars and data analysts benefit from sophisticated analytical tools. Integrating traditional bibliographic expertise with cutting-edge digital methodologies underscores the project’s ambition to document Polish digital culture and innovate in bibliographic research and digital humanities. Through its efforts, the iPBL project ensures the preservation and accessibility of Polish internet culture for current and future generations.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
<div type="notes">
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                     Project full name: Bibliography of Polish online digital culture with source catalog and archive. A supplement to the “Polish Literary Bibliography”. Research output supported from the state budget under the program implemented by the Minister of Education and Science called “National Program for the Development of the Humanities” project number NPRH/DN/SP/495736/2021/10, the amount of funding 1,315,730.00 PLN, the total value of the project 1,315,730.00 PLN.
                </note></div>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <anchor xml:id="Hlk196599824"/>
                        <hi rend="bold">Griffiths, Rebecca J. / Maron, Nancy L. / Guthrie, Kevin M.</hi> (2008): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Sustainability and Revenue Models for Online Academic Resources. An Ithaka Report</hi> &lt;
                        <ref target="http://sr.ithaka.org?p=22349">http://sr.ithaka.org?p=22349</ref>&gt; [28.04.2025].
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Miller, Vincent</hi> (2020): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Understanding digital culture</hi>. London: SAGE Publications.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nęcka, Agnieszka</hi> (2018): ”Łowcy odsłon. O blogosferze literackiej słów kilka”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Tematy i Konteksty</hi> 8, 13: 265-276.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Nęcka-Czapska, Agnieszka</hi> (2022): ”(Za)istnieć w sieci. Strategie polskich pisarzy w social mediach”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Czytanie Literatury. Łódzkie Studia Literaturoznawcze</hi> 11: 59–74. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Więckiewicz-Archacka, Marta</hi> (2024): ”Z blogosfery na platformy społecznościowe. Migracje dziennikarzy w środowisku komunikacyjnym sieci”, in: Łosiewicz, Małgorzata / Ryłko-Kurpiewska, Anna / Knoch, Konrad (eds.):
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Media i społeczeństwo. W erze platform, algorytmów i danych</hi>. Gdańsk: Polskie Towarzystwo Komunikacji Społecznej 123-136.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
