<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="VAN_DER_LEK_Iulianna_Engaging_Researchers_for_Improving_Serv">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Engaging Researchers for Improving Services and Training: Insights from the ATRIUM Survey and Researcher Forum</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Umerle</surname>
                        <forename>Tomasz</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Digital Humanities Centre IBL PAN</affiliation>
                    <email>tomasz.umerle@ibl.waw.pl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Lombardo</surname>
                        <forename>Tiziana</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Net7</affiliation>
                    <email>lombardo@netseven.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>van der Lek</surname>
                        <forename>Iulianna</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>CLARIN ERIC</affiliation>
                    <email>i.vanderlek@uu.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ilvanidou</surname>
                        <forename>Maria</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Athens University of Economics and Business</affiliation>
                    <email>milvanidou@aueb.gr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Delmazo</surname>
                        <forename>Carol</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>OPERAS</affiliation>
                    <email>carol.delmazo@operas-eu.org</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-25T09:23:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Poster</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>infrastructures</term>
                    <term>services</term>
                    <term>community</term>
                    <term>training</term>
                    <term>skills</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>curricular and pedagogical development and analysis</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>open access methods</term>
                    <term>user experience design and analysis</term>
                    <term>Communication studies</term>
                    <term>Education/ pedagogy</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>This poster will highlight the initial key outcomes of the 
                <ref target="https://atrium-research.eu/">ATRIUM project</ref>. ATRIUM is a four-year European Commission-funded project (2024-2027) 
                <hi rend="bold">facilitating access to digital research infrastructures</hi> across disciplines, languages and media. It bridges four leading Research Infrastructures (RIs) representing Arts, Humanities and Social Sciences: 
                <ref target="https://www.dariah.eu/">DARIAH</ref>, 
                <ref target="https://www.ariadne-research-infrastructure.eu/">ARIADNE</ref>, 
                <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref>, and 
                <ref target="https://operas-eu.org/">OPERAS</ref>. ATRIUM aims to 
                <hi rend="bold">enhance the services</hi> offered by these infrastructures and their partners. It seeks to 
                <hi rend="bold">articulate training materials into a pedagogical narrative</hi> within the 
                <hi rend="bold">ATRIUM Curriculum</hi>, which will be designed based on researchers' skills gaps and training needs. To achieve these goals, ATRIUM adopts an
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve"> intensive community engagement approach</hi> relying on the 
                <hi rend="bold">active</hi> participation of researchers, whose feedback and engagement are 
                <hi rend="bold">indispensable</hi>. The poster will showcase how ATRIUM brings this approach to life through the first Researcher Forum (RF) and an online 
                <hi rend="bold">survey</hi> that gathered 334 responses from researchers from the Arts, Humanities and Social Sciences across 26 European and 5 non-European countries. These contributions provided valuable insights into assessing and enhancing researchers’ skills, guiding service improvements and shaping training initiatives.
            </p>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Researchers’ Survey</head>
                <p>The Researchers’ Survey serves as a critical tool for 
                    <hi rend="bold">understanding the skills and training needs of researchers</hi>. Following the snowball sampling method, its aim was to investigate whether researchers have the required skills to actively use the research services and tools available in the 
                    <ref target="https://atrium-research.eu/services/">ATRIUM Catalogue</ref>. In addition to skills assessment, the authors also used the survey to gather 
                    <hi rend="bold">insights into the training gaps</hi> researchers encounter. This information helped in designing the 
                    <hi rend="bold">ATRIUM Curriculum</hi> to better address their needs and support their work effectively. The poster will present preliminary results, highlighting key trends, with the full analysis expected to be completed by August 2025. The analysis reveals a clear 
                    <hi rend="bold">need for training in Open Science practices and FAIR principles</hi>, reflecting the growing importance of these frameworks in enabling collaborative and transparent research. Additionally, researchers expressed a strong interest in more 
                    <hi rend="bold">specialised training on topics such as data analysis, visualisation techniques and automatic text recognition</hi>. These initial results underscore the value of the survey in guiding the ATRIUM efforts to bridge skill gaps and create relevant and impactful training resources. 
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Researcher Forum: GoTriple</head>
                <p>The Researcher Forum (RF) is a workshop format designed to gain a deeper understanding of the 
                    <hi rend="bold">needs of the users interacting with specific research infrastructure (RIs) services and tools</hi>. The first RF took place in Poznań, Poland, in October 2024, 
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">focusing on </hi>
                    <ref target="https://gotriple.eu/">
                        <hi rend="bold">GoTriple</hi>
                    </ref>, a 
                    <hi rend="bold">multilingual discovery platform</hi> provided by 
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">OPERAS </hi>for researchers in the Social Sciences and Humanities. Twelve researchers working in Poland actively participated in a 
                    <hi rend="bold">usability test and an expert review, which enabled a thorough evaluation of the service and the identification of several potential improvements to better meet</hi> the researchers' needs. This collaborative process exemplifies the 
                    <hi rend="bold">importance of involving the community</hi> in the iterative improvement of research infrastructure services, ensuring that the services and tools really support and empower the community. The RF on GoTriple is only the first of a series of RFs that will be organised through ATRIUM and dedicated to different digital services offered by RIs.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Focusing on Community Engagement &amp; Sharing the Insights</head>
                <p>Both the Researchers’ Survey and the Forum demonstrate how ATRIUM engages with the community to help improve the digital services and training service provision provided by 
                    <hi rend="bold">DARIAH, ARIADNE, CLARIN, and OPERAS</hi>. Based on a 
                    <hi rend="bold">quantitative and qualitative analysis</hi> of the results obtained from these first two engagement initiatives, 
                    <hi rend="bold">the poster will include statistics and links to reports</hi> that interested conference participants can further explore.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>Bulatovic, N., Gnadt, T., Romanello, M., Stiller, J., Thoden, K. (2016). Usability in Digital Humanities - Evaluating User Interfaces, Infrastructural Components and the Use of Mobile Devices During Research Process. In: Fuhr, N., Kovács, L., Risse, T., Nejdl, W. (eds) 
                        <hi rend="italic">Research and Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries</hi>. TPDL 2016. Lecture Notes in Computer Science(), vol 9819. Springer, Cham. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-43997-6_26">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-43997-6_26</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmazo, C., &amp; Umerle, T. (2024). Report of First Researcher Forum. Zenodo. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14514990">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14514990</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Tasovac, T., &amp; Garnett, V. (2024). The Guidelines for Producing the ATRIUM Curriculum. Zenodo. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13867113">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13867113</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vanicek, T., &amp; Popelka, S. (2023). The Think-Aloud Method for Evaluating the Usability of a Regional Atlas. 
                        <hi rend="italic">ISPRS International Journal of Geo-Information</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">12</hi>(3), 95. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi12030095">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijgi12030095</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
