<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BOERNER_Ingo_When_Worlds_Collide__A_Literary_Linked_Open_Dat">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>When Worlds Collide: A Literary Linked Open Data Model Critiqueathon (Workshop)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Boerner</surname>
                        <forename>Ingo</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Potsdam, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>ingo.boerner@uni-potsdam.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Oberreither</surname>
                        <forename>Bernhard</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>ACDH-CH, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>bernhard.oberreither@oeaw.ac.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Pianzola</surname>
                        <forename>Federico</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Groningen, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                    <email>f.pianzola@rug.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Plank</surname>
                        <forename>Lukas</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>ACDH-CH, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>lukas.plank@oeaw.ac.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Röttgermann</surname>
                        <forename>Julia</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Trier Center for Digital Humanities, Trier University, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>roettger@uni-trier.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ros</surname>
                        <forename>Salvador</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>UNED, Madrid</affiliation>
                    <email>sros@scc.uned.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schöch</surname>
                        <forename>Christof</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Trier Center for Digital Humanities, Trier University, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>schoech@uni-trier.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Skorinkin</surname>
                        <forename>Daniil</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Potsdam, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>daniil.skorinkin@uni-potsdam.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Trilcke</surname>
                        <forename>Peer</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Potsdam, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>trilcke@uni-potsdam.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-30T12:57:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Linked Open Data</term>
                    <term>Ontology</term>
                    <term>Computational Literary Studies</term>
                    <term>Community Building</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>linked (open) data</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">The workshop 
                <hi rend="italic">When Worlds Collide: A Literary Linked Open Data Model Critiqueathon</hi> invites participants from the field of Computational Literary Studies to engage in a half-day critique session dedicated to ontologies and data models for literature. By leveraging the format of a hackathon and the open discussion ethos of a bar camp, this “critiqueathon” seeks to foster a culture of honest, constructive critique. Participants will explore and challenge assumptions about how key concepts in literary studies—such as the “Literary Work,” “Author,” “Genre,” “Interpretation,” and “Features of a Literary Text”—are represented in competing data models, striving for greater clarity and cross-model understanding and sets impulses for further community-based and network-orientated development Through creative and interactive pedagogical settings, this workshop aims to push the boundaries of ontology development, promote interdisciplinary exchange, and address the fragmented state of data modeling in literary studies.
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">In line with the conference motto of “Promoting Openness and Collaboration”, and considering the definition of ontologies as “shared conceptualizations” (Gruber 1995), it is evident that no shared ontology is currently widely in use in Computational Literary Studies.</p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">Nevertheless, several proposals for ontologies in the field have been put forward (Diez Platas et al. 2021; Hinzmann et al. 2024; Oberreither 2019; Pannach et al. 2024). In designing ontologies, there are tendencies and competing systems or approaches to modelling, for example the opposition between an event based approach to modeling aligned with the CIDOC CRM and compatible models, i.e. the LRMoo versus projects relying on Wikibase and its inherent data model.</p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">The idea of this workshop for the participants is to leave the world of their own data model and try to immerse themselves into someone else's model to find common ground for data modeling in the field of Computational Literary Studies.</p>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Objectives</head>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Critique Data Models:</hi> Provide a structured yet dynamic forum to critique existing literary studies data models and ontologies in depth.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Foster Perspective Shifts:</hi> Encourage participants to engage with and interpret ontologies other than their own, broadening their understanding of diverse modeling approaches.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Identify Trends and Gaps:</hi> Examine tendencies, trends, and gaps in current modeling practices, particularly around event-based approaches (e.g., CIDOC CRM and LRMoo) or Wikibase-centric models.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Explore Interoperability:</hi> Assess the potential for compatibility and mapping between competing systems, identifying practical steps toward bridging conceptual divides.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="bold">Cultivate Critical Dialogue:</hi> Establish an honest and productive critique culture within the computational literary studies community.
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Format and Schedule</head>
                <div type="div2" rend="DH-Heading2">
                    <head>First Session: Critique Through Immersion</head>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Introduction and Orientation</hi> (15 minutes):
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Overview of the workshop goals, structure, and expectations. Participants briefly introduce their data models and highlight one challenge or issue they face.</p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Interactive Critique Method: “PowerPoint Karaoke” </hi>(45 minutes): 
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Each participant receives another’s data model or ontology to study briefly. They must then present it to the group as if it were their own, emphasizing its strengths and limitations.</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Goal</hi>: Encourage empathy and fresh perspectives by forcing participants to engage deeply with unfamiliar models.
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Outcome</hi>:
                            <list type="unordered">
                                <item>Surface implicit assumptions and biases in modeling approaches.</item>
                                <item>Show opportunities and limits of model/ontology documentation and pathways to improvement.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Discussion: Learning Through Critique </hi>(15 minutes):
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Facilitated group discussion reflecting on the insights gained from the exercise. What surprised participants about their own or others’ models? What commonalities or conceptual tensions emerged?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div2" rend="DH-Heading2">
                    <head>Second Session: Finding Common Ground and Productive Tensions</head>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Breakout Groups: Deep Dives into Key Concepts</hi> (45 minutes):
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Participants split into groups to explore and discuss specific aspects of literary data modeling, such as:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Modeling the “Literary Work”</item>
                        <item>Representing “Authorship” and “Agency”</item>
                        <item>Assigning “Genre”</item>
                        <item>Capturing textual features</item>
                        <item>Balancing precision and interoperability in metadata standards.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Reconvene: Group Presentations</hi> (30 minutes):
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Each break out group shares key insights emerging from their discussion, present their ideas and receive feedback, emphasizing strengths, weaknesses, and potential mappings to other models.</p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Mapping the Landscape: Synthesis Discussion</hi> (30 minutes):
                    </p>
                    <p style="text-align: left; ">Participants collectively identify patterns of compatibility and points of fundamental difference between models. The focus is on exploring whether mechanisms for cross-model mapping and translation can be developed.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Involved Projects and Initiatives</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The workshop builds upon a loose network of people involved in the creation of data models for Computational Literary Studies:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>CLS INFRA (EU Horizon 2020 Project “Computational Literary Infrastructures”, 
                        <ref target="https://clsinfra.io">https://clsinfra.io</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>DraCor (Drama Corpora Project, 
                        <ref target="https://dracor.org">https://dracor.org</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>GOLEM (ERC Starting Grant funded project “Graphs and Ontologies for Literary Evolution Models”, 
                        <ref target="https://https://golemlab.eu">https://https://golemlab.eu</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>INTRO (“The Intertextual, Interpictorial, and Intermedial Relations Ontology”, 
                        <ref target="https://github.com/BOberreither/INTRO">https://github.com/BOberreither/INTRO</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>LODinG (“Linked Open Data in den Geisteswissenschaften” [“LOD in the Humanities”], 
                        <ref target="https://tcdh.uni-trier.de/de/projekt/loding">https://tcdh.uni-trier.de/de/projekt/loding</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>MiMoText (“Mining and Modeling Text”, 
                        <ref target="https://mimotext.uni-trier.de">https://mimotext.uni-trier.de</ref>)
                    </item>
                    <item>POSTDATA (“Poetry Standardization and Linked Open Data”, 
                        <ref target="https://postdata.linhd.uned.es">https://postdata.linhd.uned.es</ref>)
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Intended Audience</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">This workshop is designed for researchers, developers, and practitioners in Computational Literary Studies, and everyone else involved in creating or using ontologies, metadata standards, and linked data models in the Literary Studies (i.e. digital librarians, database maintainers, research data curators). Participants should have a working knowledge of ontology design and be willing to critique and be critiqued. Participants are encouraged to provide documentation (e.g. a graphical representation of their data model) and/or a presentation prior to the workshop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Didactic Innovations</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Critiqueathon</hi> format prioritizes interaction and creative engagement over traditional presentations. By using methods like “PowerPoint Karaoke,” the workshop disrupts the conventional conference format, forcing participants to adopt new perspectives on familiar problems. Group discussions and structured critique encourage dialogue that is rigorous yet collaborative, laying the groundwork for productive intellectual collisions.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Expected Outcomes</head>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>A clearer understanding of competing literary data models, their strengths, and limitations.</item>
                    <item>Identification of shared concepts and critical divergences in modeling approaches.</item>
                    <item>Practical proposals for addressing interoperability challenges.</item>
                    <item>Strengthened community ties and a commitment to fostering a more unified approach to data modeling in the Computational Literary Studies and beyond.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Acknowledgement</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">This work is part of CLS INFRA (
                    <ref target="https://clsinfra.io">https://clsinfra.io</ref>), which is funded from the European Union's Horizon 2020 program (grant agreement No. 101004984).
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Diez Platas, L.; Bermúdez, H.; Ros S. et al. 2021. “Description of Postdata Poetry Ontology V1.0”. In P. Plecháč, R. Kolár, A. Bories, &amp; J. Říha (Eds.), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Tackling the Toolkit: Plotting Poetry through Computational Literary Studies</hi> (pp. 15–30). Prague: ICL CAS. DOI:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.51305/ICL.CZ.9788076580336.02">10.51305/ICL.CZ.9788076580336.02</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Ďurčo, M. Charvát, V.; Resch, S., et al. 2023. “CLS INFRA D6.3 Standards beyond TEI / Extended Transformation Matrix / Alternative Formats”. DOI:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10209606">10.5281/ZENODO.10209606</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Gruber, T. 1995. “Toward Principles for the Design of Ontologies Used for Knowledge Sharing?” In 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</hi> 43, No. 5–6 (November 1995) (pp.907–928). DOI:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1006/ijhc.1995.1081">10.1006/ijhc.1995.1081</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Hinzmann, M., Bremm, M., Duan, T. et al. 2024. “Patterns in Modeling and Querying a Knowledge Graph for Literary History (Preprint).” Zenodo. DOI:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.12080340">10.5281/ZENODO.12080340</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Oberreither, B. 2023. “A Linked Data Vocabulary for Intertextuality in Literary Studies, with Some Considerations Regarding Digital Editions”, In H. Klug und R. Bleier (Eds.), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digitale Edition in Österreich</hi>, pp. 69–87. URN: urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-704496.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Pannach, F., Cheng, L., Pianzola, F. 2024. “The GOLEM-Knowledge Graph and Search Interface: Perspectives into Narrative and Fiction” In 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Computational Humanities Research Conference</hi> 2024, Aarhus, Denmark. URL: 
                        <ref target="https://golemlab.eu/publications/chr2024_kg/chr2024-kg.pdf">https://golemlab.eu/publications/chr2024_kg/chr2024-kg.pdf</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
