<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GARNETT_Vicky_Building_Ethical_Bridges__Collaborative_Approa">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Building Ethical Bridges: Collaborative Approaches to Research Integrity in the Digital Humanities (Workshop)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Garnett</surname>
                        <forename>Vicky</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>DARIAH-EU, Ireland; Trinity College Dublin</affiliation>
                    <email>vicky.garnett@dariah.eu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Bodi-Fernandez</surname>
                        <forename>Otto</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>AUSSDA (Austrian Service Provider of CESSDA-ERIC)</affiliation>
                    <email>otto.bodi@uni-graz.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Crawley</surname>
                        <forename>Francis P.</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Coalition for Advancing of Research Assessment (CoARA)’s Working Group on ‘Ethics and Research Integrity Policy for Responsible Research Assessment in Data and Artificial Intelligence (ERIP)’</affiliation>
                    <email>fpc@gcpalliance.org</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Gouzi</surname>
                        <forename>Françoise</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>DARIAH-EU, Ireland</affiliation>
                    <email>francoise.gouzi@dariah.eu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Kamocki</surname>
                        <forename>Paweł</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Leibniz-Institut für Deutsche Sprache</affiliation>
                    <email>kamocki@ids-mannheim.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Kuzman Šlogar</surname>
                        <forename>Koraljka</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Institute of Ethnology and Folklore Research</affiliation>
                    <email>koraljkak@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Luyten</surname>
                        <forename>Dirk</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Belgian State Archives; Study and Documentation Centre for War and Contemporary Society</affiliation>
                    <email>Dirk.Luyten@arch.be</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Scholger</surname>
                        <forename>Walter</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Graz</affiliation>
                    <email>walter.scholger@uni-graz.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Schuster</surname>
                        <forename>Kristen</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Southampton</affiliation>
                    <email>K.M.Schuster@soton.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-28T09:29:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Pre-Conference Workshop and Tutorial</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Research ethics</term>
                    <term>research methodologies</term>
                    <term>open science</term>
                    <term>CARE principles</term>
                    <term>FAIR</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>copyright</term>
                    <term>licensing</term>
                    <term>and permissions standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and processes</term>
                    <term>digital access</term>
                    <term>privacy</term>
                    <term>and ethics analysis</term>
                    <term>open access methods</term>
                    <term>sustainable procedures</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Education/ pedagogy</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>Sociology</term>
                    <term>Transgender and non-binary studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">How do we as researchers protect ourselves legally and emotionally when accessing more information through archives, oral histories, Large Language Models (LLMs), and fieldwork? The importance of ethics in a research context is not in question; however, the evolving digital ecosystem presents new challenges to researchers and practitioners alongside new requirements to demonstrate compliance with fundamental ethical principles and emerging best practices.<ref n="1" target="ftn1"/>
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">This half-day workshop<ref n="2" target="ftn2"/> outlines approaches to research methods with an eye towards identifying opportunities to integrate research ethics into the lifecycle of a project. Through interdisciplinary conversations, the contributors will show how ethical frameworks, including the 
                <hi rend="color(1F1F1F)" xml:space="preserve">FAIR (Wilkinson et al, 2016), CARE (Carroll et al, 2020), and TRUST (Lin et al, 2020) principles, </hi>can improve research methodologies within the digital humanities. The results of this workshop will be developed into a white paper.
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">The workshop is divided into two sessions followed by an open discussion. In the first session, “
                <hi rend="italic">Ethics and the Research Infrastructure</hi>,” representatives from DARIAH-EU<ref n="3" target="ftn3"/>, CLARIN<ref n="4" target="ftn4"/>, CESSDA<ref n="5" target="ftn5"/>, and EHRI<ref n="6" target="ftn6"/>, four European research infrastructures, will demonstrate how they have engaged with their respective communities to support the application of best ethical practices in research and data archiving.
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">In the second session, “
                <hi rend="italic">Ethics from Grassroots to the Global Canopy,</hi>” three different organisations (PeTRA<ref n="7" target="ftn7"/>, ELDAH<ref n="8" target="ftn8"/>, and CoARA-ERIP<ref n="9" target="ftn9"/>), will demonstrate how they are addressing ethics issues and research integrity specific to their communities.<ref n="10" target="ftn10"/><ref n="11" target="ftn11"/>
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">
                <hi rend="color(1F1F1F)">The two sessions will be followed by an open discussion facilitated by prompt questions, including contributions provided through social media. Participants will be able to ask questions, share opinions on the presented services and initiatives, and convey their needs and wishes regarding the advancement of ethical practices across the disciplines in the European digital space.</hi><ref n="12" target="ftn12"/>
            </p>
            <p style="text-align: left; ">
                <hi rend="bold color(1F1F1F)">The target audience</hi>
                <hi rend="color(1F1F1F)" xml:space="preserve"> for this workshop includes students, researchers, and practitioners in the digital humanities and social sciences committed to fostering ethical research practices in the evolving digital ecosystem. It is particularly relevant to those engaged with open science, participatory humanities, and the application of FAIR (Wilkinson et al, 2016), CARE (Carroll et al 2020), and TRUST (Lin et al 2020) principles in digital scholarship. Academics and professionals exploring the ethics of AI, digital archives, and community-focused initiatives, as well as those addressing challenges in data governance and open research infrastructures, will benefit from this workshop. The session anticipates an audience of </hi>
                <hi rend="bold color(1F1F1F)">up to 50 participants</hi>
                <hi rend="color(1F1F1F)">, including students, early-career researchers, and seasoned scholars from across Europe.</hi>  
            </p>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Agenda</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Introduction to the session - 10 mins</item>
                    <item>Session 1: Ethics and the Research Infrastructure - 60 mins</item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="Bullets">Coffee Break - 20 mins</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>Session 2: Ethics From Grassroots to Global Canopy - 50 mins</item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="Bullets">Open Discussion - 30 mins</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="Bullets">Wrap-Up - 10 mins </hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Biographies</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Vicky Garnett</hi> is Training and Education Officer for DARIAH-EU. Within this role she manages DARIAH-Campus, the free and open online training platform, ensuring best open science practices are adhered to in the creation of training materials. Vicky co-chairs the PeTRA-CIG and has also led development of an Ethics and Research Integrity Policy within DARIAH-EU, working alongside other contributors to this workshop.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Otto Bodi-Fernandez</hi> is a sociologist at the Center for Social Research (CSR), University of Graz, representing the contact point for AUSSDA (the Austrian Social Science Data Archive), the national service provider of CESSDA-ERIC. He supports researchers in the research data management and archiving, and teaches empirical research methods and data analysis. His research focuses on childhood and youth research, educational sociology and social inequality.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold color(1F1F1F)">Francis P. Crawley</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(1F1F1F)" xml:space="preserve"> is Coordinator and Co-chair of CoARA-ERIP, Co-chair of FORCE11 RA4AI, Co-chair and Principal Investigator of EOSC-Future/RDA AIDV, and Chair of CODATA IDPC. His work focuses on integrating ethical frameworks and principles of research integrity with a focus on bridging policy and implementation in emerging digital methodologies and technologies. He leads initiatives to ensure that digital tools and methodologies used in science and academia are leveraged responsibly across disciplines, sectors, and communities.</hi>
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Françoise Gouzi </hi>is Open Science Officer at DARIAH-EU, responsible for fostering and implementing open science practices across the DARIAH network. She contributes to the design and implementation of open science policy statements, guidelines and services related to the open dissemination of research results in the humanities. She is co-chair of Research Data Management DARIAH Working Group, member of CoARA Working group "Evaluating SSH Globally" and Managing Editor for ‘Transformations: A DARIAH Journal.’
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold color(212121)">Paweł Kamocki</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve"> is a legal expert in Leibniz-Institut für Deutsche Sprache, Mannheim. Paweł has worked in the public and private sector in research policy, and co-created LegalTech tools for researchers. He chairs the CLARIN Legal and Ethical Issues Committee (CLIC) and the Working Group on Legal and Ethical Issues of the Text+ consortium, part of the German National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI). His research interests include legal issues in LLMs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Koraljka Kuzman Šlogar</hi> is a cultural anthropologist at the Institute of Ethnology and Folklore Research in Zagreb. She is the Croatian representative and national coordinator for DARIAH-ERIC and co-chair of ELDAH, focusing on ethics and legal questions in the digital arts and humanities. Her research addresses ethical challenges in the life-cycle of research data, as well as digitization projects and the development of digital repositories for intangible cultural heritage. 
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Dirk Luyten</hi> is a historian specialising in the history of the Second World War and its aftermath as well as in legal history and the history of social policies. He has been involved in the project EHRI (European Holocaust Research Infrastructure) since the beginning in 2010, focusing on privacy issues. He is currently work package leader in the EHRI-Implementation Phase project.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Walter Scholger</hi> is Deputy Director of the Department of Digital Humanities, University of Graz, and has been active in the fields of digital publishing, research management, curricular development and Open Science since 2001. He co-chairs ELDAH and CLIC, presenting and teaching on legal (and ethical) aspects of digital research processes.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Kristen Schuster</hi> (they/them) engages with the politics of data in the humanities. As an information scientist, Dr. Schuster’s research investigates the possibilities of transformative technical practices through collaborative information work. Through teaching and research, Dr. Schuster has established expertise in the fields of digital humanities education and information science, and co-chairs the PeTRA-CIG. 
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
<div type="notes">
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">European Commission, Directorate-General for Communications Networks, Content and Technology. ‘Apply AI Strategy.’ 9 April 2025. </hi>
                        <ref target="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/apply-ai">https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/apply-ai</ref>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                    
                        <hi rend="Footer_Char">Authors of this workshop are listed in alphabetical order by surname (other than the submitting author), and this is not an indication of the level or significance of their contribution to the proposal and workshop.</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> DARIAH-EU is the Digital Research Infrastructure for Arts and Humanities, a European research infrastructure with ‘European Research Infrastructure Consortium’ (ERIC) status. See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://www.dariah.eu">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://www.dariah.eu</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">  ‘CLARIN’ is the Common Language Resources and Technology Infrastructure, and has ‘ERIC’ status.  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://www.clarin.eu/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">‘CESSDA’ is the Consortium of European Social Science Data Archives, and has ERIC status.  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://www.cessda.eu/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://www.cessda.eu/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> ‘EHRI’ is the European Holocaust Research Infrastructure.  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://www.ehri-project.eu/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> The ‘Protecting the Investigator in Traumatic Research Areas’ UK/Ireland Digital Humanities Association community interest group, known in short as ‘PeTRA’.  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://digitalhumanities-uk-ie.org/community-interest-groups/protecting-the-investigator-in-traumatic-research-areas/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://digitalhumanities-uk-ie.org/community-interest-groups/protecting-the-investigator-in-traumatic-research-areas/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">The DARIAH-EU Working Group on Ethics and Legality in the Digital Arts and Humanities, ELDAH.  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://eldah.hypotheses.org/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://eldah.hypotheses.org/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">  The Coalition for Advancing of Research Assessment (CoARA)’s Working Group on ‘Ethics and Research Integrity Policy for Responsible Research Assessment in Data and Artificial Intelligence (ERIP).  See </hi>
                        <ref target="https://coara.eu/coalition/working-groups/wg-erip/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">https://coara.eu/coalition/wo</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <ref target="https://coara.eu/coalition/working-groups/wg-erip/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">r</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <ref target="https://coara.eu/coalition/working-groups/wg-erip/">
                            <hi rend="color(1155CC)" style="font-size:10pt">king-groups/wg-erip/</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 5th Dec 2024)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">European Commission, ERA Forum. ‘Living guidelines on the responsible use of generative AI in research.’ April 2025. </hi>
                        <ref target="https://ec.europa.eu/eusurvey/runner/AIinScience">https://ec.europa.eu/eusurvey/runner/AIinScience</ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 28 April 2025)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">SAPEA. ‘Successful and timely uptake of artificial intelligence in science in the EU: Evidence review report.’ April 2024. </hi>
                        <ref target="https://scientificadvice.eu/advice/artificial-intelligence-in-science/">https://scientificad</ref>
                        <ref target="https://scientificadvice.eu/advice/artificial-intelligence-in-science/">v</ref>
                        <ref target="https://scientificadvice.eu/advice/artificial-intelligence-in-science/">ice.eu/advice/artificial-intelligence-in-science/</ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 28 April 2025)</hi>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                    
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">European Commission, Directorate-General for Research and Innovation. ‘A European strategy for AI in science – paving the way for a European AI research council.’ 10 April 2025. </hi>
                        <ref target="https://ec.europa.eu/info/research-and-innovation/funding/funding-opportunities/funding-programmes-and-open-calls/ai-in-science_en">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">https://ec.europa.eu/info/research-and-innovation/funding/funding-opportunities/funding-programmes-and-open-calls/ai-in-science_en</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (accessed 28 April 2025)</hi>
                    
                </note></div>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">Carroll, Stephanie. 
                        <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2020) ‘The CARE Principles for Indigenous Data Governance’, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Data Science Journal</hi>, 19, pp. 1–12. Available at: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-042">https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-042</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">Lin, Dawei. 
                        <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2020) ‘The TRUST Principles for digital repositories’, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Data</hi>, 7(1), p. 144. Available at: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-0486-7">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-0486-7</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">Wilkinson, Mark .D. 
                        <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2016) ‘The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stewardship’, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Scientific Data</hi>, 3(1), p. 160018. Available at: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18">https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
