<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="GIR_N_PALAU_Jonathan_Rethinking_the_Publishing_System__A_Pro">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Rethinking the Publishing System: A Proposal for the Evaluation and Editing of Digital Academic Objects</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Girón Palau</surname>
                        <forename>Jonathan</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</affiliation>
                    <email>jonathan.giron@unam.mx</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-25T19:22:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>open science</term>
                    <term>editing</term>
                    <term>evaluation</term>
                    <term>digital objects</term>
                    <term>publishing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>electronic literature production and analysis</term>
                    <term>scholarly editing and editions development</term>
                    <term>analysis</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>Communication studies</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Since their creation, 
                <anchor xml:id="Hlk184392825"/>digital humanities (DH) have introduced new forms of publication, methodologies, and ways of communicating research. Efforts to recognize the field and its wide range of outputs have been translated into guides for evaluating careers 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"MnMEYLYd","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Clement, 2019)","plainCitation":"(Clement, 2019)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1528,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/FY3RNU5E"],"itemData":{"id":1528,"type":"webpage","abstract":"{metaDescription}","language":"en","title":"ACH Guidelines for Assessment of Digital Scholarship in Tenure and Promotion","URL":"https://ach.org/news/2019/09/ach-guidelines-for-assessment-of-digital-scholarship-in-tenure-and-promotion/","author":[{"family":"Clement","given":"Tanya E."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,14]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019",9,26]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Clement, 2019) and the assessment of various digital resources
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"dL01Ssee","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Galina Russell, 2022; Odell & Pollock, 2016; Risam, 2014)","plainCitation":"(Galina Russell, 2022; Odell & Pollock, 2016; Risam, 2014)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":225,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/S3BSDGYI"],"itemData":{"id":225,"type":"book","event-place":"Ciudad de México","publisher":"UNAM","publisher-place":"Ciudad de México","title":"Pautas para el desarrollo y la evaluación de proyectos digitales en las humanidades","editor":[{"family":"Galina Russell","given":"Isabel"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022"]]}}},{"id":386,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/VJYK2JQD"],"itemData":{"id":386,"type":"article-journal","DOI":"10.7912/C2NC7S","source":"DOI.org (Datacite)","title":"Open Peer Review for Digital Humanities Projects: A Modest Proposal","title-short":"Open Peer Review for Digital Humanities Projects","URL":"http://hdl.handle.net/1805/9365","author":[{"family":"Odell","given":"Jere D."},{"family":"Pollock","given":"Caitlin M. J."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2019",10,14]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016"]]}}},{"id":389,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/4N9JLSBC"],"itemData":{"id":389,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"Ada: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and Technology","language":"English","title":"Rethinking Peer Review in the Age of Digital Humanities","URL":"https://adanewmedia.org/2014/04/issue4-risam/","volume":"4","author":[{"family":"Risam","given":"Roopika"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2019",10,14]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2014",4,21]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Galina, 2022; Odell &amp; Pollock, 2016; Risam, 2014). However, the research outputs of DH have not yet been fully integrated into the formal academic communication system.<ref n="1" target="ftn1"/> While there are efforts in this direction 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"mTW22kf0","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Helling, 2024)","plainCitation":"(Helling, 2024)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1530,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/WCKUB63E"],"itemData":{"id":1530,"type":"paper-conference","DOI":"https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761079","title":"Digital Humanities is more than the paper publication -- thoughts on acknowledging non-paper research outputs","author":[{"family":"Helling","given":"Patrick"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2024"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Helling, 2024), and some journals already accept and publish various types of data and multimedia results, their full integration into universities, particularly in publishing departments, has not yet been achieved. Thus, within the context of open science and with full awareness of the epistemological value that the wide production of DH contributes to knowledge construction, this presentation aims to contribute to this debate by proposing a series of guidelines for the evaluation and editing of these objects.
            </p>
            <p>The digitization of academic communication has profoundly transformed research practices in the humanities. In this context, digital academic objects have emerged not only as an extension of traditional publications but as new ways to represent and share knowledge. These objects include databases, repositories, critical editions, visualizations, scripts, and other artifacts, enabling new and complex ways of presenting research findings. However, this shift calls for a reconfiguration of evaluation and editing processes to ensure that these objects are not only academically rigorous but also accessible and reusable within the digital open science ecosystem. A key aspect of this proposal is the epistemological value of digital objects. As Priani 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"fuBLcJtS","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Priani Sais\\uc0\\u243{}, 2020)","plainCitation":"(Priani Saisó, 2020)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":347,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/Z36JM2QR"],"itemData":{"id":347,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"In humanities research mediated by a digital environment, data appears as a source of new objects of knowledge. This article discusses the nature of the data, how they represent objects, and what difficulties are for the data to be intel-ligible. To do this, we take as an example the work developed within the Ocean Exchanges project, in order to show that the data is built in layers and that in each of them its intelligibility is compromised. That is why we consider the da-ta to be epistemologically fragile and its constitution as an object of study even insufficient to give rise to a new form of knowledge.","container-title":"Logos","language":"es","page":"9-25","source":"Zotero","title":"Una frágil episteme Los datos como objetos de conocimiento en humanidades","volume":"134","author":[{"family":"Priani Saisó","given":"Ernesto"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2020"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-family:Aptos">(2020)</hi> notes, data are constructed within an epistemological context. Digital objects, being based on computational data, not only allow for storage and retrieval of information but also constitute objects of knowledge in themselves. As Drucker 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"K7Zs51o2","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Drucker, 2010)","plainCitation":"(Drucker, 2010)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":443,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/MEPGHDS2"],"itemData":{"id":443,"type":"chapter","abstract":"Start reading this text on Debates in the DH Manifold.","container-title":"Debates in the Digital Humanities","event-place":"Minnesota","ISBN":"978-0-8166-7794-8","language":"en-US","publisher":"University of Minnesota Press","publisher-place":"Minnesota","title":"Humanistic Theory and Digital Scholarship","title-short":"“Chapter 6","URL":"https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-88c11800-9446-469b-a3be-3fdb36bfbd1e/section/0b495250-97af-4046-91ff-98b6ea9f83c0","author":[{"family":"Drucker","given":"Johanna"}],"editor":[{"family":"Gold","given":"Matthew K."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2022",3,2]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2010"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(2010) states, the digitization of data not only allows for storage but also creates new forms of analysis that expand interpretative possibilities within the humanities.
            </p>
            <p>This proposal builds on Bhaskar's 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"bTzQrHOl","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Bhaskar, 2014)","plainCitation":"(Bhaskar, 2014)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":126,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/4BQFFQKP"],"itemData":{"id":126,"type":"book","event-place":"México","publisher":"Fondo de Cultura Económica","publisher-place":"México","title":"La máquina de contenido. Hacia una teoría de la edición, desde la imprenta hasta las redes digitales","author":[{"family":"Bhaskar","given":"Michael"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2014"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(2014) publishing theory, incorporating the evaluation and editing of digital objects within his concepts of frames/models and filtering/ amplification. Evaluation must combine academic rigor with technical analysis. From an academic perspective, the evaluation must ensure that the digital object meets the highest standards of intellectual rigor, considering the clarity, depth, and relevance of the content within the context of the discipline. Additionally, the evaluation should address aspects such as the interoperability of data, the structure of the object, and its reusability within other research frameworks. To ensure that digital objects can be widely used and shared, it is crucial to apply the FAIR principles, which make objects easily locatable, accessible, and adaptable for future research.
            </p>
            <p>The proposed model emphasizes collaboration throughout the evaluation and editing processes. This process should not be seen as a series of isolated steps but as a joint effort among authors, reviewers, editors, and a wide range of technicians, who collaborate to ensure that the object not only meets academic standards but is also accessible, understandable, and useful to the broader academic community. Interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary collaboration in the evaluation and editing stages is essential to ensure that the digital object is valuable not only from an academic perspective but also from a technical one.</p>
            <p>The editing process ensures academic rigor and technical precision, using standards like Dublin Core, TEI, and protocols like OAI-PMH. It includes the creation of detailed metadata, usage licenses, and methodological notes, which collectively serve as a digital paratext, drawing on Genette's 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"7raJtlIQ","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Genette, 2001)","plainCitation":"(Genette, 2001)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":114,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/8T9T3XIT"],"itemData":{"id":114,"type":"book","event-place":"México","publisher":"Siglo XXI Editores","publisher-place":"México","title":"Umbrales","author":[{"family":"Genette","given":"Gérard"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2001"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(2001) theory of paratext. This paratext provides proper context for the objects and enables their effective use within the academic community. As Bhaskar emphasizes, the frames (or structures) in the digital object not only allow for its correct presentation but also amplify its academic and interpretative potential. The process emphasizes acknowledging contributors—researchers, editors, programmers, and designers—by linking them to recognized identifiers, strengthening the ecosystem and ensuring clear attribution. Furthermore, the inclusion of abstracts, keywords, and technical documentation aids researchers in understanding, locating, and reusing the objects, while addressing intellectual property rights and ensuring the legal status of the content is clearly outlined. This collaborative and structured approach underscores the complex, ongoing nature of curating and maintaining digital academic objects, ensuring they remain valuable and relevant in an evolving research landscape.
            </p>
            <p>Continuous curation is essential as digital objects are modifiable and evolving 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"if5bBQU2","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Kallinikos et\\uc0\\u160{}al., 2010)","plainCitation":"(Kallinikos et al., 2010)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":55,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/YLLBLQSE"],"itemData":{"id":55,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Digital objects are marked by a limited set of variable yet generic attributes such as editability, interactivity, openness and distributedness. As digital objects diffuse throughout the institutional fabric, these attributes and the information-based operations and procedures out of which they are sustained install themselves at the heart of social practice. The entities and processes that constitute the stuff of social practice are thereby rendered increasingly unstable and transfigurable, producing a context of experience in which the certainties of recurring and recognizable objects are on the wane. These claims are supported with reference to 1) the elusive identity of digital documents and the problems of authentication/preservation of records such an identity posits and 2) the operations of search engines and the effects digital search has on the content of the documents it retrieves.","container-title":"First Monday","DOI":"10.5210/fm.v15i6.3033","ISSN":"13960466","issue":"6","language":"en","license":"Copyright (c)","source":"firstmonday.org","title":"A theory of digital objects","URL":"https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/3033","volume":"15","author":[{"family":"Kallinikos","given":"Jannis"},{"family":"Aaltonen","given":"Aleksi"},{"family":"Marton","given":"Attila"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2019",4,27]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2010",6,5]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-family:Aptos">(Kallinikos et al., 2010)</hi>. This implies that curation must not only ensure the preservation of data but also keep it updated and accessible, adapting to new technological and methodological standards. As Borgman 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"FRksiyoO","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Borgman, 2007)","plainCitation":"(Borgman, 2007)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":128,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/D99N88EP"],"itemData":{"id":128,"type":"book","event-place":"Estados Unidos","publisher":"MIT Press","publisher-place":"Estados Unidos","title":"Scholarship in the digital age: information, infrastructure, and the Internet","author":[{"family":"Borgman","given":"Christine L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2007"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(2007) points out, curation of digital objects involves ongoing work to ensure that these objects remain relevant within the academic ecosystem. This adaptability is one of the features that distinguishes digital objects from traditional ones, as they can be reconfigured to address new research questions or be used in innovative methodological approaches. 
            </p>
            <p>The proposed guidelines, focused on evaluation, editing, and curation, has significant implications for knowledge building in the humanities. Digital objects, composed of structured data and semantic representations, enable a new epistemology that goes beyond traditional forms of academic publishing. Priani argues that digital data are not simply objective representations of reality, but constructions that depend on an interpretive framework. This epistemological fragility does not diminish the value of the data but highlights the need for a critical and reflective approach to how data are used and shared in research 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"X8qTYEIk","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(All\\uc0\\u233{}s Torrent, 2019)","plainCitation":"(Allés Torrent, 2019)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":346,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/2696069/items/FDR5JPUN"],"itemData":{"id":346,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Este artículo explora el concepto de datos informáticos aplicados a las Humanidades a través de tres perspectivas diferentes: en primer lugar, se analiza el significado del término desde un punto de vista histórico y se sitúa en el contexto de las Humanidades Digitales prestando atención a su acepción más técnica. A continuación, se discute sobre la naturaleza, las tipologías y se abordan algunos debates de los últimos años, como es el de su aparente objetividad. Por último, y en conexión con la producción, gestión y análisis de los datos, se toma en consideración el fenómeno big data y los desafíos de su aplicación en el terreno de las Humanidades. Se pretende, en definitiva, poner de relieve el papel central de los datos en el quehacer humanístico y cómo, para el humanista actual, existen competencias digitales básicas ineludibles.","container-title":"Revista de Humanidades Digitales","DOI":"10.5944/rhd.vol.4.2019.24679","ISSN":"2531-1786","journalAbbreviation":"RHD","language":"es","page":"1","source":"DOI.org (Crossref)","title":"Sobre la complejidad de los datos en Humanidades, o cómo traducir las ideas a datos","volume":"4","author":[{"family":"Allés Torrent","given":"Susanna"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019",11,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-family:Aptos">(Allés, 2019)</hi>.
            </p>
            <p>In conclusion, this proposal for the evaluation and editing of digital objects ensures they meet high technical and academic standards while recognizing their epistemological value. By integrating open science principles, innovative methodologies, and continuous curation, this proposal seeks to enhance the recognition of DH, enabling the creation of a more flexible, accessible, and dynamic academic communication system.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
