<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="IASHCHENKO_Iuliia_Mapping_Colonial_Devastation__Geo_Technolo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mapping Colonial Devastation: Geo-Technologies and Soviet Nuclear Testing in Central Asia</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Iashchenko</surname>
                        <forename>Iuliia</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>La Sapienza University of Rome, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>iuliia.iashchenko@uniroma1.it</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-05-08T12:29:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Soviet nuclear testing</term>
                    <term>Central Asia</term>
                    <term>geo-technologies</term>
                    <term>environmental colonialism</term>
                    <term>GIS mapping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>eco-criticism and environmental analysis</term>
                    <term>metadata standards</term>
                    <term>systems</term>
                    <term>and methods</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>Anthropology</term>
                    <term>Asian studies</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Environmental</term>
                    <term>ocean</term>
                    <term>and waterway studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                    <term>Match where technical expertise is helpful.</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p> This paper explores the intersection of Soviet environmental colonialism and modern digital humanities by leveraging geo-technologies to analyze the extensive network of nuclear testing sites in Central Asia. Focusing on open-air explosions conducted between 1949 and 1989, particularly in Kazakhstan, the research highlights the Soviet Union’s exploitation of peripheral, indigenous-populated territories for nuclear experimentation. These actions inflicted long-lasting ecological destruction, severe health crises, and cultural erasure upon marginalized communities, consequences that remain understudied. This study uses Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and digital mapping techniques to create a geospatial framework that documents the legacy of these sites and enables the visualization of their impact.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction: Nuclear Colonialism and Ecological Injustice</head>
                    <p>The Soviet Union's nuclear testing programs during the Cold War are emblematic of the state's disregard for the environmental and social consequences of its actions. One of the most extreme examples of this environmental colonialism was the use of Central Asia—particularly Kazakhstan—as a primary location for nuclear tests. From 1949 to 1989, over 450 nuclear tests were conducted at the Semipalatinsk Test Site and other locations, severely impacting the health and livelihoods of local populations, particularly indigenous Kazakhs. These tests, often conducted in remote areas, have left a complex legacy of radiation exposure, environmental degradation, and historical erasure, making it essential to study their effects and bring them to light through modern technological tools.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Geo-Technologies as a Tool for Uncovering Environmental Injustice</head>
                    <p>In recent years, digital humanities has emerged as a powerful tool to address historical injustices, offering new ways to visualize and analyze the impact of past events. This paper uses GIS, remote sensing, and other digital mapping technologies to create a geo-spatial archive of Soviet nuclear test sites in Central Asia. These tools not only document the locations and extent of contamination but also facilitate an interactive approach to understanding the geopolitical dynamics and environmental consequences of Soviet nuclear policy. By combining archival materials with contemporary mapping techniques, this research provides a more comprehensive understanding of the intersection between Soviet environmental colonialism and the region's colonial history.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology: Using GIS for Mapping Nuclear Testing Sites</head>
                    <p>The first step in this project involved collecting historical data on the locations of nuclear testing sites in Kazakhstan and surrounding areas. This data comes from a range of sources: declassified Soviet records, international environmental reports, and survivor testimonies. Once gathered, this information was input into GIS software, such as ArcGIS or QGIS, to create a geospatial model of nuclear test sites. A key element of the analysis was integrating satellite imagery and modern environmental data to assess the current state of the sites and track ongoing contamination levels.</p>
                    <p>The process involved the following steps:</p>
                    <p>1. Data Collection: Archival documents detailing the locations and dates of nuclear tests were acquired from sources such as the Russian State Archives and Kazakhstan’s National Archive. Additionally, environmental reports from organizations like Greenpeace and the UN Environment Programme were used to assess radiation contamination levels in the affected areas. Testimonies from survivors of the nuclear tests provided valuable information on the socio-economic impact of the tests on local populations.</p>
                    <p>2. Georeferencing: A critical step in creating accurate maps was georeferencing historical maps and documents that identified the test sites. Using modern satellite imagery and GPS data, these sites were located on contemporary maps. This process helped to overcome the challenges posed by inconsistent or incomplete historical records.</p>
                    <p>3. Mapping and Visualization: After georeferencing, the data was used to create maps that display the distribution of the nuclear test sites. The resulting maps provide a detailed view of how these sites were scattered across vast, isolated areas, often in regions that were home to indigenous populations. By layering these test sites with environmental data (e.g., radiation levels, water contamination), it became possible to visualize the extent of the environmental and human cost of Soviet nuclear testing.</p>
                    <p>4. Integration of Survivor Testimonies: Testimonies from local survivors, collected through oral history projects, were integrated into the GIS framework to connect the physical and environmental dimensions of nuclear testing with its social and cultural impacts. These testimonies were geolocated and mapped to specific communities, offering a personal dimension to the data and illustrating the human toll of Soviet nuclear policies.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Code for Geospatial Mapping of Nuclear Test Sites</head>
                    <p>To perform these tasks, a few essential Python libraries were used in conjunction with GIS tools. The following code snippet illustrates how to load and visualize geospatial data from a CSV file containing nuclear test site coordinates, and how to plot these locations on a map.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="8.865672222222223cm" url="/tmp/tmpo9pe167z/Pictures/cde3d6b9c6d59d05ec43e57c42ac28ec.png" rend="inline"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>This code uses GeoPandas to read coordinates from a CSV file and plot them on a world map, with test sites marked in red. This is an essential step in creating an interactive map that can be used for further analysis or educational purposes.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Visualizing Impact: GIS as a Tool for Social Justice</head>
                    <p>The mapping of Soviet nuclear test sites also enables the exploration of spatial patterns that reveal the deliberate neglect of indigenous populations. By overlaying radiation maps with historical demographic data, the project shows how indigenous communities in Kazakhstan were disproportionately affected by the nuclear tests. This geographic analysis underscores the extent to which the Soviet state treated these areas as testing grounds for their geopolitical ambitions, ignoring the environmental and health consequences for the local populations.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion: The Legacy of Nuclear Colonialism</head>
                    <p>This research underscores the potential of geo-technologies to uncover hidden histories of colonialism and environmental injustice. By combining historical data, survivor testimonies, and modern GIS tools, the project reveals how Soviet nuclear testing in Central Asia was part of a broader strategy of environmental domination and cultural erasure. The digital maps and visualizations produced in this study not only serve as valuable research tools but also contribute to the broader discussion on ecological justice, decolonization, and the legacy of Soviet policies. These tools provide an accessible platform for continued activism, education, and scholarship focused on the long-lasting effects of Soviet environmental colonialism in Central Asia.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Fialho, Paula / McClure, Andrew (2020): </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">GIS for Environmental Justice: Mapping Environmental Injustice Through Digital Tools</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt">. Cham: Springer.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Lyall, Jason (2019): “Nuclear Colonialism and Environmental Exploitation in Kazakhstan”, in: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Central Asian Studies Journal</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Pilkington, Emily (2020): </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Atomic Bomb and Soviet Nuclear Testing: A Geopolitical History</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt">. London: Routledge.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left;">
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Shkolnik, Alexei / Shmidt, Andrei (2017): “Impact of Nuclear Testing in Kazakhstan: A Geospatial Analysis”, in: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">International Environmental Research</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:12pt">.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
