<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LEVI_Yael_Mapping_Resilience__Multimodal_Digital_Analysis_of">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mapping Resilience: Multimodal Digital Analysis of Immigrant Household Experiences in the United States, 1880–1920</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Levi</surname>
                        <forename>Yael</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel</affiliation>
                    <email>yael.levi1@mail.huji.ac.il</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-30T07:52:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>migration</term>
                    <term>census</term>
                    <term>residential patterns</term>
                    <term>networks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>Geography and geo-humanities</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>This short presentation implements Geospatial analysis of historical US Federal Census from 1890-1920. Drawing on interdisciplinary approaches from the social sciences and humanities, the project explores residential networks and domestic-social habitus. The presentation addresses key questions related to the immigrant household structure and the immigrant family upon migration, such as: Were immigrant families 
                <hi rend="color(474747)" style="font-size:10.5pt">typically</hi> seperated for long periods before reunited in America? What comprised a typical immigrant household? Who hosted boarders, and how many individuals lived as boarders or lodgers? And how did boarders affect the composition and the nature oft he household? By examining these questions, the presentation offers a nuanced understanding of the lived experiences of immigrant families and explores the impact of housing arrangements on the family.
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">M. Ellis, R. Wright, “Assimilation and differences between the settlement patterns of individual immigrants and immigrant households,” Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 102 (43) 15325-15330, https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0507310102 (2005).</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Enchautegui, M.E, “Household Members and Employment Outcomes of Recent Immigrants: A Network Approach,” Social Science Quarterly 83 (2002): 594-611. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/1540-6237.00103">https://doi.org/10.1111/1540-6237.00103</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Standish, K., Nandi, V., Ompad, D.C. et al., “Household Density among Undocumented Mexican Immigrants in New York City,” Journal of Immigrant and Minority Health 12 (2010): 310–318. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-008-9175-x.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Gergely Baics, Wright Kennedy, Rebecca Kobrin, Laura Kurgan, Leah Meisterlin, Dan Miller, Mae Ngai. Mapping Historic New York: A Digital Atlas. New York, NY: Columbia University. 2021. 
                        <ref target="https://mappinghny.com">https://mappinghny.com</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Price, Joseph, Buckles, Kasey, Haws, Adrian, and Wilbert, Haley. The Census Tree, 1910-1920. Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2023-09-14. 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3886/E193252V1">https://doi.org/10.3886/E193252V1</ref>. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Susan Cotts Watkins (Editor), After Ellis Island: Newcomers and Natives in the 1910 Census. New York, NY: Russel Sage Foundation. 1994.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
