<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LI_Yi_How_Is_Gender_Portrayed_on_Preschool_Children_s_Book_C">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>How Is Gender Portrayed on Preschool Children’s Book Covers? An Analysis of the Chinese National Library Catalogue between 2012-2022</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <forename>Yi</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>s2127837@ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <forename>Yongning</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Te Shi Liangcai School of Journalism and Communication, Zhejiang Sci-Tech University, Hangzhou, China</affiliation>
                    <email>lee9512@163.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-03-29T17:09:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Chinese children’s books; library catalogue; metadata; text mining; gender representation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>database creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>mixed-media analysis</term>
                    <term>semantic analysis</term>
                    <term>text mining and analysis</term>
                    <term>Asian studies</term>
                    <term>Feminist studies</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Background</item>
            </list>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The multimodality, especially the visual elements of picture books, empowers preschool children to read and perceive gender and other features independently</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"fRFtbJiy","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Danko-McGhee & Slutsky, 2011; Jalongo, 2004)","plainCitation":"(Danko-McGhee & Slutsky, 2011; Jalongo, 2004)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2497,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/DI4FYJBR"],"itemData":{"id":2497,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This article discusses the results of a research investigation into the aesthetic preferences of young children, aged 2–5, with regard to their choice of picture book covers. The objective was to assess the nature of children’s aesthetic preferences by observing which picture book covers they like as they peruse a selection of them (abstract, representational, colourful, and black and white illustrations). The results of the research indicate that 2-, 3- and 4-year-old children gravitate towards book covers that are representational and colourful and that have images that they are familiar with. Five-year-old children preferred colourful and black and white images. However, the difference, when compared to younger children, is that they liked illustrations that are scary and mysterious. Literacy learning should be child-led with the teacher serving as facilitator during the process. This includes allowing children to have access to a variety of books with covers that are aesthetically pleasing to them, not to adults.","container-title":"International Journal of Education Through Art","DOI":"10.1386/eta.7.2.171_1","ISSN":"1743-5234, 2040-090X","issue":"2","language":"en","note":"publisher: Intellect","page":"171-185","source":"intellectdiscover-com.eux.idm.oclc.org","title":"Judging a book by its cover: Preschool children’s aesthetic preferences for picture books","title-short":"Judging a book by its cover","volume":"7","author":[{"family":"Danko-McGhee","given":"Katherina"},{"family":"Slutsky","given":"Ruslan"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2011",7,12]]}}},{"id":2511,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/DG2LKURI"],"itemData":{"id":2511,"type":"book","abstract":"When adults share picture books with young children, they build their lifelong literacy and enjoyment of reading. In beautiful full color, the new edition of this popular book will help recognize quality in children's literature and illustration and see how to use picture books to best advantage. Following an introduction, this book is organized into the following seven chapters: (1) Importance of Picture Books; (2) Quality in Picture Books; (3) Bringing Children and Books Together; (4) Young Children's Responses to Picture Responses to Picture Books; (5) Acquiring Literacy through Picture Books; (6) Families and Picture Books; and (7) Linking Picture Books with Curriculum. This book concludes with: A Final Word--The Future of Picture Books. The following are appended: (1) Outstanding Picture Book Authors and Illustrators; (2) Internet Resources on Children's Literature; (3) Board Books; and (4) Selected Books for Toddlers, and Resources for Teachers. A list of references is also included.","ISBN":"978-1-928896-15-9","language":"en","note":"container-title: National Association for the Education of Young Children\nERIC Number: ED489849","publisher":"National Association for the Education of Young Children, 1509 16th Street, NW, Washington, DC 20036","source":"ERIC","title":"Young Children and Picture Books. 2nd Edition","author":[{"family":"Jalongo","given":"Mary"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",12,6]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2004"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Danko-McGhee &amp; Slutsky, 2011; Jalongo, 2004)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">. Research suggests preschool children are mostly illiterate, but they can recognise stories or books from covers and illustrations, they are even able to search for books in the libraries by describing the book cover</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"G9MxQvBO","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Danko-McGhee & Slutsky, 2011; Kemple & Lopez, 2009; Li, 2022)","plainCitation":"(Danko-McGhee & Slutsky, 2011; Kemple & Lopez, 2009; Li, 2022)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2497,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/DI4FYJBR"],"itemData":{"id":2497,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This article discusses the results of a research investigation into the aesthetic preferences of young children, aged 2–5, with regard to their choice of picture book covers. The objective was to assess the nature of children’s aesthetic preferences by observing which picture book covers they like as they peruse a selection of them (abstract, representational, colourful, and black and white illustrations). The results of the research indicate that 2-, 3- and 4-year-old children gravitate towards book covers that are representational and colourful and that have images that they are familiar with. Five-year-old children preferred colourful and black and white images. However, the difference, when compared to younger children, is that they liked illustrations that are scary and mysterious. Literacy learning should be child-led with the teacher serving as facilitator during the process. This includes allowing children to have access to a variety of books with covers that are aesthetically pleasing to them, not to adults.","container-title":"International Journal of Education Through Art","DOI":"10.1386/eta.7.2.171_1","ISSN":"1743-5234, 2040-090X","issue":"2","language":"en","note":"publisher: Intellect","page":"171-185","source":"intellectdiscover-com.eux.idm.oclc.org","title":"Judging a book by its cover: Preschool children’s aesthetic preferences for picture books","title-short":"Judging a book by its cover","volume":"7","author":[{"family":"Danko-McGhee","given":"Katherina"},{"family":"Slutsky","given":"Ruslan"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2011",7,12]]}}},{"id":166,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/CIEL4JTK"],"itemData":{"id":166,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"The article reviews several books including \"Two eyes, a nose, and a mouth,\" by Roberta Grobel Intrater, \"All the colors of the Earth\" by S. Hamanaka, and \"The colors of us,\" by K. Katz.","container-title":"Dimensions of Early Childhood","ISSN":"10686177","issue":"1","page":"23-30","source":"EBSCOhost","title":"Blue Eyes, Brown Eyes, Cornrows, and Curls: Building on Books to Explore Physical Diversity With Preschool Children","title-short":"Blue Eyes, Brown Eyes, Cornrows, and Curls","volume":"37","author":[{"family":"Kemple","given":"Kristen M."},{"family":"Lopez","given":"Maria"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2009"]],"season":"Winter"}}},{"id":988,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/SV54GK4A"],"itemData":{"id":988,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Children’s picture books are the first books that children come into contact with. They are an important carrier for children to contact and perceive the outside world and are essential for children to form subconscious and basic cognition of the world. Because of the particularity of picture books’ audience, picture books must be specially processed before they can be recognized by children and parents, and as children’s enlightening reading materials, their cultural attributes cannot be ignored. Compared with foreign countries, picture books in China started late, drawing lessons from and imitating western picture books to a certain extent, which led to the shadow of western culture in picture book materials, which was not conducive to children’s cognition and recognition of Chinese traditional culture, and even more detrimental to their cultural confidence. As future preschool educators, preschool education majors are the first teachers of children’s culture and life and also users of children’s picture books. Therefore, it is of practical significance for preschool education majors to know and understand children’s picture books. Firstly, this paper points out the significance and main methods of studying children’s picture books and summarizes the development status of picture books at home and abroad. Secondly, it expounds the important functions of children’s picture books, explores the characteristics of children’s psychology and behavior, and explores the development direction and related theories of children’s picture books. Finally, from the perspective of preschool education majors, we understand the educational value of children’s picture books that the design of picture books should meet the needs of children and point out that children’s picture books are the enlightenment education of Chinese culture and revolutionary spirit. This paper discusses the related understanding of children’s picture books from the perspective of preschool education majors and expounds the significance of children’s picture books for children’s enlightenment education from the aspects of picture book development, picture book function, education and enlightenment value, etc., to carry out theoretical research for the development of picture books in China and help the brand and product development of picture books.","container-title":"Wireless Communications and Mobile Computing","DOI":"10.1155/2022/9697874","ISSN":"1530-8669","language":"en","note":"publisher: Hindawi","page":"e9697874","source":"www.hindawi.com","title":"Preschool Education Students’ Understanding of Children’s Picture Books","volume":"2022","author":[{"family":"Li","given":"Shengnan"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022",7,30]]}},"ignoreRetraction":true}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Danko-McGhee &amp; Slutsky, 2011; Kemple &amp; Lopez, 2009; Li, 2022)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">. Therefore, gender representations in these titles would influence how children see and think of gender by emphasising characters, narratives and storytelling</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"cHuT6DPh","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Bal & Veltkamp, 2013; Bartholomaeus, 2016; Caple & Tian, 2022; Faver & Alanis, 2012)","plainCitation":"(Bal & Veltkamp, 2013; Bartholomaeus, 2016; Caple & Tian, 2022; Faver & Alanis, 2012)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":354,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/83UYYFHT"],"itemData":{"id":354,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"PLoS ONE","DOI":"10.1371/journal.pone.0055341","ISSN":"1932-6203","issue":"1","journalAbbreviation":"PLoS ONE","language":"en","page":"e55341","source":"DOI.org (Crossref)","title":"How Does Fiction Reading Influence Empathy? An Experimental Investigation on the Role of Emotional Transportation","title-short":"How Does Fiction Reading Influence Empathy?","volume":"8","author":[{"family":"Bal","given":"P. Matthijs"},{"family":"Veltkamp","given":"Martijn"}],"editor":[{"family":"Young","given":"Liane"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2013",1,30]]}}},{"id":726,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/53WZ63JT"],"itemData":{"id":726,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Few studies have examined children's understandings of feminist picture books, and thus their potential usefulness for disrupting dominant discourses and providing alternate storylines. This article draws on research conducted in Australia with a class of 6- and 7-year-olds, examining students’ responses to four feminist picture books. The students provided diverse responses to the books, at times reflecting what I viewed as the (feminist) messages of the books and sometimes picking up on other themes or (re)interpreting them as supporting dominant gender discourses. The challenges to understanding the books in straightforward ways related both to the books themselves as well as the gender discourses available to the students. This article argues that there are three key challenges to the feminist potential of these books: a reliance on categories of ‘girl’ and ‘boy’, children's lack of identification with book characters, and the influence of intertextual knowledge.","container-title":"Gender & Education","DOI":"10.1080/09540253.2015.1106443","ISSN":"09540253","issue":"7","note":"publisher: Routledge","page":"935-950","source":"EBSCOhost","title":"‘Girls can like boy toys’: junior primary school children's understandings of feminist picture books","title-short":"‘Girls can like boy toys’","volume":"28","author":[{"family":"Bartholomaeus","given":"Clare"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016",12]]}}},{"id":730,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/QVG7T2AD"],"itemData":{"id":730,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This article examines the visual and verbal expressions of gender in Australian award-winning early childhood picture books. It brings together social semiotic analysis and the narratological concepts of narration and focalization to examine the extent to which one community of practice (authors, illustrators, publishers and awards council) reproduces symbolic manifestations of gender, or offers readers space to engage with alternatives. The authors? findings suggest that, while the literary works produced by this community of practice mostly serve to reinforce hegemonic cultural attitudes of what constitutes desirable femininity and masculinity in Australia, there is ample opportunity for change.","container-title":"Visual Communication","DOI":"10.1177/14703572211069604","ISSN":"1470-3572","journalAbbreviation":"Visual Communication","note":"publisher: SAGE Publications","page":"14703572211069604","source":"SAGE Journals","title":"Opening up semiotic spaces for gender expression: a case study of the construction of gender in Australian award-winning early childhood picture books","title-short":"Opening up semiotic spaces for gender expression","author":[{"family":"Caple","given":"Helen"},{"family":"Tian","given":"Ping"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022",1,27]]}}},{"id":338,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/4YYIP5C3"],"itemData":{"id":338,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Special needs children with a history of maltreatment often have behavioral and emotional difficulties that pose challenges for adoptive parents. In response to the need for support services for adoptive parents and children, this project used stories to foster empathy and enhance communication in special needs adoptive families. Eight families, including fourteen parents and seventeen children, participated in the program. An evaluative survey indicated that the program prompted parent–child discussions, provided support to adoptive parents, and helped parents view the adoption experience from their children's perspective. The findings suggest that stories can be used to address the challenging emotional issues confronting adoptive families of special needs children.","container-title":"Children and Youth Services Review","DOI":"10.1016/j.childyouth.2011.12.012","ISSN":"0190-7409","issue":"4","journalAbbreviation":"Children and Youth Services Review","language":"en","page":"660-665","source":"ScienceDirect","title":"Fostering empathy through stories: A pilot program for special needs adoptive families","title-short":"Fostering empathy through stories","volume":"34","author":[{"family":"Faver","given":"Catherine A."},{"family":"Alanis","given":"Erika"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2012",4,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Bal &amp; Veltkamp, 2013; Bartholomaeus, 2016; Caple &amp; Tian, 2022; Faver &amp; Alanis, 2012)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">. Library catalogues are filtered by librarians annually, and book selections are usually reviewed by experts in the children’s literature field. Library is a place to assist children’s right to search for information</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"vW5dyl5a","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Brock & Rankin, 2012, p. 75; Busayo, 2011)","plainCitation":"(Brock & Rankin, 2012, p. 75; Busayo, 2011)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2529,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/Z7MZAJE4"],"itemData":{"id":2529,"type":"chapter","abstract":"IntroductionThis chapter will help to provide the evidence as to why libraries are successful at reaching and engaging their communities in reading activities. It presents underpinning theory and research about effective provision and draws on the rich practice occurring in both school and public libraries in the UK and internationally. Perspectives and commentary from library practitioners are included, as they are actively involved in planning and delivering services and resources. Viewpoints from children and young people are also included, as their needs and desires need to be recognized by adults. This provides authentic, rich evidence about the benefits of partnership.The chapter will discuss popular culture and will examine issues surrounding age and gender, reflecting on the attitudes and specific needs of boys and girls, both at home and at school. The valuing of cultural and linguistic diversity will also permeate the discussions, as libraries need to provide a welcoming ethos and specifically target groups, in order to connect and engage different audiences. As a result of reading this chapter, the reader should be aware of the rights of children to have access to information and resources to support their personal interests, educational attainment and enhanced family lives.Reading, learning and a life-long love of booksCompetence in literacy is essential for a successful life in contemporary society, and it dramatically contributes to people's emotional well-being, mental health and economic success. This section demonstrates how a range of particular skills, a breadth of reading materials, a depth of understanding and positive attitudes are important for children and young people becoming capable competent and active readers. The responsibility involved in achieving this not only lies with the children and young people themselves, but also with parents, teachers, librarians and politicians. Books and other literacy materials, public libraries, schools and school libraries all have roles to play in the successful achievement of developing youngsters who will read for pleasure, for information and knowledge acquisition and for educational attainment. How they engage in the reading process, the materials they access and their developing attitudes to reading are all key elements in achieving competence in literacy.","container-title":"Library Services for Children and Young People: Challenges and Opportunities in the Digital Age","ISBN":"978-1-85604-898-9","note":"DOI: 10.29085/9781856048989.007","page":"65-88","publisher":"Facet","source":"Cambridge University Press","title":"Libraries, literacy and popular culture – let's get reading!","URL":"https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/library-services-for-children-and-young-people/libraries-literacy-and-popular-culture-lets-get-reading/5C45704D3187F88E8B32837B44DE01D2","editor":[{"family":"Brock","given":"Avril"},{"family":"Rankin","given":"Carolynn"}],"author":[{"family":"Brock","given":"Avril"},{"family":"Rankin","given":"Carolynn"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",12,7]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2012"]]}},"locator":"75","label":"page"},{"id":1023,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/893DVTPD"],"itemData":{"id":1023,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"<em>Gale</em> Academic OneFile includes The school library as a foundational step to childrens& by Isaac Oluwadare Busayo. Click to explore.","container-title":"Library Philosophy and Practice","ISSN":"15220222","language":"English","note":"publisher: University of Nebraska-Lincoln","source":"go-gale-com.eux.idm.oclc.org","title":"The school library as a foundational step to childrens' effective reading habits","URL":"https://go.gale.com/ps/i.do?p=AONE&sw=w&issn=15220222&v=2.1&it=r&id=GALE%7CA277107197&sid=googleScholar&linkaccess=abs","author":[{"family":"Busayo","given":"Isaac Oluwadare"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",8,19]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2011",11,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Brock &amp; Rankin, 2012, p. 75; Busayo, 2011)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">, library catalogues should be inclusive and cover different aspects of life, including gender. Book covers and titles, aside from the main body, are important parts of peritext</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"FXNgRtOM","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Genette, 1997)","plainCitation":"(Genette, 1997)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2481,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/2DGS3ZSN"],"itemData":{"id":2481,"type":"book","abstract":"Paratexts are those liminal devices and conventions, both within and outside the book, that form part of the complex mediation between book, author, publisher and reader: titles, forewords, epigraphs and publishers' jacket copy are part of a book's private and public history. In this first English translation of Paratexts, Gérard Genette shows how the special pragmatic status of paratextual declaration requires a carefully calibrated analysis of their illocutionary force. With clarity, precision and an extraordinary range of reference, Paratexts constitutes an encyclopedic survey of the customs and institutions as revealed in the borderlands of the text. Genette presents a global view of these liminal mediations and the logic of their relation to the reading public by studying each element as a literary function.","ISBN":"978-0-511-87999-9","publisher":"Cambridge University Press","source":"ACLS Humanities EBook","title":"Ebook of Paratexts: Thresholds of Interpretation","title-short":"Ebook of Paratexts","URL":"https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb40164.0001.001","author":[{"family":"Genette","given":"Gerard"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",10,21]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["1997"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Genette, 1997)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and can reveal the beginning of storytelling in preschool books</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Lw5usvZk","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Solomon Eaglstein & Berman, 1990)","plainCitation":"(Solomon Eaglstein & Berman, 1990)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":227,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/LWFGBHUY"],"itemData":{"id":227,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"In 1966, Clive Bingley described a blurb: A good blurb has a beginning, a middle and an end, a light style and a definite point to make about the content or purpose of the book, as well as an expression of the publisher's own confidence in its merits. This definition specifies that a good blurb contains at least the elements of book praise and book subject matter. Based upon Bingley's definition wide‐ranging and indepth analysis were carried out both within the blurbs of one book and between several books. The sample of books selected for the study were drawn from the fields of sociology, education and psychology and were analysed by the four elements of an analytical framework. Element one of the framework concerned the presence or absence of praise or subject matter in a blurb. Element two dealt with the substantive categories of these two variables. Element three related to a set of other blurb descriptors. Element four consisted of an additional set of variables describing the books of the sample. Combination of simple marginal and cross‐tabulational analysis with appropriate parametric and non‐parametric statistical methods were applied for analysing each element and the relationship of all four elements. The most salient finding was that the Bingley definition proved to serve as a valuable heuristic tool for blurbology, i.e. the scientific study of the blurb. Operationally this meant that no blurbs were found that lacked information concerning praise and subject matter. Further, it was found that praise was a ubiquitous phenomenon. It appeared in over 95% of the blurbs and was consistently high both within and between books. On the other hand, the appearance of other blurb content and descriptor variables was less frequent and more diffuse. There was no evidence of any systematic relationship between book descriptor variables and blurb content. Suggestions for objective and independent research testing blurb selling power were submitted.","container-title":"Aslib Proceedings","DOI":"10.1108/eb051156","ISSN":"0001-253X","issue":"1","note":"publisher: MCB UP Ltd","page":"17-30","source":"Emerald Insight","title":"You can tell a book by its cover: an analysis of blurbs","title-short":"You can tell a book by its cover","volume":"42","author":[{"family":"Solomon Eaglstein","given":"A."},{"family":"Berman","given":"Yitzhak"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1990",1,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Solomon Eaglstein &amp; Berman, 1990)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">. Previous studies examined book covers focus on their functions for books and diverse styles and designing</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"i5sz6iuh","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Gruppetta, 2008; Osvath, 2021)","plainCitation":"(Gruppetta, 2008; Osvath, 2021)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":134,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/GA88YGHT"],"itemData":{"id":134,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"The Bookseller","ISSN":"00067539","issue":"5357","language":"English","note":"publisher: Bookseller Media Limited","page":"24-27","source":"go-gale-com.ezproxy.is.ed.ac.uk","title":"Getting them hooked: how can publishers entice children to pick up books and buy them? Start with the cover design, argues Chris Gruppetta, but make sure the jacket is flashy, the blurb exciting and the book has street cred","title-short":"Getting them hooked","author":[{"family":"Gruppetta","given":"Chris"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2008",11,7]]}}},{"id":1053,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/QW9CAGLD"],"itemData":{"id":1053,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Picture books are important mediums for transformation and learning. They offer both the tools and the truths for readers to critically engage with important issues, such as the reality of death and dying. The primary purpose of this study is to inspire engaged and deliberate conversations about mortality, dying, and grief in the context of picture books. I also present a new methodology of analyzing the cover arts of death-themed picture books. This method is influenced by M. M. Bakhtin’s (\nThe dialogic imagination: four essays\n. The University of Texas Press, Austin, 2006) dialogism and Lois Rosenblatt’s (\nThe reader, the text, the poem: the transactional theory of the literary work\n. Southern Illinois University Press, Carbondale, 1978) work on transactional theory and aesthetic reading. In order to gain a deeper understanding of how death is portrayed/represented through visual or linguistic expressions, my inquiry centers on the following questions: In what ways do artists/illustrators use text and images to depict death on the covers/jacket design of picture books related to death and dying? Through a dialogic, aesthetic engagement with death-themed book covers, what meaning can arise related to death as a phenomenon and a social construct? Also, how this meaning can lead to individual transformation and new ways picture books are used in personal and educational settings?","container-title":"Children's literature in education","DOI":"10.1007/s10583-020-09399-5","ISSN":"0045-6713","issue":"1","language":"eng","note":"publisher-place: Dordrecht\npublisher: Springer Netherlands","page":"68–87","source":"discovered.ed.ac.uk","title":"Uncovering Death: A Dialogic, Aesthetic Engagement with the Covers of Death-Themed Picture Books","title-short":"Uncovering Death","volume":"52","author":[{"family":"Osvath","given":"Csaba"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2021"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Gruppetta, 2008; Osvath, 2021)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">, but lack analysis from a gender perspective based on digital methods. To merge the gap, this study applies a combination of ChatGPT and text mining on the Chinese children’s library catalogues with a 10-year timeline (2012-2022).</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Method
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Data Collection</item>
                    </list>
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">We collected the children’s book catalogue of the National Library of China between 2012 and 2022</hi><ref n="1" target="ftn1"/>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and selected books that target 0-6-year-old young readers as our research objects. We then searched ISBN for all titles on Douban (the largest reading community in China, equalise Goodreads)</hi><ref n="2" target="ftn2"/>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">, and crawled book covers of all 6,229 titles to make up the initial dataset using Python.</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">Data process</hi>
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">We first uploaded book covers of 6,229 titles one by one. In the initial stage, we asked ChatGPT</hi><ref n="3" target="ftn3"/>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">two questions for each title: 1) Is gender inferred in the book title? If so, what is it? 2) Are there any other elements suggesting gender? If so, what are they? </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">For each title, we will get two independent textual answers judging gender expressions from the book title and illustrations on book covers. Answers are semi-structured, suggesting if the title and illustrations infer gender or not, with further explaining the gendered word/phrase. For example, in the answer for a book title “Yes, gender is inferred in the book title <hi rend="Chinese">这是我爸爸 </hi>(</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">This Is My Dad</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"vzH7rx8z","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Hout, 2022)","plainCitation":"(Hout, 2022)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2526,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/3T5XJDRP"],"itemData":{"id":2526,"type":"book","abstract":"Let's guess together, who is the father of the little animal? Open the book, on the two-page spread, there is an animal or insect childhood on the left, and there are four options on the right. Each animal has some of the characteristics of an animal when it was a child, but who is the real dad? The seemingly simple design is actually quite challenging and requires young readers to mobilize their existing life experience and cognitive experience to answer.","edition":"First Edition","ISBN":"978-7-5589-1000-5","language":"Chinese","publisher":"Shao Nian Er Tong Chu Ban She","source":"Amazon","title":"This Is My Father","author":[{"family":"Hout","given":"Mies Von"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022",1,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Hout, 2022)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">. The term <hi rend="Chinese">爸爸 </hi>(dad) explicitly refers to a male parent, so the gender of the subject, "dad," is male”(ChatGPT 4.0, 2024), ChatGPT recognise the title includes a male character and identify the gender word “<hi rend="Chinese">爸爸</hi>dad”. Similar answer structure are reported for the analysis of illustrations on book covers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">To check the precision of ChatGPT in gender detection, the two authors manually coded the first 60 books and compared them with ChatGPT answers. The Kappa coefficient for inter-rater reliability was 0.82, suggesting substantial agreement between coders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">To follow up, ChatGPT answers will make up a final corpus for our further analysis. We will use the term frequency to analyse the recurrences of gender/non-gender titles, classify the uses of different elements in illustrations to portray gender, and see how they vary from time (publication date) and book genre (CLCS</hi><ref n="4" target="ftn4"/>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">).</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Figure 1</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Research Process: Gender Detection on Children’s Library Catalogue of NLC</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Results</item>
            </list>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The results of this paper will be presented at the conference.</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">Implications</hi>
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This study uses ChatGPT 4.0 to recognise gender embedded in preschool children’s books which are displayed in Chinese public libraries. It will reveal the semantic networks and associations between words to imply gender in children’s books. Based on the large language model, ChatGPT can exhibit gender perceptions for book covers from a public perspective, although it might also reflect gender biases</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"wXEYY0wd","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Alexopoulos, Lyons, Mahetaji, Barnes, & Gutwillinger, 2023; Gross, 2023; Sebo, 2024)","plainCitation":"(Alexopoulos, Lyons, Mahetaji, Barnes, & Gutwillinger, 2023; Gross, 2023; Sebo, 2024)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2521,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/8WA9IQW9"],"itemData":{"id":2521,"type":"article","abstract":"An increasing number of studies use gender information to understand phenomena such as gender bias, inequity in access and participation, or the impact of the Covid pandemic response. Unfortunately, most datasets do not include self-reported gender information, making it necessary for researchers to infer gender from other information, such as names or names and country information. An important limitation of these tools is that they fail to appropriately capture the fact that gender exists on a non-binary scale, however, it remains important to evaluate and compare how well these tools perform in a variety of contexts. In this paper, we compare the performance of a generative Artificial Intelligence (AI) tool ChatGPT with three commercially available list-based and machine learning-based gender inference tools (Namsor, Gender-API, and genderize.io) on a unique dataset. Specifically, we use a large Olympic athlete dataset and report how variations in the input (e.g., first name and first and last name, with and without country information) impact the accuracy of their predictions. We report results for the full set, as well as for the subsets: medal versus non-medal winners, athletes from the largest English-speaking countries, and athletes from East Asia. On these sets, we find that Namsor is the best traditional commercially available tool. However, ChatGPT performs at least as well as Namsor and often outperforms it, especially for the female sample when country and/or last name information is available. All tools perform better on medalists versus non-medalists and on names from English-speaking countries. Although not designed for this purpose, ChatGPT may be a cost-effective tool for gender prediction. In the future, it might even be possible for ChatGPT or other large scale language models to better identify self-reported gender rather than report gender on a binary scale.","DOI":"10.48550/arXiv.2312.00805","note":"arXiv:2312.00805","number":"arXiv:2312.00805","publisher":"arXiv","source":"arXiv.org","title":"Gender inference: can chatGPT outperform common commercial tools?","title-short":"Gender inference","URL":"http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00805","author":[{"family":"Alexopoulos","given":"Michelle"},{"family":"Lyons","given":"Kelly"},{"family":"Mahetaji","given":"Kaushar"},{"family":"Barnes","given":"Marcus Emmanuel"},{"family":"Gutwillinger","given":"Rogan"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",12,7]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023",11,24]]}}},{"id":2518,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/AFT3PZMW"],"itemData":{"id":2518,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"<em>Gale</em> Academic OneFile includes What ChatGPT Tells Us about Gender: A Cautionary Tale a by Nicole Gross. Click to explore.","container-title":"Social Sciences","DOI":"10.3390/socsci12080435","ISSN":"20760760","issue":"8","language":"English","note":"publisher: MDPI AG","page":"NA-NA","source":"go-gale-com.eux.idm.oclc.org","title":"What ChatGPT Tells Us about Gender: A Cautionary Tale about Performativity and Gender Biases in AI.","title-short":"What ChatGPT Tells Us about Gender","volume":"12","author":[{"family":"Gross","given":"Nicole"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023",8,1]]}}},{"id":2515,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/5848688/items/3SFQUXJT"],"itemData":{"id":2515,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"JMIR AI","DOI":"10.2196/53656","ISSN":"2817-1705","journalAbbreviation":"JMIR AI","note":"PMID: 38875596\nPMCID: PMC11041478","page":"e53656","source":"PubMed Central","title":"What Is the Performance of ChatGPT in Determining the Gender of Individuals Based on Their First and Last Names?","volume":"3","author":[{"family":"Sebo","given":"Paul"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2024",3,13]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Alexopoulos, Lyons, Mahetaji, Barnes, &amp; Gutwillinger, 2023; Gross, 2023; Sebo, 2024)</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and need to be improved. However, this will help librarians identify gender role assumptions and be aware of gender biases in categorising titles for future practice, thus improving gender equality and boosting diverse representations in the library collection of preschool children’s books.</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
<div type="notes">
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                     The catalogue was published on the website of the National Library of China on 3/1/2024. Data can be publicly accessed at: 
                        <ref target="http://kids.nlc.cn/srtsg/sytc/20240104_2637583.shtml">http://kids.nlc.cn/srtsg/sytc/20240104_2637583.shtml</ref>
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                     See 
                        <ref target="https://www.douban.com">https://www.douban.com</ref> to access Douban. Compared to WorldCat which is an open online platform and provides library archives and collections, Douban provides covers for Chinese books with high resolution.
                    
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                     ChatGPT supports Chinese and provides English analysis.
                </note>
<note rend="footnote text" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                     Chinese Library Classification System, see at 
                        <ref target="https://www.clcindex.com">https://www.clcindex.com</ref>
                    
                </note></div>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Alexopoulos, M., Lyons, K., Mahetaji, K., Barnes, M. E., &amp; Gutwillinger, R. (2023, November 24). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Gender inference: Can chatGPT outperform common commercial tools?</hi> arXiv. doi: 10.48550/arXiv.2312.00805
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Bal, P. M., &amp; Veltkamp, M. (2013). How Does Fiction Reading Influence Empathy? An Experimental Investigation on the Role of Emotional Transportation. 
                        <hi rend="italic">PLoS ONE</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">8</hi>(1), e55341. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0055341
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Bartholomaeus, C. (2016). ‘Girls can like boy toys’: Junior primary school children’s understandings of feminist picture books. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Gender &amp; Education</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">28</hi>(7), 935–950. doi: 10.1080/09540253.2015.1106443
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Brock, A., &amp; Rankin, C. (2012). Libraries, literacy and popular culture – let’s get reading! In A. Brock &amp; C. Rankin (Eds.), 
                        <hi rend="italic">Library Services for Children and Young People: Challenges and Opportunities in the Digital Age</hi> (pp. 65–88). Facet. doi: 10.29085/9781856048989.007
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Busayo, I. O. (2011). The school library as a foundational step to childrens’ effective reading habits. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Library Philosophy and Practice</hi>. Retrieved from https://go.gale.com/ps/i.do?p=AONE&amp;sw=w&amp;issn=15220222&amp;v=2.1&amp;it=r&amp;id=GALE%7CA277107197&amp;sid=googleScholar&amp;linkaccess=abs
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Caple, H., &amp; Tian, P. (2022). Opening up semiotic spaces for gender expression: A case study of the construction of gender in Australian award-winning early childhood picture books. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Visual Communication</hi>, 14703572211069604. doi: 10.1177/14703572211069604
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Danko-McGhee, K., &amp; Slutsky, R. (2011). Judging a book by its cover: Preschool children’s aesthetic preferences for picture books. 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Education Through Art</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">7</hi>(2), 171–185. doi: 10.1386/eta.7.2.171_1
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Faver, C. A., &amp; Alanis, E. (2012). Fostering empathy through stories: A pilot program for special needs adoptive families. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Children and Youth Services Review</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">34</hi>(4), 660–665. doi: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2011.12.012
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Genette, G. (1997). 
                        <hi rend="italic">Ebook of Paratexts: Thresholds of Interpretation</hi>. Cambridge University Press. Retrieved from https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb40164.0001.001
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Gross, N. (2023). What ChatGPT Tells Us about Gender: A Cautionary Tale about Performativity and Gender Biases in AI. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Social Sciences</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">12</hi>(8), NA-NA. doi: 10.3390/socsci12080435
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Gruppetta, C. (2008). Getting them hooked: How can publishers entice children to pick up books and buy them? Start with the cover design, argues Chris Gruppetta, but make sure the jacket is flashy, the blurb exciting and the book has street cred. 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Bookseller</hi>, (5357), 24–27.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Hout, M. V. (2022). 
                        <hi rend="italic">This Is My Father</hi> (First Edition). Shao Nian Er Tong Chu Ban She.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Jalongo, M. (2004). Young Children and Picture Books. 2nd Edition. In 
                        <hi rend="italic">National Association for the Education of Young Children</hi>. National Association for the Education of Young Children, 1509 16th Street, NW, Washington, DC 20036.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Kemple, K. M., &amp; Lopez, M. (2009). Blue Eyes, Brown Eyes, Cornrows, and Curls: Building on Books to Explore Physical Diversity With Preschool Children. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Dimensions of Early Childhood</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">37</hi>(1), 23–30.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Li, S. (2022). Preschool Education Students’ Understanding of Children’s Picture Books. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Wireless Communications and Mobile Computing</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">2022</hi>, e9697874. doi: 10.1155/2022/9697874
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Osvath, C. (2021). Uncovering Death: A Dialogic, Aesthetic Engagement with the Covers of Death-Themed Picture Books. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Children’s Literature in Education</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">52</hi>(1), 68–87. doi: 10.1007/s10583-020-09399-5
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Sebo, P. (2024). What Is the Performance of ChatGPT in Determining the Gender of Individuals Based on Their First and Last Names? 
                        <hi rend="italic">JMIR AI</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">3</hi>, e53656. doi: 10.2196/53656
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Solomon Eaglstein, A., &amp; Berman, Y. (1990). You can tell a book by its cover: An analysis of blurbs. 
                        <hi rend="italic">Aslib Proceedings</hi>, 
                        <hi rend="italic">42</hi>(1), 17–30. doi: 10.1108/eb051156
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
