<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="REVILLA_SANCHEZ_Sarah_Reading_Spanish_NovEllas_through_an_An">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Reading Spanish NovEllas through an Antiracist, Inclusive, and Feminist Text Encoding Framework</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Revilla-Sanchez</surname>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of British Columbia, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>revillas@student.ubc.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Lagresa-González</surname>
                        <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of British Columbia, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>elizabeth.lagresa@ubc.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-03-29T17:09:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>TEI schema</term>
                    <term>Antiracist</term>
                    <term>Inclusive</term>
                    <term>Novellas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>bibliographic analysis</term>
                    <term>manuscripts description</term>
                    <term>representation</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>public humanities collaborations and methods</term>
                    <term>text encoding and markup language creation</term>
                    <term>deployment</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Cultural studies</term>
                    <term>Feminist studies</term>
                    <term>Gender and sexuality studies</term>
                    <term>Literary studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">The proposed short paper will introduce some of the work conducted by “The Adaptive Text Encoding Initiative Network,” an interdisciplinary research group of PhD students, faculty, and DH librarians affiliated to The University of British Columbia and Simon Fraser University in Canada. Working across various departments in The Faculty of Arts (Hispanic Studies, English Literatures, and Central and Eastern European Studies), we are co-developing an antiracist, decolonial, and inclusive framework for encoding and analyzing digitized texts. The new TEI schema that we are co-writing will be submitted for approval to the TEI Council. Once the proposed elements become part of the TEI standard, any project that uses XML-TEI will be able to access and employ these antiracist and inclusive schema in their own markup practices and interventions. The presentation will consist of two parts. First, we will report and reflect on the Network’s progress one year after it was initially funded (May 2024) and outline the steps we are taking to advance our collaborative work. Next, focusing on one of the projects developed by the Network, we will provide some insights into the antiracist, decolonial, and inclusive TEI guidelines we are proposing as a team.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">As will be further explained with our case study on the NovElla project, the work conducted by the Network is aligned with the objectives of open science and the efforts for democratizing access to knowledge. However, given that our research group is currently housed in English-speaking Canadian universities, our training and resources for learning the markup language XML-TEI is predominantly adapted from/to Anglocentric texts and Western Cultures. This has not only posed a challenge for four team members who are studying Latin American and peninsular literatures, but it has also made us aware of some larger limitations around producing bilingual (Spanish/English) projects and their global impact. Despite ongoing efforts to translate TEI resources and guidelines into Spanish to make them accessible across the globe, there is a significant gap in access to technology and material resources between the Global North and the Global South (Allés-Torrent and del Rio Riande 2019). Furthermore, we must consider the “power imbalances and multinational exploitative mechanisms that are literally hardwired into the digital architecture of Latin America” (Raynor and Lewis 2023: 274). In dialogue with previous scholarship, our TEI project seeks to address unequal opportunities for knowledge exchange and research dissemination in the Spanish-speaking world. As our Network grows, we want to ensure that this TEI project will also be shaped by insights and research beyond North America. To address this gap, we are actively seeking opportunities to partner with research institutions in Latin America. By the time we are submitting this proposal, we are awaiting response on two grant applications that will allow us to expand our network beyond these two Canadian universities by partnering with similar projects in The United States and Argentina.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">In the proposed presentation, we will begin by sharing our progress since the Network’s initial creation. As a multilingual and multi-disciplinary group, some of the challenges we are currently navigating are: 1) insufficient TEI training available to members, particularly framed around Spanish language, texts, and cultures; 2) lack of institutional guidelines to properly recognize and validate collaborative work at the dissertation level; and 3) finding institutional support to expand our Network and research impact beyond Canada and English-speaking Higher Education institutions and with community partners. Next, we will present on one of the projects in the Network. The NovElla project aims to analyze and compare digitized versions of 17th-century “novellas” (short prose fiction) written by Spanish women. This digital project will include annotated bilingual (Spanish and English) transcriptions of novella case studies, a catalog of annotated bibliographies of primary and secondary sources, summaries of the novellas, identifications of sub-genres and main themes, as well as a timeline. This virtual hub aims to increase visibility of the literary production of the only five presently known female novella writers of this period and present them in dialogue with each other for the first time: María de Zayas y Sotomayor, Leonor de Meneses, Mariana de Carvajal y Saavedra, María Egual and Ana Francisca Abarca de Bolea y Mur. Our proposed antiracist and inclusive TEI schema will also draw on Gender and Sexuality theories and Feminist Studies. The Adaptive TEI Network, rooted in a team-oriented ethos, offers alternative ways of conducting collaborative research among early career scholars and experienced professors with a shared interest in developing open and accessible digital humanities projects.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Allés-Torrent, Susanna / del Rio Riande, Gimena 
                            <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">(2019): </hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">“</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold">
                            <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">The Switchover: Teaching and Learning the Text Encoding Initiative in Spanish”,</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">in: Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative 
                            <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">12: </hi>1-29 
                        </hi>
                        <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/2994">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/2994</hi>
                        </ref>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> [28.04.2024]</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">  </hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Raynor, Cecily / Rhian Lewis </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">(2023): </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Digital Encounters: Envisioning Connectivity in Latin American Cultural Production</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">. Toronto: University of Toronto Press.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
