<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ULM_Kerry_Marie_Examining_Digital_Humanities_Projects_throug">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Examining Digital Humanities Projects through the Lens of Technical and Professional Communication</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Ulm</surname>
                        <forename>Kerry Marie</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>The Ohio State University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>ulm.16@osu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-30T13:30:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>technical and professional communication</term>
                    <term>content analysis</term>
                    <term>web design</term>
                    <term>user interface design</term>
                    <term>accessibility</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>Interface design</term>
                    <term>development</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>user experience design and analysis</term>
                    <term>Design studies</term>
                    <term>Disability and differently-abled studies</term>
                    <term>Literacy</term>
                    <term>composition</term>
                    <term>and creative writing</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The field of technical and professional communication (TPC) explores topics that naturally overlap with digital humanities (DH.) However, this overlap has not been fully explored. This presentation argues that DH would benefit from additional research conducted through the lens of TPC. It also reports the findings of a study that uses TPC methods to examine the genre of DH project websites. </p>
            <p> According to Carolyn Rude, the central research question in TPC is “how do texts (print, digital, multimedia; visual, verbal) and related communication practices mediate knowledge, values, and action in a variety of social and professional contexts?” 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"R0SdeqD4","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Rude, 2009)","plainCitation":"(Rude, 2009)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":565,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/N2HBJCB7"],"itemData":{"id":565,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Agreement about research questions can strengthen disciplinary identity and give direction to a field that is still maturing. The central research question this article poses foregrounds texts, broadly defined as verbal, visual, and multimedia, and the power of texts to mediate knowledge, values, and action in a variety of contexts. Related questions concern disciplinarity, pedagogy, practice, and social change. These questions overlap and inform each other. Any single study does not necessarily fall exclusively into one area. A mapping of a field's research questions is a political act, emphasizing some questions and marginalizing or excluding others. The emphases may change over time. This mapping illustrates reasons for the tensions between the academic and practitioner areas of the field. It also points out their shared research interests and opportunities for future research.","container-title":"Journal of Business and Technical Communication - J BUS TECH COMMUN","DOI":"10.1177/1050651908329562","journalAbbreviation":"Journal of Business and Technical Communication - J BUS TECH COMMUN","page":"174-215","source":"ResearchGate","title":"Mapping the Research Questions in Technical Communication","volume":"23","author":[{"family":"Rude","given":"Carolyn"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2009",1,23]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Rude 2009: 176). This question is typically explored by TPC scholars in one of four areas: “disciplinarity” (research about the field of TPC,) “pedagogy” (research about teaching in TPC,) “practice” (research about the creation and management of documents,) and “social change” (research about the changes documents make in the world) (Rude 2009: 176). TPC scholars who have examined TPC and DH overlaps have focused on pedagogy 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"WdV8NDui","properties":{"unsorted":true,"formattedCitation":"(B. D. Ballentine, 2015; Litterio, 2021; B. Ballentine, 2022)","plainCitation":"(B. D. Ballentine, 2015; Litterio, 2021; B. Ballentine, 2022)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":469,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/SLKMVMSP"],"itemData":{"id":469,"type":"paper-conference","abstract":"This paper examines similarities and differences between Professional and Technical Communication and the development of the field of the Digital Humanities. The humanistic concerns of both fields offer natural alliances, as does the frequent colocation of DH and PTC faculty in departments of English. The paper examines a new syllabus for an introduction to DH graduate course offered by a PTC program as evidence of how PTC concerns are relevant to DH.","container-title":"2015 IEEE International Professional Communication Conference (IPCC)","DOI":"10.1109/IPCC.2015.7235821","event-title":"2015 IEEE International Professional Communication Conference (IPCC)","note":"ISSN: 2158-1002","page":"1-4","source":"IEEE Xplore","title":"The digital humanities and professional and technical communication: Teaching opportunities and challenges","title-short":"The digital humanities and professional and technical communication","URL":"https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7235821","author":[{"family":"Ballentine","given":"Brian D."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",9,24]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015",7]]}}},{"id":472,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/VVSHX7WJ"],"itemData":{"id":472,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"This article examines pedagogical results from an IRB-approved study that used the Omeka platform in two sections of technical writing classes. The research question explored how a digital humanities (DH) project can be an opportunity for students to learn concepts and take ownership of publicly facing content. The method used is qualitative, and findings indicated that students embraced an open-source and collaborative project. Results also demonstrated how technical and professional communication (TPC) instructors might find DH tools well suited to TPC competencies.","container-title":"Technical Communication Quarterly","DOI":"10.1080/10572252.2020.1789744","ISSN":"1057-2252","issue":"1","note":"publisher: Routledge\n_eprint: https://doi.org/10.1080/10572252.2020.1789744","page":"77-88","source":"Taylor and Francis+NEJM","title":"Digital Humanities in Professional and Technical Communication: Results of a Pedagogical Pilot Study","title-short":"Digital Humanities in Professional and Technical Communication","volume":"30","author":[{"family":"Litterio","given":"Lisa M."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2021",1,2]]}}},{"id":465,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/2NQXTNZR"],"itemData":{"id":465,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Technical communication instructors, especially those with expertise in visual rhetoric, information design, or multimedia writing are well-suited to teach an introductory Digital Humanities (DH) course. Offering a DH course provides an opportunity to reach extrafield audiences and work with students from a variety of humanities disciplines who may not have the option of taking such a course in their home department. The article advocates for a DH course that offers a methods-driven pedagogy that engages students with active learning by requiring them to research, dissect, and report on existing DH projects, as well as work with existing datasets and methods from prior student research projects or existing DH tools. The sample student project reviewed here uses the data visualization software ImagePlot, and discussion includes how the student used the tool to examine changes in brightness, hue, and color saturation, as well as calculate the total number of distinct shapes from 397 comic book covers. Ultimately, the students are tasked with developing a research question and moving to an articulated methods-driven approach for exploring the question. The student project along with the tools and sample datasets available with them are treated as a module that may be included in an introductory DH course syllabus or training session.","container-title":"Commun. Des. Q. Rev","DOI":"10.1145/3507454.3507457","issue":"1","page":"24–37","source":"ACM Digital Library","title":"Digital humanities and technical communication pedagogy: a case and a course for cross-program opportunities","title-short":"Digital humanities and technical communication pedagogy","volume":"10","author":[{"family":"Ballentine","given":"Brian"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022",8,25]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Ballentine 2015: 1-3; Litterio 2021: 77-88; B. Ballentine, 2022: 24-37). However, the other three research areas could also be used to explore DH. This presentation describes one study in which TPC “practice” research is applied to DH.
            </p>
            <p> TPC “practice” research examines the effective design of documents, and in recent decades, the term “documents” has expanded to include multimodal material, such as websites 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"8xvsnOAW","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Rude, 2009)","plainCitation":"(Rude, 2009)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":565,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/N2HBJCB7"],"itemData":{"id":565,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Agreement about research questions can strengthen disciplinary identity and give direction to a field that is still maturing. The central research question this article poses foregrounds texts, broadly defined as verbal, visual, and multimedia, and the power of texts to mediate knowledge, values, and action in a variety of contexts. Related questions concern disciplinarity, pedagogy, practice, and social change. These questions overlap and inform each other. Any single study does not necessarily fall exclusively into one area. A mapping of a field's research questions is a political act, emphasizing some questions and marginalizing or excluding others. The emphases may change over time. This mapping illustrates reasons for the tensions between the academic and practitioner areas of the field. It also points out their shared research interests and opportunities for future research.","container-title":"Journal of Business and Technical Communication - J BUS TECH COMMUN","DOI":"10.1177/1050651908329562","journalAbbreviation":"Journal of Business and Technical Communication - J BUS TECH COMMUN","page":"174-215","source":"ResearchGate","title":"Mapping the Research Questions in Technical Communication","volume":"23","author":[{"family":"Rude","given":"Carolyn"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2009",1,23]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Rude 2009: 175). Often effective document design involves using design features that are conventional to a particular genre of document, which helps the designer situate the document in relation to similar ones and streamlines people’s use of the document 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"0pXbUSbY","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Bateman, 2008)","plainCitation":"(Bateman, 2008)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1406,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/LIUP6CNM"],"itemData":{"id":1406,"type":"chapter","abstract":"In this chapter, we address in detail the joint issues of comparison and constraint. We have raised the issue of comparison at various points in the discussion so far. Whenever we analyse a multimodal document, we need to consider the sets of documents that it resembles and the sets of documents with which it stands in contrast. This kind of comparison is of much more than academic interest: in fact, it is only because of this comparison that particular interpretations can be made rather than others. The overwhelming majority of constructs that we have seen in this book are elements and configurations that have, through use, developed the potential to carry meaning in multimodal documents: this potential is only made real in the context of actual documents standing in relations of similarity and contrast with other documents.","container-title":"Multimodality and Genre: A Foundation for the Systematic Analysis of Multimodal Documents","event-place":"London","ISBN":"978-0-230-58232-3","language":"en","note":"DOI: 10.1057/9780230582323_5","page":"177-248","publisher":"Palgrave Macmillan UK","publisher-place":"London","source":"Springer Link","title":"Multimodal Documents and Genre","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1057/9780230582323_5","author":[{"family":"Bateman","given":"John A."}],"editor":[{"family":"Bateman","given":"John A."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,13]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2008"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Bateman 2008: 177-248). This study examines document design within the genre of online DH projects by reporting the usage of 59 features in the interfaces of 100 DH projects. In doing so, it supports the development of a better understanding of the genre of DH projects, which in turn can be used to enhance their design.
            </p>
            <p> Central to the study is the TPC research method of content analysis, which is defined in the field as “a research technique for making replicable and valid inferences from texts (or other meaningful matter) to the contexts of their use” 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"oUAWBF29","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Krippendorff, 2018)","plainCitation":"(Krippendorff, 2018)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1405,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/9R5JUKGP"],"itemData":{"id":1405,"type":"book","call-number":"P1 .T3","edition":"Fourth Edition","event-place":"Los Angeles","ISBN":"978-1-5063-9567-8","note":"OCLC: 1240716778","number-of-pages":"1","publisher":"SAGE","publisher-place":"Los Angeles","source":"Library Catalog (InnoPAC)","title":"Content analysis: an introduction to its methodology","title-short":"Content analysis","author":[{"family":"Krippendorff","given":"Klaus"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2018"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Krippendorff 2018: 24). For this study, I applied the four-step quantitative content analysis method developed by Ryan K. Boettger and Laura A. Palmer 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"MIRO7INH","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Boettger & Palmer, 2010)","plainCitation":"(Boettger & Palmer, 2010)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1269,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/Z8S249I9"],"itemData":{"id":1269,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Quantitative content analysis can enrich research in technical communication by identifying the frequency of thematic or rhetorical patterns and then exploring their relationship through inferential statistics. Over the last decade, the field has published few content analyses, and several of these applications have been qualitative, diluting the method's inherent rigor. This paper describes the versatility of quantitative content analysis and offers a broader application for its use in the field. This discussion frames two original case studies that illustrate the design variability that content analysis offers researchers.","container-title":"IEEE Transactions on Professional Communication","DOI":"10.1109/TPC.2010.2077450","ISSN":"1558-1500","issue":"4","note":"event-title: IEEE Transactions on Professional Communication","page":"346-357","source":"IEEE Xplore","title":"Quantitative Content Analysis: Its Use in Technical Communication","title-short":"Quantitative Content Analysis","volume":"53","author":[{"family":"Boettger","given":"Ryan K."},{"family":"Palmer","given":"Laura A."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2010",12]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Boettger / Palmer 2010: 346-357). 
            </p>
            <p>In the first step of this study, “identifying a sample,” I gathered all of the DH projects listed in the “Project Registry, A-Z” page on the 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Reviews in Digital Humanities </hi>website. This step, which was conducted in November 2024, yielded a total of 219 projects. I then assigned each project a number and used a random number generator to select 100 projects for my study sample.
            </p>
            <p>In the second step, “collecting and categorizing data,” I developed a list of features to examine in all the sample projects. First, I explored existing literature to compile a list of common web design features in similar website genres. These genres included university, museum education, art museum library, cultural heritage, and special library websites 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"DXtlI4bd","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Hite & Railsback, 2010; Huffman, 2011; Manjunatha, 2016; Pi\\uc0\\u241{}eiro-Naval et al., 2014; Saiki, 2010)","plainCitation":"(Hite & Railsback, 2010; Huffman, 2011; Manjunatha, 2016; Piñeiro-Naval et al., 2014; Saiki, 2010)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1876,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/NIN3C3YP"],"itemData":{"id":1876,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"The development of customer-centered websites is a difficult but essential component of many organizations' overall management information systems. Specifically, the study examined the content and characteristics of the web home pages and admissions-related web pages of a sample of institutions listed in the U.S. News & World Report List of Best Colleges & Universities to help web developers create customer-centric sites and to help web design educators teach students to create such sites. Overall, the content of the text and the images was user-centered. Three design principles were followed on over 90% of the websites: consistency of font styles as well as text and background colors, fast loading time, and hyperlinks placed in the two places users view first. Accessibility by the visually impaired may be difficult as numerous websites used images and bullets as hyperlinks and did not have high contrast between text and background colors.","container-title":"Journal of Computer Information Systems","DOI":"10.1080/08874417.2010.11645455","ISSN":"0887-4417","issue":"1","note":"publisher: Taylor & Francis\n_eprint: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/08874417.2010.11645455","page":"107-113","source":"Taylor and Francis+NEJM","title":"Analysis of the Content and Characteristics of University Websites with Implications for Web Designers and Educators","volume":"51","author":[{"family":"Hite","given":"Nancy Groneman"},{"family":"Railsback","given":"Barbara"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2010",9,1]]}}},{"id":1882,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/A5BQK7MD"],"itemData":{"id":1882,"type":"thesis","language":"http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/iso639-2/eng","note":"Context Object: url_ver=Z39.88-2004&ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fblacklight.rubyforge.org%3Agenerator&rft.title=A+Content+Analysis+of+Art+Museum+Library+Websites&rft.subject=Content+analysis&rft.subject=Art+libraries+and+collections&rft.subject=Museum+libraries--Administration&rft.subject=Art+libraries+and+collections--Administration&rft.date=March+6%2C+2013&rft.format=Masters+Paper&rft.language=http%3A%2F%2Fid.loc.gov%2Fvocabulary%2Fiso639-2%2Feng","publisher":"University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill","title":"A Content Analysis of Art Museum Library Websites","author":[{"family":"Huffman","given":"Suzanne M."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2011",11]]}}},{"id":1909,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/NJW6FSAR"],"itemData":{"id":1909,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"International Journal of Next Generation Library and Technologies","issue":"2","journalAbbreviation":"IJNGLT","title":"Content Analysis of Special Library Websites: An Analytical Study","URL":"https://www.researchgate.net/publication/329526974_Content_Analysis_of_Special_Library_Websites_An_Analytical_Study","volume":"2","author":[{"family":"Manjunatha","given":"K. S."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,27]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2016",5]]}}},{"id":1886,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/D49KTT4B"],"itemData":{"id":1886,"type":"paper-conference","abstract":"The following text presents a research project focusing on cultural heritage through the Internet. The main goal of this study is to identify the mechanisms used to spread the Spanish cultural heritage through municipalities' websites. It is well known that cultural heritage represents one of the tourism industry bases, which is very important to Spanish economy. However, cultural heritage is also an element that helps to shape the social identity of Spanish citizens. Thus, this research aims to carry out content analysis of 500 websites, and then make a cultural portrait of our society in the Digital Age.","collection-title":"TEEM '14","container-title":"Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Technological Ecosystems for Enhancing Multiculturality","DOI":"10.1145/2669711.2669970","event-place":"New York, NY, USA","ISBN":"978-1-4503-2896-8","page":"659–665","publisher":"Association for Computing Machinery","publisher-place":"New York, NY, USA","source":"ACM Digital Library","title":"A study of web content analysis on cultural heritage","URL":"https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/2669711.2669970","author":[{"family":"Piñeiro-Naval","given":"Valeriano"},{"family":"Nuevo","given":"Lucía Alejandra Sánchez"},{"family":"Lazcano","given":"Felipe de Jesús Marañón"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,20]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2014",10,1]]}}},{"id":1878,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/URGTQMJQ"],"itemData":{"id":1878,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"The purpose of this research was to assess the degree of viewer interaction capabilities of features found on the education portion of museum websites. A content analysis was completed where features were categorized by learning levels including: narrative (the learner is a passive recipient), interactive (the learner chooses what he/she views), communicative (the learner engages in discussion), adaptive (the learner discusses with instructor feedback), and productive (the learner expresses what was learned). From the 153 websites analysed 69 (45.1%) had narrative and 51 (33.3%) had interactivity functionality. There were 55 (35.9%) websites that had communicative, 38 (n = 24.8%) had adaptive, and 34 (22.2%) had productive features. Features found at the adaptive and productive levels tended to incorporate offline activity. The results contribute to an understanding of the adoption of technology to educate and can be used as baseline data to assess future changes in online education by museums. (Contains 5 tables and 1 figure.)","container-title":"Journal of Learning Design","ISSN":"1832-8342","issue":"1","language":"en","note":"publisher: Queensland University of Technology\nERIC Number: EJ910055","page":"52-62","source":"ERIC","title":"Interacting Online: A Content Analysis of Museum Education Websites","title-short":"Interacting Online","volume":"4","author":[{"family":"Saiki","given":"Diana"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2010"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Hite / Railsback 2010: 109-111; Huffman 2011: 24-35; Manjunatha 2016: 3-7; Piñeiro-Naval et al. 2014: 659–665; Saiki 2010: 55-61). I developed a list of design features using emergent coding, a method in TPC content analysis in which noteworthy features “emerge” through observation 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"X6nhFtRs","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Thayer et al., 2007)","plainCitation":"(Thayer et al., 2007)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1272,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/524QX4JG"],"itemData":{"id":1272,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Content analysis is a powerful empirical method for analyzing text, a method that technical communicators can use on the job and in their research. Content analysis can expose hidden connections among concepts, reveal relationships among ideas that initially seem unconnected, and inform the decision-making processes associated with many technical communication practices. In this article, we explain the basics of content analysis methodology and dispel common misconceptions, report on a content analysis case study, reveal the most important objectives associated with conducting high quality content analyses, and summarize the implications of content analysis as a tool for technical communicators and researchers.","container-title":"Journal of Technical Writing and Communication","DOI":"10.2190/TW.37.3.c","ISSN":"0047-2816","issue":"3","language":"en","note":"publisher: SAGE Publications Inc","page":"267-279","source":"SAGE Journals","title":"Content Analysis as a Best Practice in Technical Communication Research","volume":"37","author":[{"family":"Thayer","given":"Alexander"},{"family":"Evans","given":"Mary"},{"family":"McBride","given":"Alicia"},{"family":"Queen","given":"Matt"},{"family":"Spyridakis","given":"Jan"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2007",7,1]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Thayer et al. 2007: 268). For my emergent coding, I randomly selected 10 DH projects from the 119 projects that were not included in the study sample, and I closely examined each of them. Finally, I selected 10 accessibility-specific features using emergent coding in combination with the Level A criteria in the Website Accessibility Content Guidelines 2.2 (WACG 2.2) 
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"h1OEeWNw","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Campbell et al., 2023)","plainCitation":"(Campbell et al., 2023)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1911,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/14771475/items/329BFS27"],"itemData":{"id":1911,"type":"document","title":"Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.2","URL":"https://www.w3.org/TR/2023/REC-WCAG22-20231005/","editor":[{"family":"Campbell","given":"Alastair"},{"family":"Adams","given":"Chuck"},{"family":"Bradley Montgomery","given":"Rachael"},{"family":"Cooper","given":"Michael"},{"family":"Kirkpatrick","given":"Andrew"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",11,27]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023",10,5]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Campbell et al. 2023). Altogether, I compiled a list of 59 total features to examine in my sample of 100 DH projects.
            </p>
            <p>In the third step, “developing a coding scheme and training raters,” I defined the 59 features and used the definitions to identify their presence in the sample projects, several of which were no longer online.</p>
            <p>Finally, in step four, “analyzing the data,” I used descriptive statistics to determine how common the features were among the DH projects that currently have websites (
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 92.)
            </p>
            <p>My results demonstrate commonalities as well as differences among the websites. About half of the homepages contain a guide for using the website (50%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 46) or access to a database or digital collection (51%, 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">n </hi>= 47.) Many—but not all—of the sites have a main menu (77%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 71) or a footer (67%, 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">n </hi>= 62) and most sites adjust to different screen sizes (90%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 83.) In terms of site identity, some projects have their own logo (49%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 45) explain how to cite themselves (36%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 33) and use first-person language (52%, 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">n </hi>= 48.) Most of the project sites contain photographs (80%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 74,) but virtual tours (7%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 6) and digital 3D models (3%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 3) are less common. Regarding accessibility of the projects’ homepages, most are coded such that the language can be changed (77%, 
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 71) and the page can be navigated using a keyboard (79%, 
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">n </hi>= 73,) but only 26% (
                <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 24) of the projects have suitable alternative text. I will present these statistics and my other findings alongside data regarding the DH projects’ home institutions and countries.
            </p>
            <p> This TPC content analysis is a starting point for identifying genre conventions among DH projects. Scholars can refer to these conventions as they design and refine their DH projects, particularly as they tackle challenges related to sustainability and accessibility. Future research may examine the impact of certain design features in terms of usability and ecological impact. By undertaking a content analysis of DH projects, this presentation demonstrates one application of TPC methods to DH research. It also argues that TPC research can and should be applied to DH because that would broaden the research questions and answers available to scholars in both fields.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Ballentine, Brian D.</hi> (2015): “The digital humanities and professional and technical communication: Teaching opportunities and challenges“, in: IEEE: 
                        <hi rend="italic">2015 IEEE International Professional Communication Conference (IPCC)</hi>, Limerick, Ireland, July 2015: 1–4. DOI: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/IPCC.2015.7235821">https://doi.org/10.1109/IPCC.2015.7235821</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Ballentine, Brian</hi> (2022): "Digital humanities and technical communication pedagogy: A case and a course for cross-program opportunities“, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Communication Design Quarterly Review</hi> 10, 1: 24–37.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Bateman, John A</hi> (2008): "Multimodal Documents and Genre“, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Multimodality and Genre: A Foundation for the Systematic Analysis of Multimodal Documents.</hi> London: Palgrave Macmillan UK 177–248.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Boettger, Ryan K. / Palmer, Laura A.</hi> (2010): "Quantitative Content Analysis: Its Use in Technical Communication“, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">IEEE Transactions on Professional Communication</hi> 53, 4: 346–357. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Baayen, Harald / Halteren, Hans van / Tweedie, Fiona 
                            <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">(1996): “Outside the cave of shadows: using syntactic annotation to enhance authorship attribution”, in: </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                            <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 11, 3: 121–132.</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Campbell, Alastair et al.</hi> (2023): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.2</hi>. &lt;
                        <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2023/REC-WCAG22-20231005/">https://www.w3.org/TR/2023/REC-WCAG22-20231005/</ref>&gt; 
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">[30.04.2025]</hi>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Hite, Nancy Groneman / Railsback, Barbara</hi> (2010): "Analysis of the Content and Characteristics of University Websites with Implications for Web Designers and Educators“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Computer Information Systems</hi> 51, 1: 107–113. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Huffman, Suzanne M.</hi> (2011): 
                        <hi rend="italic">A Content Analysis of Art Museum Library Websites</hi>. Masters Paper, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Krippendorff, Klaus</hi> (2018): "Conceptual Foundation“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Content Analysis: An Introduction to Ist Methodology</hi>, Fourth Edition. Thousand Oaks, California: SAGE 24-50.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Litterio, Lisa M.</hi> (2021): “Digital Humanities in Professional and Technical Communication: Results of a Pedagogical Pilot Study“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Technical Communication Quarterly</hi> 30, 1: 77–88.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Manjunatha, K S</hi> (2016): „Content Analysis of Special Library Websites: An Analytical Study“ in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Next Generation Library and Technologies</hi> 2, 2: 1-9.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Piñeiro-Naval, Valeriano et al.</hi> (2014): "A study of web content analysis on cultural heritage“, in: TEEM '14: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Technological Ecosystems for Enhancing Multiculturality</hi>, Salamanca, Spain, October 2014: 659–665. DOI: 
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2669711.2669970">https://doi.org/10.1145/2669711.2669970</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Rude, Carolyn D.</hi> (2009): “Mapping the Research Questions in Technical Communication“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Business and Technical Communication</hi> 23, 2: 174–215. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl rend="Bibliography">
                        <hi rend="bold">Saiki, Diana</hi> (2010): "Interacting Online: A Content Analysis of Museum Education Websites“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Learning Design</hi> 4, 1: 52–62.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Thayer, Alexander et al.</hi> (2007): "Content Analysis as a Best Practice in Technical Communication Research“, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Technical Writing and Communication</hi> 37, 3: 267–279.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
