<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BROADWELL_Peter_The_Director_s_Signature__Stylometry_of_Thea">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Director’s Signature: Stylometry of Theater Choreography via Pose and Action Estimation</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Broadwell</surname>
                        <forename>Peter</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>broadwell@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Rau</surname>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>mjrau@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Wiles</surname>
                        <forename>Simon</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>simon.wiles@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Abraham</surname>
                        <forename>Vijoy</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Stanford University, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>vijoy@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-14T20:27:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>pose estimation</term>
                    <term>action recognition</term>
                    <term>directing</term>
                    <term>stylometry</term>
                    <term>cinemetrics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>attribution studies and stylometric analysis</term>
                    <term>cultural analytics</term>
                    <term>spatial &amp; spatio-temporal analysis</term>
                    <term>modeling and visualization</term>
                    <term>Film and cinema arts studies</term>
                    <term>Media studies</term>
                    <term>Performance Studies: Dance</term>
                    <term>Theatre</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                    <term>Match where technical expertise is helpful.</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The concept of a director’s “signature” or unique style is central to 
                    <hi rend="italic">auteur theory</hi>, which posits that a director’s personal vision and stylistic choices imprint a distinct identity on their work, making their contribution recognizable regardless of collaborative efforts. The notion is most commonly applied to film studies, but theater studies often holds up directors with distinct visual styles (Robert Wilson, Ivo van Hove, Romeo Castellucci) as examples of “auteurs.” Unlike film, where a director has many more options in terms of camera placement, lighting, design, editing, and post-production effects, the live performance director has more limited tools and less control over the work as a whole. The main tool for a theater director is choreography of the actors’ bodies and their positioning in space, a distinct phenomenon that theater scholars acknowledge yet rarely analyze. And compared to literary stylometrics, where each word and letter is generally attributable to the intentions of the author, a theater performance comprises many different mediating factors (the script, the stage design, the actors’ bodies). A combined distant and narrow viewing of poses applied across multiple productions therefore is more likely to determine a director’s consistent choreographic patterns, rather than only considering a single performance.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Related Work</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Advances in deep-learning technologies for moving images have benefitted computational theater studies (Bardiot 2021, Escobar Varela 2021) by greatly expanding the data that can be extracted from conventional video recordings, augmenting the traditional “cinemetrics” of shot durations and pixel colors by looking deeper into the frame to identify faces, objects, poses and three-dimensional spatial relations (Chávez Heras 2023). Applying such tools across many recordings of staged performances further enables new “distant viewing” analyses (Arnold / Tilton 2019), including efforts to quantify and compare stage directors’ “signature” choreographic styles. The body of scholarship on literary stylometry offers promising questions and methods, although our current effort ventures into non-linguistic realms rarely visited even in previous “beyond authorship” studies of theatrical style that focused primarily on the written word (Craig / Greatley-Hirsch 2017). Our work owes much to efforts to categorize deployments of human poses in visual art history (Kutrzyński / Król 2024), although considering theatrical performances greatly increases the degree of spatio-temporal complexity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Corpus and Data Preprocessing</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We assembled a corpus of 30 full-length theatrical performance recordings, evenly divided among three contemporary “auteur” directors: Bill T. Jones, Romeo Castellucci, and Krzysztof Warlikowski (Appendix 1). We applied an advanced transformer-based pose estimation and tracking tool (Rajasegaran et al. 2022) to each recording, generating both 2D and estimated 3D pose coordinates of figures tracked across consecutive frames. We reduced each estimated pose to the 13-keypoint COCO standard (head, shoulders, hips, arms, legs) for compatibility with downstream tools and also divided each pose track into “movelets” of 1/6 of a second for motion quantification. We further applied an action recognition model that assigns a 60-element Atomic Visual Actions (AVA) embedding vector to each individual pose (Rajasegaran et al. 2023), and also generated a 16-element probabilistic view-invariant “POEM” embedding for each pose (Sun et al. 2020).</p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The data described above were loaded into an instance of the MIME (Machine Intelligence for Motion Exegesis) framework (
                    <ref target="http://github.com/sul-cidr/mime">github.com/sul-cidr/mime</ref>), which provides a web-based video pose timeline exploration interface and is built upon a Postgres database using the pgvector extension to enable fast similarity searching of pose and action vectors and coordinates (Figure 1).
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="15.134166666666667cm" height="9.278055555555556cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Figure 1.</hi> The MIME interface’s timeline view, displaying pose and motion data for a full performance, with details and inferred 3D body armatures for a selected frame.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We queried the MIME instance’s API to derive a set of pose, action, motion and distance statistics for each performance. Averages (mean and median) and standard deviation of each distribution were calculated per populated frame for the elements of the following:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>POEM pose embedding values</item>
                    <item>AVA action recognition embedding values</item>
                    <item>3D “global orientation” representations of each pose (13 x 3 coordinates in meters)</item>
                    <item>3D distances between pose centroids (meters)</item>
                    <item>In-place keypoint movement of each tracked pose movelet (meters/second)</item>
                    <item>“Sidereal” motion (relative to the background) of each tracked pose movelet (meters/second)</item>
                </list>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Examining multiple performances per director helps to attenuate the influence of “noise” data from non choreography-related shots of musicians, audience members and post-performance curtain calls (for example), as well as the vision model’s struggles with certain camera effects and lighting conditions, and perhaps most significantly, choices of shot angles and framing made by the video directors, who are usually not the same person as the stage director.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Analytical Methods</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We framed our primary stylometric inquiry as a performance-to-director classification problem: from the derived pose, action, motion and distance data above, which elements are most effective at predicting the correct stage director for a given performance? We began with “leave one out” (LOO) tests in which we assembled the average pose distance and motion features into a vector for each performance, repeated the process for the 3D “global orientation” pose keypoint coordinates, view-invariant POEM pose vectors and action recognition vectors, and compared these to aggregate vectors that averaged values from all of a director’s works except the held-out performance. Simple cosine similarity-based matching of directors to held-out works gave way to machine-learning classification algorithms (a “random forest” combined decision-tree estimator was slightly more accurate than others), which facilitated tests to estimate the relative contribution (“importance”) of each element of the feature vectors to successful predictions. Tests were repeated with multiple random seeds and eventually via 10-fold cross-validation to avoid inadvertently cherry-picking results.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">Motion &amp; distance</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">Pose embeddings</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">3D global pose keypoints</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">Action embeddings</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">LOO cosine similarity</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">63.33% (19/30)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">80% (24/30)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">73.33% (22/30)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">80% (24/30)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">LOO random forest</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">61% (183/300)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">89% (267/300)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">66% (198/300)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">80.67% (242/300)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="bold">10-fold random forest</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">58.7%
                            <lb/>stdev: 35%
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">68%
                            <lb/>stdev: 35.3%
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">68.80%
                            <lb/>stdev: 32.3%
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">71.60%
                            <lb/>stdev: 32.1%
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Table 1.</hi> Accuracies of performance-to-director classifiers by method (rows) and input features (columns). 33% accuracy is expected by chance. Input features are based on mean values of component elements across performances (median values resulted in slightly lower accuracies).
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="6.773333333333333cm" height="6.138333333333334cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="6.773333333333333cm" height="6.138333333333334cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Figure 2.</hi> Confusion matrices of directorial classifications of 30 performances using a “leave one out” train/test split across 10 runs with different random seeds.
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1004" width="6.773333333333333cm" height="5.044722222222222cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                    <graphic n="1005" width="6.773333333333333cm" height="5.044722222222222cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Figure 3.</hi> Feature importances from “random forest” classifiers based on motion and distance (left) and pose embeddings (right).
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Results</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">As Table 1 and Figure 2 (left) indicate, distance and motion statistics aggregated across each performance helped to discern stagings by Bill T. Jones from the others, but the confusion between Castellucci and Warlikowski suggests this may be seizing upon the differences in 
                    <hi rend="italic">genre</hi> between their oeuvres, rather than specific directorial styles: the performances in our corpus directed by Jones are dance works, while the others’ tend to be from more static genres, particularly opera. Yet comparing average pose embeddings was largely successful at differentiating between all three directors (see Figure 2, right). Average action embeddings performed similarly (Table 1). This may be due to the tendency of embedding spaces to accentuate semantic differences that are “baked in” during pre-training – which also suggests why comparing the raw global 3D pose data was not as successful, as it does not incorporate such learned biases. The drop-off in accuracy of the embedding-based classifiers during 10-fold cross-validation does however imply that they struggle when the training set is reduced.
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1006" width="8.643055555555556cm" height="8.537222222222223cm" url="/tmp/tmp9hog0aw4/Pictures/ea782cb3885a8b8909b4985579dbbcec.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Figure 4.</hi> UMAP projection of the POEM embeddings of a 1% sample of poses in the corpus, color-coded by director, showing the locations of the average embedding for each director and sample poses with high similarity to these embeddings.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The superior performance overall of the embedding-based approaches, however, has the drawback that it is more difficult to translate their computational discernment into actual insights regarding the directors’ favored poses and action patterns. It is not generally possible to convert an averaged POEM embedding to a single pose, nor is it straightforward to determine precisely what the importance of “feature 1” (Figure 3, right) means for actual poses. Likewise, the AVA action embeddings only map to fairly vague descriptions such as “51%: stand, 38%: watch a person, 33%: carry an object.” Yet thanks to the massive vector database available via the MIME platform, it is at least possible to explore poses from the full data set whose embeddings are most similar to a director’s averages. Figure 4 suggests this can reveal useful insights, such as the overall greater similarity between Castellucci’s and Warlikowski’s pose repertoires relative to Jones’s, and the tendencies of Jones to employ dramatically contorted poses, Castellucci to favor hunched-over standing postures, and Warlikowski to deploy figures in an active sitting position.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">This work demonstrates technologies and methods for addressing the question of directorial style in theater via distant and close viewing of pose choreography. Future iterations will introduce a more diverse set of performances and directors and investigate whether action embeddings can help to untangle the computational challenges inherent to quantification of gesture. Other enhancements will better control for genre and content by comparing different directors’ stagings of the same work, and consider scene-level subdivisions of the source performances.</p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <hi rend="bold">Table 2.</hi> Details of the 30 full-length performance recordings analyzed.
                </p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Title</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Director</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Duration</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Poses</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Tracks</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Shots</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">A Letter to My Nephew</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:09:02</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">308088</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">698</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">182</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Analogy/Dora: Tramontane</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:17:12</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">411046</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2136</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1794</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">A Quarrelling Pair</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:17:50</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">267257</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">759</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">729</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">D-Man in the Waters</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">0:35:10</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">141191</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">855</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">110</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Fondly Do We Hope... Fervently Do We Pray</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:23:55</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">435160</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1001</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">846</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Holzer Duet... Truisms</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">0:17:45</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">43206</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">88</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Play and Play</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:12:50</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">462918</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2359</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">230</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Secret Pastures</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:33:54</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">419080</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1470</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Story/Time: The Life of an Idea</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:13:35</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">402026</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1470</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">869</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">We Shall Not Be Moved</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bill T. Jones</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:57:30</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">633482</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3244</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4111</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Das Floß der Medusa (Henze)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:21:35</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">114133</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">724</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">549</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Democracy in America</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:43:05</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">219148</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">524</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">46</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Don Giovanni (Mozart)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3:30:01</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">897915</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">5155</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1009</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Go Down, Moses</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:02:40</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">122960</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">289</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">78</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Inferno</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:36:16</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">345711</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2837</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">799</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Parsifal (Wagner)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3:58:29</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">780960</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3551</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">847</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Purgatorio</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:13:48</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">93387</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">399</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">392</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Requiem (Mozart)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:38:57</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">507498</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2874</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">365</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Resurrección (Gustav Mahler)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:40:15</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">295840</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2212</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">610</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">The Magic Flute (Mozart)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Castellucci</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2:43:15</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">763697</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4385</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">863</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bluebeard's Castle (Bartók) / La voix humaine (Poulenc)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2:02:19</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">278984</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1389</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">736</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Die Gezeichneten (Schreker)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3:48:41</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">954114</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">5454</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1345</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Elektra (Strauss)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2:06:25</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">324719</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1220</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">532</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Iphigénie en Tauride (Gluck)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2:11:26</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">510703</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2648</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">822</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lady Macbeth of Mtsensk (Shostakovich), 1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:47:13</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">412434</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3402</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">774</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lady Macbeth of Mtsensk (Shostakovich), 2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:17:36</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">446255</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3619</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">526</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Médée (Cherubini)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2:24:41</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">653184</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4443</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1029</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Les Contes d'Hoffmann (Offenbach)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3:08:39</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">930245</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">6181</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1432</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">The French</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3:45:47</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">906390</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3410</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">982</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Wozzeck (Berg)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Warlikowski</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1:45:20</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">352588</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2766</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">887</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Arnold, Taylor / Tilton, Lauren.</hi> (2019): “Distant Viewing: Analyzing Large Visual Corpora”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 34, Supplement_1: i3–16. DOI: 10.1093/llc/fqz013.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Bardiot, Clarisse.</hi> (2021): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Performing Arts and Digital Humanities: From Traces to Data</hi>. Hoboken, NJ: ISTE Ltd / John Wiley and Sons, Inc.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Chávez Heras, Daniel.</hi> (2024): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Cinema and Machine Vision: Artificial Intelligence, Aesthetics and Spectatorship</hi>. Edinburgh University Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Craig, Hugh / Greatley-Hirsch, Brett.</hi> (2017): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Style, Computers, and Early Modern Drama: Beyond Authorship.</hi> Cambridge University Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Escobar Varela, Miguel.</hi> (2021): 
                        <hi rend="italic">Theater as Data: Computational Journeys into Theater Research</hi>. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Kutrzyński, Marcin / Król, Dariusz.</hi> (2024): “Deep Learning-Based Human Pose Estimation towards Artworks Classification”, in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Information and Telecommunication</hi> 8, 4: 470–489. DOI: 10.1080/24751839.2024.2331866.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Rajasegaran, Jathushan / Pavlakos, Georgios / Kanazawa, Angjoo / Malik, Jitendra.</hi> (2022): “Tracking People by Predicting 3D Appearance, Location &amp; Pose”, in 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</hi>, New Orleans, LA, USA, June 21–24, 2022: 2730–2739. DOI: 10.1109/CVPR52688.2022.00276.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Rajasegaran, Jathushan / Pavlakos, Georgios / Kanazawa, Angjoo / Feichtenhofer, Christoph / Malik, Jitendra.</hi> (2023): “On the Benefits of 3D Pose and Tracking for Human Action Recognition,” in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</hi>, Vancouver, Canada, June 18–22, 2023: 640–649. DOI: 10.1109/CVPR52729.2023.00069.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold">Sun, Jennifer J / Zhao, Jiaping / Chen, Liang-Chieh / Schroff, Florian / Adam, Hartwig / Liu, Ting.</hi> (2020): “View-Invariant Probabilistic Embedding for Human Pose,” in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Computer Vision – ECCV 2020: 16th European Conference</hi>, Glasgow, UK, August 23–28, 2020: 53–70. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-030-58558-7_4.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
