<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="VAN_HYNING_Victoria_Key_findings_from__Crowdsourced_Data__Ac">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Key findings from “Crowdsourced Data: Accuracy, Accessibility, and Authority (CDAAA)”</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Van Hyning</surname>
                        <forename>Victoria</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Maryland, College of Information, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>vvh@umd.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Jones</surname>
                        <forename>Mace</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Maryland, College of Information, United States of America</affiliation>
                    <email>majones@umd.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-04-29T19:27:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Long Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>crowdsourcing</term>
                    <term>accessibility</term>
                    <term>blind</term>
                    <term>low vision</term>
                    <term>cultural heritage</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>crowdsourcing</term>
                    <term>digital access</term>
                    <term>privacy</term>
                    <term>and ethics analysis</term>
                    <term>Design studies</term>
                    <term>Disability and differently-abled studies</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference online</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">In a systematic literature review on the topic of accessibility of DH projects and digital cultural heritage for people with disabilities, in the period 2018 to 2022, Pirrone et al (2023) found too few sources to answer their initial question “RQ1: How Digital Humanities are supporting people with impairment in cultural enjoyment?”. The dearth of scholarship on the topic of accessibility and DH caused them to change their question to be future-oriented and speculative: “RQ2: How Digital Humanities </hi>
                    <hi rend="italic normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">might</hi>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> improve the quality of the cultural experience for people with disabilities?” (Pirrone et al, 2023, Table 1, emphasis added). The paucity of sources is particularly notable given that their study considered all forms of disability. Given these findings, the DH25 conference theme is timely. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">The research questions and findings from “Crowdsourced Data: Accuracy, Accessibility, and Authority (CDAAA),” a 3-year</hi>
                    <ref target="https://www.imls.gov/grants/awarded/re-252344-ols-22">
                        <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">Institute of Museum and Library Services</hi>
                    </ref>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (IMLS, USA) grant project offers new insights into questions of accessibility of the cultural heritage record. CDAAA aimed to identify any barriers that Library, Archive, and Museum (LAM) professionals and academics face in making crowdsourced transcriptions accessible to blind and low vision (BLV) people who use assistive technology to access digital text; as well as solutions to these issues. Between 2022 and 2025, the CDAAA team, led by Victoria Van Hyning, set out to understand whether the crowdsourced transcription projects deployed by LAM organizations have worked as many creators of such projects believed they would. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Our research questions are: </hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:11pt">RQ1 (Authority):</hi>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Are LAMs able to integrate crowdsourced transcriptions into their CMSs (the authoritative record)? If yes, how? If not, what technical barriers do they face? </hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:11pt">RQ2 (Accuracy and Authority):</hi>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> What are LAM practitioners’ attitudes towards crowdsourced transcription data quality? Do these attitudes impact whether or not crowdsourced data are incorporated into CMSs? How do LAM practitioners assess the quality of crowdsourced data? </hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:11pt">RQ3 (Accessibility):</hi>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> When transcription data is successfully integrated with CMSs, is it accessible to print-disabled people? What are print-disabled users’ experiences of searching for and reading transcription data? </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">To answer these questions, we worked with two key constituencies: project owners and users of the resulting data: </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">12 US-based Partners, including representatives from private, public, university, and federal LAM institutions, and one community-led group, who use platforms like Zooniverse.org, FromThePage, and/or bespoke software to run transcription projects. We selected LAM Partners who also have responsibility for managing the resulting crowdsourced transcriptions and any other data, i.e. tags or index terms.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">11 blind and 1 low vision users with diverse academic backgrounds and training.  </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Methods</head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">We used a mixed-methods approach, including a recruitment survey, semi-structured interviews, and technical demonstration interviews with LAM partners; and accessibility focused user-testing sessions with BLV participants. LAM Partners were recruited through a survey sent to multiple mailing lists, posted on LinkedIn, and shared by members of the Advisory Board. LAM Partner interviews were conducted between 2023-06-28 and 2024-04-15, and resulted in 21 recordings, including a pilot interview. The 3 LAM Partners who had not yet integrated transcription data into a LAM system or data repository did not participate in a technical demonstration.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">User testers were recruited through a blind academics listserv managed by the National Federation of the Blind in Baltimore, USA. The NFB vetted our research proposal before sharing the recruitment email. We recruited an exceptionally international, multilingual, and diverse user tester pool of 12 people. Each participant tested 3 LAM Partner systems in a roughly 120-minute-long session. 10 BLV participants tested an additional accessible semantic HTML rendering of a transcription of a page from the diary of Ada Blackjack held at Dartmouth College Libraries, which we presented at DH24 (Van Hyning et al, 2024). </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">All recordings were transcribed through Otter.ai and then manually checked by members of the CDAAA team and sent to participants who had the opportunity to amend and redact the transcript. An initial codebook for the accessibility testing was created by PI Van Hyning, Research Scientist J. Bern Jordan (Y2 of the grant only), and Graduate Assistant Mace Jones in summer 2024. We met together and read through transcripts to develop codes through discussion and consensus. The codes include in vivo, deductive and inductive types. Jones and Van Hyning separately began coding the LAM Partner transcripts in spring 2025 using Evaluative and Magnitude coding approaches (Sadaña, 2021).  </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Interviews, Demos, and Accessibility testing protocols all included Likert scale questions that enable us to compare findings across LAM Partner organizations and systems. For example, we asked each BLV tester to perform tasks on three LAM systems and rate their experience on a five-point scale in response to </hi>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:12pt">statements such as “This discovery system website is easy to use” (strongly agree, somewhat agree, neither agree nor disagree, somewhat disagree, strongly disagree). We tested the following tasks for usability and accessibility: </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Locate the website of the relevant LAM Partner</head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">Search the website, content management system, data repository, etc for transcriptions of any kind.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">Search the relevant system for a specific quotation created through the LAM Partner’s transcription project and known to be housed in the platform. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">These five-point scale questions are based on the System Usability Score (SUS) questionnaire that aims to make comparison between systems possible. Users were assigned LAM systems to test by a randomized approach. Each system was tested by 4 users. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>LAM Partner Findings (RQ1 and RQ2)  </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Through Interviews and Demos, we identified that LAM Partners experience common challenges with crowdsourced data integration, including infrequent and complex manual ingest processes, however, more LAMs were able to upload content more successfully than we had anticipated (N=10/12). LAM practitioners approach data ingestion in different ways, i.e. placing transcriptions in notes or description fields, publishing a separate .txt or .pdf file attached to the object record, or as datasets in a separate repository like Dataverse. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">We asked each LAM Partner participant questions about their data quality assessments and processes (if any) of vetting transcriptions. We found that 10 LAM Partners rate volunteer transcriptions as high enough quality to ingest (Table 1). Many performed some text editing and post-processing before ingest. </hi>
                </head>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Magnitude Codes</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A5</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A6</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A7</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A8</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A9</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A10</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A11</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">LAM A12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Positive</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X (wiki)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Leans positive</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X (FTP)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Neutral</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X (Zoo)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Leans negative</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">Negative</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default">X (Zoo)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Table 1: Sentiment of LAM Practitioners About Their Data Quality</head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">LAM Partners tended to take a positive view of crowdsourced transcription quality. Some made no changes to transcriptions before ingesting them to their CMSs, while others vetted every line. The negative results require a little unpacking. LAM Partner A4’s “leans negative” assessment stems from the fact that they use crowdsourcing for pedagogical purposes, and the data that results is published in Dataverse in order to provide credit and acknowledgement to students taking part in paleography institutes, rather than for the primary purpose of creating searchable and accessible transcription content. 2 LAM Partners collected crowdsourcing data that are too low quality or difficult to use and had not ingested it at the time of the interview. LAM Partner 12 had originally used the codebase Scribe, developed by Zooniverse and the New York Public Library, and finding the data quality too low, moved the content to the Zooniverse Project Builder for retranscription. LAM Partner 9 had a good experience with Wikisource, but greater challenges with the Zooniverse Project Builder. We did not find a correlation between time spent vetting transcriptions and assessments of data quality.</hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Accessibility User Tester Findings (RQ3)  </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">While the data management practices of our LAM Partners often meet FAIR and CARE principles of data sharing that may work well for sighted users, that not all data sharing methods are equal in terms of accessibility for BLV users. Depositing batches of transcriptions in repositories such as Dataverse and Zenodo–commonly used data repositories for many DH and LAM practitioners–are notably tricky, as they do not facilitate full text search, which is a significant limitation for many users, but particularly for BLV users. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">As stated above, all BLV participants undertook the same series of tasks for each CMS or database. Though many located the Partner websites and often found transcriptions using a search string and iterative approaches to their search, it is notable that our participants struggled as much as they did. Many pointed out that a first encounter with a website usually requires what we call “bushwacking” and navigating through heterogeneous site architecture. Many of our participants were highly adept at this, but said that under normal circumstances they tend to abandon poorly architected websites in favaor of those that are more intuitive or better structured. It is notable that all of our participants had earned or were working towards advanced degrees and regularly conduct sophisticated online and LAM-based searches for their studies or work. The sheer variety of search architectures, website layouts, and methods for publishing crowdsourced transcription data pose challenges for BLV users, which aligns with prior findings about BLV users’ search experiences in other kinds of library CMSs and websites (Xie et al, 2018 and 2021). Here is an example of findings for just one LAM Partner’s bespoke CMS:</hi>
                </head>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(D9D9D9)">
                            <p rend="paragraph" style="text-align: center;">ACC Tester ID</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(D9D9D9)">
                            <p rend="paragraph" style="text-align: center;">Blind or low vision</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">
                            <p rend="paragraph" style="text-align: center;">
                                <hi rend="normaltextrun">
                                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Navigate to </hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">the </hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">L</hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">AM Partner</hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> website</hi>
                                </hi>
                            </p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">Search for digitized materials w/ transcriptions</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">
                            <p rend="paragraph" style="text-align: center;">Phrase search</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">Rate statement: ‘This discovery system website is easy to use’</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">Rate statement: ‘This website meets my needs as a user.’</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph background-color(DDDDDD)">
                            <p rend="paragraph" style="text-align: center;">LAM CMS test position</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">ACC-4</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">B</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Complete Success</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Strongly Disagree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Strongly Disagree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">2</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">ACC-6</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">B</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Complete Success</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Neither Agree nor Disagree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Agree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">1</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">ACC-8</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">B</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Complete Success</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Agree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Agree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">3</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">ACC-11</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">B</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Complete Success</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Failure</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Success w/ major issues</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Agree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">Agree</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" rend="paragraph">
                            <hi rend="normaltextrun">1</hi>
                            <hi rend="eop"> </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p style="text-align: center;">
                    <hi rend="bold">Table 2: Findings for LAM Partner A4, an R1 University Library in the USA.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:11pt">CDAAA has many lessons for the DH and LAM community as we consider how to ensure the accessibility of our collections, scholarly editions, and other web-based content. Typically, when DH and cultural heritage practitioners say that something is accessible, we mean that it is digital and online, rather than truly accessible to people with disabilities. Our findings are especially timely, given swift-approaching changes to legislation in the USA, in the form of ‘35.200 Requirements for web and mobile accessibility’, an update to the Americans with Disabilities Act Title II regulations, subpart-H. Effective 24 June, 2024 the Department of Justice in the USA enacted this new rule to provide “technical standards for web content and mobile app accessibility to give public entities greater clarity in exactly how to meet their ADA obligations and to help ensure equal access to government services for individuals with disabilities,” which explicitly cites the WCAG 2.1 AA as the expected standard. All Title II organizations, including state and university libraries and archives, local governments, etc. must comply with these regulatory standards by 24 April of 2026 or 2027, depending on the size of the jurisdiction they serve. Similar legislation exists in Europe (European Accessibility Act, which came into force in June 2025), and the UK (Public Sector Bodies (Websites and Mobile Applications) (No. 2) Accessibility Regulations 2018). We believe new and existing laws and statutes will impact DH and LAM work for the better and move us towards addressing many of the thematic concerns of the DH25 conference, and many of the deepest ethical concerns at the heart of our work. </hi>
                </head>
            </div>
            <div/>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Pirrone, Maria / Centorrino, Marco /Galletta, Antonino / Sicari, Christian / Villari, Massimo </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(2023)</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Digital Humanities and Disability: A Systematic Literature Review of Cultural Accessibility for People with Disability”, in: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt"> 38, 1: 313-329. (April 3, 2023): DOI: https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqac045.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Saldaña, Johnny</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. (2021): </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">The coding manual for qualitative researchers</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (4th ed.). SAGE.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Van Hyning, Victoria / Jordan, J. Bern / Jones, Mace</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(2024): “Responsible Transcription and Text Markup Practices to Enhance Accessibility for People Who Use Screen Readers: An Ada Blackjack Case Study”, in:</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">DH2024 Book of Abstracts</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">. DH2024. Arlington, VA: Zenodo. DOI: &lt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761079&gt;.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Xie, Iris / Babu, Rakesh / Lee, Tae Hee / Castillo, Melissa Davey / You, Sukjin / Hanlon, Ann M </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(2020): “Enhancing Usability of Digital Libraries: Designing Help Features to Support Blind and Visually Impaired Users”, in:</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Information Processing &amp; Management</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">,</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">57, 3: 102–110. DOI: 10.1016/j.ipm.2019.102110.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Xie, Iris / Babu, Rakesh / Castillo, Melissa Davey / Han, Hyejung</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(2018). “Identification of Factors Associated with Blind Users’ Help</hi>
                        <hi style="font-family:Cambria Math;font-size:10pt">‐</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">seeking Situations in Interacting with Digital Libraries”, in:</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">,</hi>
                        <hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">69, 4: 514–527. DOI:10.1002/asi.23982.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
