<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="VEGA_S_NCHEZ_Rodrigo_Progress_of_The_New_Spain_Fleets_Projec">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Progress of The New Spain Fleets Project: accurate Handwritten Text Recognition models for 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century Spanish calligraphies.</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Vega-Sánchez</surname>
                        <forename>Rodrigo</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Lancaster University, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>r.vega-sanchez@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Brito-Ramos</surname>
                        <forename>Edna</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia, México</affiliation>
                    <email>edna_brito_ramos@hotmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Cruz-Ríos</surname>
                        <forename>Francisco</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Independent researcher</affiliation>
                    <email>hfranciscoczr@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Montiel-Alejos</surname>
                        <forename>Fryda</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Archivo General de la Nación, México</affiliation>
                    <email>frydama@hotmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>González-Aceves</surname>
                        <forename>Andrea</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia, México</affiliation>
                    <email>oknakkiin@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Hernández-Ronquillo</surname>
                        <forename>Abril</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia, México</affiliation>
                    <email>oronquix.gold@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Díaz-Vázquez</surname>
                        <forename>Martín</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia, México</affiliation>
                    <email>martin.noches@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Valadez-Vázquez</surname>
                        <forename>Ricardo</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</affiliation>
                    <email>ricardovaladezvazquez@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Camacho-Gamez</surname>
                        <forename>Lidia</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidad de Guadalajara, México</affiliation>
                    <email>y.wlre.7@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Candela</surname>
                        <forename>Guillaume</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>University of Leeds, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>guillaume.candela.gc@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Favila-Vázquez</surname>
                        <forename>Mariana</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Centro de Investigaciones y Estudios Superiores en Antropología Social, México</affiliation>
                    <email>mariana.favila@ciesas.edu.mx</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Trejo-Rivera</surname>
                        <forename>Flor</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Subdirección de Arqueología Subacuática-INAH, México</affiliation>
                    <email>clonopio@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Sánchez-Díaz</surname>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Universidad de Alicante, España</affiliation>
                    <email>alex.sd2023@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Murrieta-Flores</surname>
                        <forename>Patricia</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Lancaster University, United Kingdom</affiliation>
                    <email>p.murrieta@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-03-29T17:09:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>Handwritten Text Recognition</term>
                    <term>New Spain</term>
                    <term>16th century</term>
                    <term>palaeography</term>
                    <term>machine learning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>artificial intelligence and machine learning</term>
                    <term>digital research infrastructures development and analysis</term>
                    <term>image processing and analysis</term>
                    <term>manuscripts description</term>
                    <term>representation</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>Archaeology</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Humanities computing</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                    <term>Match where technical expertise is helpful.</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <ref target="https://wp.lancs.ac.uk/newspainfleets/">New Spain Fleets project</ref> is an ongoing large research endeavour by an interdisciplinary team of archaeologists, historians and computer scientists to delve into the socioeconomic history of the former Spanish empire’s maritime trade. Leveraging Artificial Intelligence methods, we analyse a large historical corpus created in Spain and Mexico between the 16th and 17th centuries.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">A major challenge for accessing the information in these documents lies in their calligraphy, terminology, and conventions, which require years of specialised training for reading and analysis. This has limited historical research to relatively few scholars, maintaining most of our written heritage still “locked away” in archives.</p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Historical documents from the Spanish colonial era comprise a distinctive set of calligraphies, the most prominent being cortesana, redonda, procesal simple, itálica cursiva, procesal encadenada, and pseudorredonda. These types are found throughout the Spanish colonial archive, often presenting regional variations, particularly in documents created in Mexico 
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"i9ZHvW3n","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Murrieta-Flores et al., 2025)","plainCitation":"(Murrieta-Flores et al., 2025)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/12692394/items/28EENFVL"],"itemData":{"id":1,"type":"article-journal","container-title":"Journal Science and Technology of Archaeological Research","DOI":"https://doi.org/10.1080/20548923.2025.2484828","issue":"1","license":"All rights reserved","title":"Unlocking colonial records with Artificial Intelligence. Achieving the automated transcription of large-scale 16th and 17th-century Latin American historical collections.","volume":"11","author":[{"family":"Murrieta-Flores","given":"Patricia"},{"family":"Vega-Sánchez","given":"Rodrigo"},{"family":"Sánchez-Díaz","given":"Alexander"},{"family":"Cruz-Ríos","given":"Héctor Francisco"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2025"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Murrieta-Flores et al., 2025).
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR) models have been successfully developed for the automatic transcription of historical manuscripts, leveraging Convolutional Neural Networks 
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"BEyuAyrF","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Nockels et al., 2022; Ferro et al., 2023)","plainCitation":"(Nockels et al., 2022; Ferro et al., 2023)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1566,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/YZF4RZ6F"],"itemData":{"id":1566,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR) technology is now a mature machine learning tool, becoming integrated in the digitisation processes of libraries and archives, speeding up the transcription of primary sources and facilitating full text searching and analysis of historic texts at scale. However, research into how HTR is changing our information environment is scant. This paper presents a systematic literature review regarding how researchers are using one particular HTR platform, Transkribus, to indicate the domains where HTR is applied, the approach taken, and how the technology is understood. 381 papers from 2015 to 2020 were gathered from Google Scholar, Scopus, and Web of Science, then grouped and coded into categories using quantitative and qualitative approaches. Published research that mentions Transkribus is international and rapidly growing. Transkribus features primarily in archival and library science publications, while a long tail of broad and eclectic disciplines, including history, computer science, citizen science, law and education, demonstrate the wider applicability of the tool. The most common paper categories were humanities applications (67%), technological (25%), users (5%) and tutorials (3%). This paper presents the first overarching review of HTR as featured in published research, while also elucidating how HTR is affecting the information environment.","container-title":"Archival Science","DOI":"10.1007/s10502-022-09397-0","ISSN":"1573-7500","issue":"3","journalAbbreviation":"Arch Sci","language":"en","page":"367-392","source":"Springer Link","title":"Understanding the application of handwritten text recognition technology in heritage contexts: a systematic review of Transkribus in published research","title-short":"Understanding the application of handwritten text recognition technology in heritage contexts","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-022-09397-0","volume":"22","author":[{"family":"Nockels","given":"Joe"},{"family":"Gooding","given":"Paul"},{"family":"Ames","given":"Sarah"},{"family":"Terras","given":"Melissa"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2023",10,23]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2022",9,1]]}}},{"id":1673,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/MLP2BVXB"],"itemData":{"id":1673,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Preserving historical archival heritage involves not only physical measures to safeguard these valuable texts but also providing for their digital preservation. However, merely digitising manuscripts and codexes is not enough. A further step is needed: the digitalisation of their content, i.e. the verbatim transcription of scanned texts. This process enables the accurate preservation of their textual content, making it easier to search for information and conduct further analyses. With the help of artificial intelligence, particularly Deep Neural Networks (DNNs), automatic handwriting recognition can be performed. In this study, we employed a Convolutional Recurrent Neural Network (CRNN), an established type of DNN, to determine the minimum amount of labelled data required to automatically transcribe five different historical datasets that vary in language and time period. The results show that a Character Error Rate (CER) lower than 10% can be achieved with just a few hundred labelled text lines in almost all cases.","container-title":"The International Archives of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences","DOI":"10.5194/isprs-archives-XLVIII-M-2-2023-557-2023","ISSN":"1682-1750","language":"English","note":"event-title: 29th CIPA Symposium “Documenting, Understanding, Preserving Cultural Heritage. Humanities and Digital Technologies for Shaping the Future” - 25&ndash;30 June 2023, Florence, Italy\npublisher: Copernicus GmbH","page":"557-562","source":"Copernicus Online Journals","title":"AI-ASSISTED DIGITALISATION OF HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS","URL":"https://isprs-archives.copernicus.org/articles/XLVIII-M-2-2023/557/2023/","volume":"XLVIII-M-2-2023","author":[{"family":"Ferro","given":"S."},{"family":"Pelillo","given":"M."},{"family":"Traviglia","given":"A."}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",10,8]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023",6,24]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Nockels et al., 2022; Ferro et al., 2023) although most freely available models have been designed for Northern European languages, and few have only recently become available for Spanish 
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"g567zUMw","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Ball et al., 2021; Cu\\uc0\\u233{}llar, 2023b; Coss\\uc0\\u237{}o Olavide, 2023; Cu\\uc0\\u233{}llar, 2023a)","plainCitation":"(Ball et al., 2021; Cuéllar, 2023b; Cossío Olavide, 2023; Cuéllar, 2023a)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1658,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/5B6XM7VV"],"itemData":{"id":1658,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Samples of Charles V/ Carlos V’s handwriting \n\n\nIt is based upon the book: Rachael Ball and Geoffrey Parker (eds.), Cómo ser rey. Instrucciones del emperador Carlos V a su hijo Felipe. Mayo de 1543. Spanish-English bilingual edition; jointly published with the CSA and The Hispanic Society of America; 2014; ISBN 978-84-15245-45-2. You can find an HTR+-model in Transkribus as of 3 September 2021 named Carlos V/ Charles V – Early modern Spanish – 15th century (1543).\n\n\nThe samples below give an indication how the handwriting of Charles V looked like in 1543. These examples are provided with The Hispanic Society of America’s permission.","DOI":"10.5281/zenodo.5381739","language":"osp","note":"publisher: Zenodo","source":"Zenodo","title":"Sample of Charles V handwriting","URL":"https://zenodo.org/records/5381739","author":[{"family":"Ball","given":"Rachael"},{"family":"Parker","given":"Geoffrey"},{"family":"America","given":"The Hispanic Society","dropping-particle":"of"},{"family":"Romein","given":"Christel Annemieke"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",10,9]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2021",9,3]]}}},{"id":1620,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/25BEUMZJ"],"itemData":{"id":1620,"type":"software","medium":"Transkribus","title":"Coloso Español","URL":"app.transkribus.org","author":[{"family":"Cuéllar","given":"Álvaro"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023",7,18]]}}},{"id":1621,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/XQD6BX32"],"itemData":{"id":1621,"type":"article-journal","abstract":"Un elevado porcentaje de impresos y manuscritos teatrales del periodo aurisecular no ha sido nunca transcrito en un formato analógico ni, por supuesto, digital. Es imposible, por tanto, emplear estos documentos para realizar búsquedas de nuestro interés o para los valiosos análisis informáticos (estilometría, topic modelling, detección de sentimientos, etc.) que se están desarrollando en los últimos años. Gracias a la Inteligencia Artificial (Transkribus) y técnicas de HTR (Handwritten Text Recognition) he entrenado tres modelos, públicos ya para la comunidad investigadora, capaces de transcribir y modernizar ortográficamente estos documentos de forma automática con un alto grado de precisión: alrededor del 97% de acierto en impresos y 91% en manuscritos. A través de estos modelos he podido procesar unas 1.300 obras teatrales contenidas en impresos y manuscritos procedentes de numerosas bibliotecas, archivos y otras fuentes digitalizadas. Las transcripciones resultantes forman ahora parte del proyecto ETSO, del buscador TEXORO y, además de suponer un avanzado punto de partida para la edición cuidada de los textos, cuentan por sí mismas con la calidad suficiente para ser sometidas a análisis estilométricos, los cuales están arrojando atribuciones autoriales de interés.","container-title":"Hipogrifo. Revista de literatura y cultura del Siglo de Oro","DOI":"10.13035/H.2023.11.01.08","ISSN":"2328-1308","issue":"1","language":"es","license":"Derechos de autor 2023 Hipogrifo. Revista de literatura y cultura del Siglo de Oro","note":"number: 1","page":"101-115","source":"www.revistahipogrifo.com","title":"La Inteligencia Artificial al rescate del Siglo de Oro: transcripción y modernización automática de mil trescientos impresos y manuscritos teatrales","title-short":"La Inteligencia Artificial al rescate del Siglo de Oro","URL":"https://www.revistahipogrifo.com/index.php/hipogrifo/article/view/1262","volume":"11","author":[{"family":"Cuéllar","given":"Álvaro"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",1,24]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023"]]}}},{"id":1640,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5238213/items/DK2YFBAZ"],"itemData":{"id":1640,"type":"post-weblog","abstract":"The purpose of this outreach blog is to document the process of preparing a critical annotated edition of Sancho IV’s Lucidario using digital humanities. It also serves as a tool to promote the application of digital humanities tools for editing medieval texts and of textual criticism. What is the Lucidario? The Lucidario, written...","container-title":"Lucidarios","language":"es","title":"Lucidarios. Editando el <<Lucidario>> de Sancho IV","URL":"https://lucidarios.hypotheses.org/sobre-el-proyecto/about","author":[{"family":"Cossío Olavide","given":"Mario"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2024",12,20]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2023"]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Ball et al., 2021; Cuéllar, 2023b; Cossío Olavide, 2023; Cuéllar, 2023a). However, in our experience, the latter still do not yield accurate transcriptions, either because of being trained for specific sets of documents or too heterogeneous datasets with documents spanning several calligraphies and centuries. Large Spanish models available perform best with late (19th–20th century) documents, their accuracy greatly diminishing when working with earlier documents and “dirty” calligraphies such as procesal simple. To tackle these challenges, we trained specific models, carefully classifying the documents by calligraphy and generating a large sample of human transcription by specialist palaeographers.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Here, we describe advances and results in developing four accurate HTR models for the automatic transcription of 16th–17th-century Spanish calligraphies: Itálica cursiva, Procesal simple, Redonda, and Procesal encadenada.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We trained both HTR models using Transkribus. The workflow involved 1) the creation of a 170-document corpus classified by calligraphy; 2) uploading the digitised images of the historical documents, obtained from the archives’ websites or manual digitisation; 3) preparing the Ground Truth datasets; 4) training the models; 5) iterating until a Character Error Rate (CER) of &lt;10% on the validation sample was obtained; 6) preparing test datasets and performing accuracy tests. </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Ground Truth refers to the images and the corresponding accurate transcriptions on which a model will learn during training. All transcriptions were carried out manually by a group of palaeographers specialised in New Spain calligraphies. One team member prepared and another revised/corrected literal transcriptions, maintaining spelling, grammar, and punctuation as appeared in the originals, without expanding abbreviations.</p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Historical documents in the Ground Truth datasets (Table 1), currently held in major public archives from Mexico, France, Spain, and the USA, were originally produced in New Spain (today’s Mexico) or Spain between the 16th and 17th centuries. All were written in Spanish, although some contain words (e.g., toponyms) in their original indigenous language, mainly Nahuatl. We only included words in Spanish in the training datasets.</p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <anchor xml:id="Ref184563683"/>Table 1. Ground Truth datasets.
                </p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">
                            <hi rend="italic">Itálica cursiva (m3t1)</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">
                            <hi rend="italic">Procesal simple (m3t4)</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">
                            <p style="text-align: left; ">Redonda</p>
                            <p style="text-align: left; ">(m1t3)</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">
                            <hi rend="italic">Procesal encadenada (m2t2)</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">Documents</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">40</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">76</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">12</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">Number of pages</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">339</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">1,148</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">319</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">410</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">Number of lines</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">10,579</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">38,725</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">1,804</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">15,237</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">Number of words</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">106,046</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">258,503</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">21,860</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;" rend="DH-Default">111,807</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">One distinctive aspect of our workflow was adjusting line polygons to ensure they completely encapsulated the letters. Although it has been discussed elsewhere that this process might not always be necessary, this was particularly crucial for the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal simple</hi> calligraphy in which letters usually exceed line limits (Figure 1). We used the adjusted line polygons for training, but all other basic and advanced training settings were set to default in Transkribus (i.e., epochs=100, learning rate=0.0003, batch size=24). The Validation set comprised 10% of the Ground Truth sample.
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="4.266847222222222cm" url="/tmp/tmpee6lvse9/Pictures/c0462addf72d8d7eb8a4a9144ae59841.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <anchor xml:id="Ref184447912"/>Figure 1. Adjusting line polygons.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We performed accuracy tests for each HTR model using the Transkribus Compute Accuracy tool (Transkribus Expert Client v1.28.0), using documents not included in training or validation. The testing datasets included 60 pages (years 1554 to 1712) for the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Itálica cursiva</hi> model, 35 pages (1590-1608) for the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal simple</hi> model, 21 pages (1570-1580) for the 
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Redonda </hi>model, and 13 pages (1621) for the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal encadenada</hi> model.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Results</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Itálica cursiva</hi> model was trained on 97 documents from 1536 to 1717. Its first three iterations comprised relatively small datasets (&lt;82,000 words), not achieving the expected CER. The fourth iteration (Itálica_cursiva_m3t1) included over 106,000 words, achieving a CER=8.8% without a base model. Accuracy tests yielded a median CER=7.61% (IQR=13.23%) on the test sample. Text comparisons showed that most automatic transcriptions were accurate, and errors would be negligible to a trained reader (
                    <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>). Furthermore, a comparison with the largest freely available HTR model for Spanish (Coloso Español, CER=4.8%) showed that our model significantly outperforms the former (CER=23.70% ColEsp vs 15.97% ItalCur_m3t1).
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="16.002cm" height="9.017cm" url="/tmp/tmpee6lvse9/Pictures/b3abc46edd46730ecd9dad81d6b53d10.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">
                    <anchor xml:id="Ref184449965"/>Figure 2. Text comparison for an Italica cursiva HTR transcription.
                    <lb/>The test only highlights those words where Ground Truth (green) and HTR (red) differ.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal simple</hi> HTR model was trained on over 80 documents from 1512 to 1657, involving nine iterations. The last iteration (Procesal_simple_m3t4) included an accumulated sample of 258,503 words, achieving a CER=8.92%. Accuracy tests showed a median CER=16.72% (IQR=12.23%). This higher CER was affected by two factors. First, image resolution: low-resolution images from an archive’s website (≤1.24 MP, n=17) yielded significantly higher CERs than manually digitised images (8.41 MP, n=18) (median=26.04% vs 14.53%, p&lt;0.001, Figure 3). The negative effect of image resolution on model recognition accuracy has long been reported and continues to be an important challenge in character recognition 
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"ZJJMXZe3","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Jacobs et al., 2005; Baek et al., 2019; Wang et al., 2020)","plainCitation":"(Jacobs et al., 2005; Baek et al., 2019; Wang et al., 2020)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2123,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5680011/items/BJKLQUCB"],"itemData":{"id":2123,"type":"paper-conference","abstract":"Cheap and versatile cameras make it possible to easily and quickly capture a wide variety of documents. However, low resolution cameras present a challenge to OCR because it is virtually impossible to do character segmentation independently from recognition. In this paper we solve these problems simultaneously by applying methods borrowed from cursive handwriting recognition. To achieve maximum robustness, we use a machine learning approach based on a convolutional neural network. When our system is combined with a language model using dynamic programming, the overall performance is in the vicinity of 80-95% word accuracy on pages captured with a 1024x768 webcam and 10-point text.","collection-title":"ICDAR '05","container-title":"Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition","DOI":"10.1109/ICDAR.2005.233","event-place":"USA","ISBN":"978-0-7695-2420-7","page":"695–699","publisher":"IEEE Computer Society","publisher-place":"USA","source":"ACM Digital Library","title":"Text Recognition of Low-resolution Document Images","URL":"https://doi.org/10.1109/ICDAR.2005.233","author":[{"family":"Jacobs","given":"Charles"},{"family":"Simard","given":"Patrice Y."},{"family":"Viola","given":"Paul"},{"family":"Rinker","given":"James"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",4,30]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2005"]],"season":"Agosto"}}},{"id":1902,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5680011/items/5T6L49Q4"],"itemData":{"id":1902,"type":"article","abstract":"Many new proposals for scene text recognition (STR) models have been introduced in recent years. While each claim to have pushed the boundary of the technology, a holistic and fair comparison has been largely missing in the field due to the inconsistent choices of training and evaluation datasets. This paper addresses this difficulty with three major contributions. First, we examine the inconsistencies of training and evaluation datasets, and the performance gap results from inconsistencies. Second, we introduce a unified four-stage STR framework that most existing STR models fit into. Using this framework allows for the extensive evaluation of previously proposed STR modules and the discovery of previously unexplored module combinations. Third, we analyze the module-wise contributions to performance in terms of accuracy, speed, and memory demand, under one consistent set of training and evaluation datasets. Such analyses clean up the hindrance on the current comparisons to understand the performance gain of the existing modules.","DOI":"10.48550/arXiv.1904.01906","note":"arXiv:1904.01906","number":"arXiv:1904.01906","publisher":"arXiv","source":"arXiv.org","title":"What Is Wrong With Scene Text Recognition Model Comparisons? Dataset and Model Analysis","title-short":"What Is Wrong With Scene Text Recognition Model Comparisons?","URL":"http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.01906","author":[{"family":"Baek","given":"Jeonghun"},{"family":"Kim","given":"Geewook"},{"family":"Lee","given":"Junyeop"},{"family":"Park","given":"Sungrae"},{"family":"Han","given":"Dongyoon"},{"family":"Yun","given":"Sangdoo"},{"family":"Oh","given":"Seong Joon"},{"family":"Lee","given":"Hwalsuk"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",4,30]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019",12,18]]}}},{"id":1901,"uris":["http://zotero.org/groups/5680011/items/NN9F2XS4"],"itemData":{"id":1901,"type":"article","abstract":"Low-resolution text images are often seen in natural scenes such as documents captured by mobile phones. Recognizing low-resolution text images is challenging because they lose detailed content information, leading to poor recognition accuracy. An intuitive solution is to introduce super-resolution (SR) techniques as pre-processing. However, previous single image super-resolution (SISR) methods are trained on synthetic low-resolution images (e.g.Bicubic down-sampling), which is simple and not suitable for real low-resolution text recognition. To this end, we pro-pose a real scene text SR dataset, termed TextZoom. It contains paired real low-resolution and high-resolution images which are captured by cameras with different focal length in the wild. It is more authentic and challenging than synthetic data, as shown in Fig. 1. We argue improv-ing the recognition accuracy is the ultimate goal for Scene Text SR. In this purpose, a new Text Super-Resolution Network termed TSRN, with three novel modules is developed. (1) A sequential residual block is proposed to extract the sequential information of the text images. (2) A boundary-aware loss is designed to sharpen the character boundaries. (3) A central alignment module is proposed to relieve the misalignment problem in TextZoom. Extensive experiments on TextZoom demonstrate that our TSRN largely improves the recognition accuracy by over 13%of CRNN, and by nearly 9.0% of ASTER and MORAN compared to synthetic SR data. Furthermore, our TSRN clearly outperforms 7 state-of-the-art SR methods in boosting the recognition accuracy of LR images in TextZoom. For example, it outperforms LapSRN by over 5% and 8%on the recognition accuracy of ASTER and CRNN. Our results suggest that low-resolution text recognition in the wild is far from being solved, thus more research effort is needed.","DOI":"10.48550/arXiv.2005.03341","note":"arXiv:2005.03341","number":"arXiv:2005.03341","publisher":"arXiv","source":"arXiv.org","title":"Scene Text Image Super-Resolution in the Wild","URL":"http://arxiv.org/abs/2005.03341","author":[{"family":"Wang","given":"Wenjia"},{"family":"Xie","given":"Enze"},{"family":"Liu","given":"Xuebo"},{"family":"Wang","given":"Wenhai"},{"family":"Liang","given":"Ding"},{"family":"Shen","given":"Chunhua"},{"family":"Bai","given":"Xiang"}],"accessed":{"date-parts":[["2025",4,30]]},"issued":{"date-parts":[["2020",8,2]]}}}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Jacobs et al., 2005; Baek et al., 2019; Wang et al., 2020). Second, calligraphy “neatness”: A subset of documents with clearer calligraphy yielded even lower CERs than those in the validation sample (median=6.1%, IQR=2.04%).
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <anchor xml:id="Ref184447296"/>
                    <graphic n="1003" width="16.002cm" height="7.189611111111111cm" url="/tmp/tmpee6lvse9/Pictures/eb90093b9c3312e49713158e70cfb8ba.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">Figure 3. Impact of image resolution on the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal simple</hi> model accuracy.
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Redonda</hi> and 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal Encadenada</hi> models are our latest developments. The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Redonda</hi> model was trained on twelve documents from 1536 to 1576. Although it was a relatively small dataset, the homogeneity and clarity of this calligraphy style allowed the model to achieve a CER=5.25% when trained with the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal Simple</hi> as a base model. 
                </p>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">The 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal Encadenada</hi> model recognises a particularly challenging calligraphy. It required the preparation of a large training set by a group of expert palaeographers, comprising over 111,000 words in documents from 1590 to 1640. Leveraging the 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal Simple</hi> as base model, the model achieved a CER=7.80% on the validation set. Accuracy tests showed a median CER=18.17% (IQR=6.23%) on the testing set while also confirming its outperformance of the largest freely available model, Coloso Español, on this sample (CER=33.55%, IQR=6.94).
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="DH-Heading1">
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p style="text-align: left; ">We developed HTR models for 
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Itálica cursiva, Procesal simple, Redonda, </hi>and 
                    <hi rend="italic">Procesal encadenada</hi> calligraphies (CER=8.8%, 8.92%, 5.25%, and 7.80%, respectively), four of the most prevalent in 16
                    <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-17
                    <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century Spanish historical documents. The models provide sufficiently accurate transcriptions, allowing users to read the text fluidly, requiring minor corrections. Considering the significant effect of image quality on models’ accuracy, users and cultural heritage institutions should work with high-resolution images whenever possible. Our models will soon become publicly available as outputs of the New Spain Fleets project, allowing interested audiences to access vast amounts of historical information so far locked behind challenging Spanish American calligraphies.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Baek, Jeonghun / Kim, Geewook / Lee, Junyeop / Park, Sungrae / Han, Dongyoon / Yun, Sangdoo / Oh, Seong Joon / Lee, Hwalsuk. (2019). What Is Wrong With Scene Text Recognition Model Comparisons? Dataset and Model Analysis. (arXiv:1904.01906) 10.48550/arXiv.1904.01906.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Ball, Rachael / Parker, Geoffrey / The Hispanic Society of America / Romein, Christel Annemieke. (2021). Sample of Charles V handwriting. 10.5281/zenodo.5381739.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Cossío Olavide, Mario. (2023). Lucidarios. Editando el &lt;&lt;Lucidario&gt;&gt; de Sancho IV. Lucidarios. https://lucidarios.hypotheses.org/sobre-el-proyecto/about (accessed 20 December 2024).</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Cuéllar, Álvaro. (2023a). Coloso Español.app.transkribus.org.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Cuéllar, Álvaro. (2023b). La Inteligencia Artificial al rescate del Siglo de Oro: transcripción y modernización automática de mil trescientos impresos y manuscritos teatrales. Hipogrifo. Revista de literatura y cultura del Siglo de Oro, 11(1), pp. 101–15. 10.13035/H.2023.11.01.08.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Ferro, Sara / Pelillo, Marcello / Traviglia, Arianna. (2023). AI-ASSISTED DIGITALISATION OF HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS. The International Archives of the Photogrammetry, Remote Sensing and Spatial Information Sciences, XLVIII-M-2–2023, pp. 557–62. 10.5194/isprs-archives-XLVIII-M-2-2023-557-2023.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Jacobs, Charles / Simard, Patrice Y. / Viola, Paul / Rinker, James. (2005). Text Recognition of Low-Resolution Document Images. In Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition. ICDAR ’05. USA: IEEE Computer Society, pp. 695–9. 10.1109/ICDAR.2005.233.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Murrieta-Flores, Patricia / Vega-Sánchez, Rodrigo / Sánchez-Díaz, Alexander / Cruz-Ríos, Héctor Francisco. (2025). Unlocking Colonial Records with Artificial Intelligence. Achieving the Automated Transcription of Large-Scale 16th and 17th-Century Latin American Historical Collections. Journal Science and Technology of Archaeological Research, 11(1). https://doi.org/10.1080/20548923.2025.2484828.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Nockels, Joe / Gooding, Paul / Ames, Sarah / Terras, Melissa. (2022). Understanding the Application of Handwritten Text Recognition Technology in Heritage Contexts: A Systematic Review of Transkribus in Published Research. Archival Science, 22(3), pp. 367–92. 10.1007/s10502-022-09397-0.</bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">Wang, Wenjia / Xie, Enze / Liu, Xuebo / Wang, Wenhai / Liang, Ding / Shen, Chunhua / Bai, Xiang. (2020). Scene Text Image Super-Resolution in the Wild. (arXiv:2005.03341) 10.48550/arXiv.2005.03341.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
