<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="YUAN_Xinyi_Research_on_the_Construction_of_a_Digital_Narrati">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Research on the Construction of a Digital Narrative Model for Chinese Historical Classics</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Yuan</surname>
                        <forename>Xinyi</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Renmin University of China, China, People's Republic of</affiliation>
                    <email>yuanxinyi0707@ruc.edu.cn</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Yan</surname>
                        <forename>Chengxi</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Renmin University of China, China, People's Republic of</affiliation>
                    <email>20218113@ruc.edu.cn</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Yu</surname>
                        <forename>Min</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>Renmin University of China, China, People's Republic of</affiliation>
                    <email>yumin_fx@163.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2025-03-29T17:09:00Z</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <authority>Stichting ADHO Foundation</authority>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Oudezijds Achterburgwal 185, 1012DK</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Amsterdam</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Netherlands</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="DHCONVALIDATOR" version="1.22">
                    <label>DHConvalidator</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="category">
                    <term>Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Short Presentation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="keywords">
                    <term>digital narrative</term>
                    <term>Chinese historical classics</term>
                    <term>narrative model</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="ConfTool" n="topics">
                    <term>data modeling</term>
                    <term>digital libraries creation</term>
                    <term>management</term>
                    <term>and analysis</term>
                    <term>History</term>
                    <term>Library &amp; information science</term>
                    <term>I plan to attend the conference on-site in Lisbon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Introduction</p>
            <p>Chinese historical classics, situated within the History (Shi) category of the traditional bibliographic system Jing, Shi, Zi, Ji (Classics, History, Philosophy, and Literature), embody rich narrative traditions shaped by classical historiography. However, their linear and static formats fall short of digital-era expectations for interactivity, flexibility, and personalization.</p>
            <p>This study introduces a digital narrative model specifically designed for these texts. Drawing on digital narratology and Chinese historiographical principles, it analyzes narrative elements, structural formats, and interaction design. The model proposes flexible narrative pathways that address diverse user needs, offering a novel framework for digitally restructuring and engaging with historical knowledge.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Digital Narrative Models</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">A range of influential models inform the field of digital narratology. Ryan (2014) outlines multiple navigational forms—networks, vectors with side-branches, sea-anemone shapes, and mazes—supporting diverse plot curves. Carstensdottir et al. (2017) emphasize user interaction in game-based narratives via linear, branching, foldback, broom, and opportunistic structures. Koenitz et al. (2018) challenge Western-centric assumptions by incorporating non-Western narrative forms, such as etiological oral accounts and religious epics. Millard et al. (2013) propose a spatial model using metaphors like canyons, deltas, and plains to guide reader navigation. Basaraba (2018) highlights the feedback loop between creators and audiences in interactive digital narratives (IDNs) within cultural heritage contexts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Digital Narrative Model for Chinese Historical Classics</p>
            <p>In this model, the role of “narrator” is expanded to include both the historical author and the digital narrative designer. On the recipient side, narratees are divided into two main groups: professional researchers and the general public. These roles and relationships give rise to four narrative pathways: single-path, comparative, exploratory, and generative. Figure 1 illustrates the core structure of the model.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1001" width="10.741469444444444cm" height="6.041913888888889cm" url="/tmp/tmpruh9quxg/Pictures/56eb7d5b794221f12e1afdfad32c6dc5.png" rend="inline"/>
            </figure>
            <p style="text-align: center;">
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">Figure 1: Model Diagram</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The following sections will analyze and interpret each component of the model in detail.</p>
            <p>Narratives units and structure</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">As a vital component of China’s cultural heritage, historical classics exhibit unique narrative traditions shaped by longstanding historiographical practices. Their narrative construction centers on four fundamental elements: time, space, character, and event. Each corresponds to a classical Chinese historiographic format: bian nian ti (Annals), guo bie ti (Regional Chronicles), ji zhuan ti (Biographies), and jishi benmo ti (Event-based Narratives). This study analyzes the structural features and constituent units of each, laying the groundwork for a digital model tailored to historical texts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Interactive architecture</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">Interactivity distinguishes digital narratives from traditional forms, placing interaction design at the heart of the user experience (Carstensdottir et al. 2019). Building on established models, this study integrates interactive structures with the narrative features of Chinese historical classics.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The model incorporates five types of interactive architecture:</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">Linear: A single, fixed path where narrative elements unfold sequentially (Carstensdottir et al. 2017).</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Branching: A tree-like structure that enables divergent narrative paths based on user decisions.</p>
            <p>Network: A loop-enabled format where choices influence narrative progression.</p>
            <p>Vector with Side-Branches: A forward-moving path with optional digressions to supplementary content (Ryan 2014).</p>
            <p>Track-Switching: Allows movement across different narrative threads at defined nodes, mirroring the four classical narrative structures.</p>
            <p>This framework, designed by the narrative architect, is adapted based on content, user needs, and the desired balance of coherence and flexibility.</p>
            <p>Multidimensional Narrative Pathways</p>
            <p>Digital narrative scholarship increasingly prioritizes user-centered design, emphasizing the narratee’s role in shaping narrative progression. In the proposed model, narratees are grouped into professional researchers and the general public. To meet their differing needs, the model defines four narrative pathways:</p>
            <p>Single-path Narrative: A fixed structure authored by the original historian, uniformly addressing all users.</p>
            <p>Comparative Narrative: Designed for scholarly use, juxtaposes multiple elements for analytical comparison.</p>
            <p>Exploratory Narrative: Offers nonlinear, cross-linked content for personalized, associative exploration.</p>
            <p>Generative Narrative: Goes beyond the original text via creative expansion. Through technologies like AI and VR, designers and users co-create immersive, participatory narratives.</p>
            <p>Together, these narrative modes foster flexible engagement with historical texts, aligned with diverse user intents and interactive preferences.</p>
            <p>Conclusion</p>
            <p>The proposed digital narrative model offers a conceptual foundation for reimagining Chinese historical classics in digital contexts. It supports deeper content exploration, enriches public cultural engagement, and opens new directions for digital humanities scholarship. While still theoretical, future work will focus on implementation, empirical evaluation, and iterative refinement.</p>
            <p>Acknowledgement</p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:10pt">This study is supported by the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities, and the Research Funds of Renmin University of China (No. 24XNF043). The corresponding author is Chengxi Yan (ORCID: 0000-0003-1128-550X, Email: 20218113@ruc.edu.cn).</hi>
            </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliogr">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Basaraba, Nicole</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2018): “A Communication Model for Non-Fiction Interactive Digital Narratives: A Study of Cultural Heritage Websites”, in: Frontiers of Narrative Studies 4: s48–s75.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Carstensdottir, Elin / Kleinman, Erica / El-Nasr, Magy Seif</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2017): “Towards an Interaction Model for Interactive Narratives”, in: Lecture Notes in Computer Science 10690, 1: 274–277.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Carstensdottir, Elin / Kleinman, Erica / El-Nasr, Magy Seif</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2019): “Player Interaction in Narrative Games: Structure and Narrative Progression Mechanics”, in: FDG '19: Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Harrison, Nicole (n.d.)</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">: Interaction, Virtuality, and Heavy Rain: An Exploration of Character and Interactive Narrative. Unpublished dissertation.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Koenitz, Hartmut / Di Pastena, Andrea / Jansen, Dennis / et al.</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2018): “The Myth of ‘Universal’ Narrative Models: Expanding the Design Space of Narrative Structures for Interactive Digital Narratives”, in: Lecture Notes in Computer Science 11318: 107–120.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Li, Jianzhong (<hi rend="Chinese">李建中</hi>) </hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">(2023): The Classical Paradigms of Study on the Keywords of Jing Shi Zi Ji and Literary Theory [《<hi rend="Chinese">经史子集关键词与文论研究的经典范式》</hi>], in: Jiangxi Social Sciences (<hi rend="Chinese">江西社会科学</hi>) 43, 5: 35–45, 206–207, 2.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Millard, David / Hargood, Charlie / Jewell, Michael O. / Weal, Mark J</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt">. (2013): “Canyons, Deltas and Plains: Towards a Unified Sculptural Model of Location-Based Hypertext”, in: HT '13: Proceedings of the 24th ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ryan, Marie-Laure</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2014): Avatars of Story. Nanjing: Yilin Press.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl style="text-align: left; ">
                        <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Szilas, Nicolas</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (2003): “IDtension: A Narrative Engine for Interactive Drama”, in: Göbel, Stefan et al. (eds.): Proceedings of the Technologies for Interactive Digital Storytelling and Entertainment (TIDSE) Conference. Frauenhofer IRB Verlag: 187–203.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
